教授：上次Gerry教授揭晓了秘密
他介绍了赋值的概念
赋值与状态
正如我们所见，语言引入了赋值与状态，其含义是相当令人惊骇的
首先，计算的代换模型失效了
我们不得不使用更为复杂的环境模型和这种带图解的机械性的东西，甚至还要讲解声明编程语言中意味着什么
这不仅仅是技术上的一点
看，代换模型在这里完全失效了，我们得想些其它办法
代换模型什么都做不了
因为突然地，一个变量不仅仅代表着一个值了
变量现在用来指定一个存放值的位置
并且在这个位置的值是可以变的
比如像 (f x) 这个表达式就可能有副作用
如果我们执行(f x)得到某些值，之后我们再次执行(f x)，可能因为执行顺序的关系而得到不同的值
所以突然间，我们不能仅仅关注于值，也要开始关注时间
序对也不仅仅只是CAR和CDR了
序对不仅是它的CAR和CDR，更是它的“同一”
所以一个序对有“同一”
它是一个对象
两个CAR与CDR相同的序对可能相同也可能不同，因为我们必须关注“共享”
一引入赋值。这些都变成要考虑的问题了
确实，这和我们说讲代换的时候差别悬殊
技术角度来看，我们必须相加机械的思考程序语言，因此看待事情也变得更加困难
我们还不能仅仅用数学的方式来思考
哲学上也很难理解，什么是事物的改变？两个事物是否相同？我们突然要开始思考这类问题
并且，编程也更加困难，正如Gerry上次演示的，会有很多由于别名与顺序引发的bug，对于不考虑对象的语言，这些问题是绝对不会出现的
我们是怎样陷入这样的困境的呢？
想想我们之前所做的，原因就在于我们想要构造模块化的系统，而且这些模块的划分是很自然的
举例来说，我们构造一个随机数生成器并打包生成器的状态，所以我们可以把求随机数的计算过程与蒙特卡罗方法相分离，与那个用随机数求Pi的计算过程相分离
相似地，如果我们动身去构建一个现实世界的模型，我们就想要程序自然的分成很多部分，每一部分各自代表着我们在现实世界所看到的事物
举个例子，看到一个电子电路，我们可能会说，哇，这有一个电路板，它有一个这样的元件，有一个那样的元件
这些元件在某种程度上都有“同一”
它们都有各自的状态
状态附着在电路上
我们把这个元件看作一个不同于其它对象的对象
当系统发生变化，我们想着，信号从这里过来，可能在这里改变了一个状态，信号又到了那里，和一个存储在那里的状态相互作用，等等
所以我们在做的是构建一个如实映射现实的电脑系统，每一部分都与现实的某一部分相对应，用这样的方法来构建的话，系统便很容易的分成模块
这样来构造系统的原因是想说明
介绍如此复杂的技术与计算机本身没有什么关系
看到了吧，我们付出了这么大的代价来编写映射现实世界的程序，却因为我们错误的认知现实而失败
或许时间只是错觉，什么都没有改变
举例来说，我拿起这个粉笔，我们会想，哦，这是一个对象，它有自己的状态
每时每刻，它都有一个位置与速度
如果我们做点什么，就可以改变它的状态
但是你如果了解一点相对性的概念，你可能不会认为粉笔的路径是某种东西随着时间运动而形成的
把整个粉笔的存在认为是时空中的路径，这是很有洞察力的
全部都展开了
没有单独的位置与速度
只有在时空中不变的存在
相似地，如果我们想象这些电子系统是一个信号处理系统，组合这个系统的工程师可不会这样想，“哦，每个瞬间有一个电压过来，
转换成了某种东西，
影响了这里的状态，还改变了那里的状态”
没有一个做信号处理的会这样想
相反，你说这里有一个在时间上伸展的信号
如果有一个滤波器，就会把整个信号变成整个完全不同的输出信号
你不必考虑在某个时间点上事物的状态
以某种方式，把这个盒子作为完整的东西，而不是在某些个特定时间的状态的集合
好的，今天我们就从信号处理工程师的角度而不是之前以对象思考的角度来分解系统
它被称为“流处理”
我们打算展示如何使那些对时间过度关注的程序更具统一性，而且可以从中看到很多的共性
我们来对比这两个过程
第一个是这样
想像这有一个树
一个自然数的树
还是一个二叉树
看起来就像这样
在每个结点上都有一个数
我们想计算的是，对这个树中所有的奇数，计算它们的平方和
看起来很熟悉
这里我们用递归的方式来计算
观察每个叶子结点，如果是奇数我们求它的平方，如果是偶数我们不需要，也就是0
递归求解，我们知道 一棵树的解 = 左子树的解 + 右子树的解，就这样递归下去
这种思考方式我们已经很熟悉了
我们来看看幻灯片
计算一棵树的奇数平方和，这里有一个判断，是否是一个叶子结点，断而判断是否是一个奇数，然后我们计算它的平方，否则就取0
然后，整个的解就是左、右子树解的总和
好的，现在我们对比第二个问题
假如给你一个整数n，还有一些函数来计算每一个从1到n的数
然后我想把那些所有满足特定属性的值收集到一个列表中
这是一个广泛的概述
说的更具体一点，假如对于每个整数k，计算第k个斐波那契数
然后挑出其中的奇数并把它们放入一个列表
这个过程是这样的
寻找n个斐波那契数中的奇数
这里是一个循环的标准写法
一个递归
一个循环，参数是k，如果k大于n，返回空列表；否则计算第k个斐波那契数，称它为f
如果是奇数，我们把它与从k+1计算得到的列表相连接
否则，我们只取从k+1计算得到的结果
这是迭代式循环的标准写法
我们以1为参数开始这个循环
好的，这就是这两个过程
直观来看，它们两个没有什么共同点
结构完全不同
但是从一个特定的角度来看，两个过程做的事情是一样的
如果我是一个信号处理工程师，我可能会说，第一个过程枚举了树叶结点
可以认为是一个全部是树叶结点的信号从这里输出
然后把信号导入某个过滤器，过滤出其中的奇数
通过这样的一个变换器
对每一个输出，我们对其取平方
最后把结果累积在一起
我们通过从0开始的加法来累计它们
这是第一个程序
第二个程序，也可以用一个非常非常相似的方法来描述
枚举了从1到n的所有整数
对于每个数，计算斐波那契数，通过一个转换器
对于输出的结果，再通过奇偶性进行过滤
最后，我们将这些放入累积器
这里我们累积出一个列表，传递CONS方法，与空列表作为参数
从这个角度来看，这两个程序真的是太相似了
问题在于两个程序的写法导致我们看不出其中的共性
我们回头再来看第一个奇数平方和的问题，问题来了，枚举器是什么？
程序中哪一部分有枚举的作用？
枚举不是仅仅在一个地方表现出来的
在叶子结点的判断处存在一部分
也下面的递归结构中也有体现
累积器又在哪儿呢？
和枚举器类似，也不是在一个地方
它由 0 和 + 这两个地方体现出来
累积器的完整过程并不体在唯一一个地方
相似地，我们来观察奇数斐波那契数的例子，程序中也存在枚举器与累积器的含义，但是有些不同
枚举的含义部分的表现在 ( > k n) 的判断中，部分的表现在下面的递归调用中
同样地，累积的含义也被混杂在其中，比如在这里和那里
我们之前所画出的盒子在我们的程序中完全看不出来，因为它们混杂在一起了
因此，这些程序并没有很好的对问题进行划分
回到计算机科学的基本原理上来，为了控制某种东西，你需要给它命名，即使我们如此思考，我们也并没有完全地控制住它，因为我们没有明确地深入它的内部
我们没有一个好的语言来说明
好吧，我们来发明合适的语言来构造这些部分
这种语言的关键在于 这些叫作信号的东西到底是什么？
这些沿着箭头传递的又是什么？
直接说明吧，这些东西将变成一种叫做流的数据结构，也是发明这个语言的关键
什么是流呢？
流，和其它的相似，是一种数据抽象
所以，我先说明它的选择器与构造器分别是什么
构造器我们称其为CONS-stream
CONS-stream把两个事物放在一起构造出一个流
选择器叫作HEAD，用于从流中提取数据
可以提取head，也要可以提取tail
我把我和George的约定告诉你，是想让你明确到底是什么相关的法则
对于任何的x与y，(HEAD (CONS-STREAM x y)) => x，(TAIL (CONS-STREAM)) => y
一个构造函数，两个选择函数，一个法则，就是这些
这里有点可疑
你可能注意到了这完全和CONS，CAR，CDR序对相关的法则完全一样啊，把CONS-STREAM换成CONS，HEAD换成CAR，TAIL换成CDR，就完全一样了
事实上，还有另一个东西
我们有一个叫空流的东西，像空列表
为什么我要介绍这个术语呢？
为什么我不直接说序对与列表呢？
好吧，我们将会看到
暂时地，如果你喜欢，为什么不把流假装作列表的另一种术语
一会儿我们就知道了为什么我们需要这样的抽象而不是仅仅把它叫做列表
OK, now that we have streams, we can start constructing the pieces of the language to operate on streams. And there are a whole bunch of very useful things that we could start making.
For instance, we'll make our map box to take a stream, s, and a procedure, and to generate a new stream which has as its elements the procedure applied to all the successive elements of s.
In fact, we've seen this before.
This is the procedure map that we did with lists.
And you see it's exactly map, except we're testing for empty-stream.
Oh, I forgot to mention that.
Empty-stream is like the null test. So if it's empty, we generate the empty stream.
Otherwise, we form a new stream whose first element is the procedure applied to the head of the stream, and whose rest is gotten by mapping along with the procedure down the tail of the stream.
So that looks exactly like the map procedure we looked at before.
Here's another useful thing.
Filter, this is our filter box.
We're going to have a predicate and a stream.
We're going to make a new stream that consists of all the elements of the original one that satisfy the predicate.
That's case analysis.
When there's nothing in the stream, we return the empty stream.
We test the predicate on the head of the stream.
And if it's true, we add the head of the stream onto the result of filtering the tail of the stream.
And otherwise, if that predicate was false, we just filter the tail of the stream.
Right, so there's filter.
Let me run through a couple more rather quickly.
They're all in the book and you can look at them.
Let me just flash through.
Here's accumulate.
Accumulate takes a way of combining things and an initial value in a stream and sticks them all together.
If the stream's empty, it's just the initial value.
Otherwise, we combine the head of the stream with the result of accumulating the tail of the stream starting from the initial value.
So that's what I'd use to add up everything in the stream.
I'd accumulate with plus.
How would I enumerate the leaves of a tree?
Well, if the tree is just a leaf itself, I make something which only has that node in it.
Otherwise, I append together the stuff of enumerating the left branch and the right branch.
And then append here is like the ordinary append on lists.
You can look at that.
That's analogous to the ordinary procedure for appending two lists.
How would I enumerate an interval?
This will take two integers, low and high, and generate a stream of the integers going from low to high.
And we can make a whole bunch of pieces.
So that's a little language of talking about streams. Once we have streams, we can build things for manipulating them.
Again, we're making a language.
And now we can start expressing things in this language.
Here's our original procedure for summing the odd squares in a tree.
And you'll notice it looks exactly now like the block diagram, like the signal processing block diagram.
So to sum the odd squares in a tree, we enumerate the leaves of the tree.
We filter that for oddness.
We map that for squareness.
And we accumulate the result of that using addition, starting from 0.
So we can see the pieces that we wanted.
Similarly, the Fibonacci one, how do we get the odd Fibs?
Well, we enumerate the interval from 1 to n, we map along that, computing the Fibonacci of each one.
We filter the result of those for oddness.
And we accumulate all of that stuff using CONS starting from the empty-list.
OK, what's the advantage of this?
Well, for one thing, we now have pieces that we can start mixing and matching.
So for instance, if I wanted to change this, if I wanted to compute the squares of the integers and then filter them, all I need to do is pick up a standard piece like this in that square and put it in.
Or if we wanted to do this whole Fibonacci computation on the leaves of a tree rather than a sequence, all I need to do is replace this enumerator with that one.
See, the advantage of this stream processing is that we're establishing-- this is one of the big themes of the course-- we're establishing conventional interfaces that allow us to glue things together.
Things like map and filter are a standard set of components that we can start using for pasting together programs in all sorts of ways.
It allows us to see the commonality of programs.
I just ought to mention, I've only showed you two procedures.
But let me emphasize that this way of putting things together with maps, filters, and accumulators is very, very general.
It's the generate and test paradigm for programs. And as an example of that, Richard Waters, who was at MIT when he was a graduate student, as part of his thesis research went and analyzed a large chunk of the IBM scientific subroutine library, and discovered that about 60% of the programs in it could be expressed exactly in terms using no more than what we've put here-- map, filter, and accumulate.
All right, let's take a break.
Questions?
AUDIENCE: It seems like the essence of this whole thing is just that you have a very uniform, simple data structure to work with, the stream.
PROFESSOR: Right.
The essence is that you, again, it's this sense of conventional interfaces.
So you can start putting a lot of things together.
And the stream is as you say, the uniform data structure that supports that.
This is very much like APL, by the way.
APL is very much the same idea, except in APL, instead of this stream, you have arrays and vectors.
And a lot of the power of APL is exactly the same reason of the power of this.
OK, thank you.
Let's take a break.
All right.
We've been looking at ways of organizing computations using streams. What I want to do now is just show you two somewhat more complicated examples of that.
Let's start by thinking about the following kind of utility procedure that will come in useful.
Suppose I've got a stream.
And the elements of this stream are themselves streams.
So the first thing might be 1, 2, 3.
So I've got a stream.
And each element of the stream is itself a stream.
And what I'd like to do is build a stream that collects together all of the elements, pulls all of the elements out of these sub-streams and strings them all together in one thing.
So just to show you the use of this language, how easy it is, call that flatten.
And I can define to flatten this stream of streams. Well, what is that?
That's just an accumulation.
I want to accumulate using append, by successively appending.
So I accumulate using append streams, starting with the-empty-stream down that stream of streams.
OK, so there's an example of how you can start using these higher order things to do some interesting operations.
In fact, there's another useful thing that I want to do.
I want to define a procedure called flat-map, flat map of some function and a stream.
And what this is going to do is f will be a stream of elements.
f is going to be a function that for each element in the stream produces another stream.
And what I want to do is take all of the elements and all of those streams and combine them together.
So that's just going to be the flatten of map f down s.
Each time I apply f to an element of s, I get a stream.
If I map it all the way down, I get a stream of streams, and I'll flatten that.
Well, I want to use that to show you a new way to do a familiar kind of problem.
The problem's going to be like a lot of problems you've seen, although maybe not this particular one.
I'm going to give you an integer, n.
And the problem is going to be find all pairs and integers i and j, between 0 and i, with j less than i, up to n, such that i plus j is prime.
So for example, if n equals 6, let's make a little table here, i and j and i plus j.
So for, say, i equals 2 and j equals 1, I'd get 3.
And for i equals 3, I could have j equals 2, and that would be 5.
And 4 and 1 would be 5 and so on, up until i goes to 6.
And what I'd like to return is to produce a stream of all the triples like this, let's say i, j, and i plus j.
So for each n, I want to generate this stream.
OK, well, that's easy.
Let's build it up.
We start like this.
We're going to say for each i, we're going to generate a stream.
For each i in the interval 1 through n, we're going to generate a stream.
What's that stream going to be?
We're going to start by generating all the pairs.
So for each i, we're going to generate, for each j in the interval 1 to i minus 1, we'll generate the pair, or the list with two elements i and j.
So we map along the interval, generating the pairs.
And for each i, that generates a stream of pairs.
And we flatmap it.
Now we have all the pairs i and j, such that i is less than j.
So that builds that.
Now we're got to test them.
Well, we take that thing we just built, the flatmap, and we filter it to see whether the i-- see, we had an i and a j.
i was the first thing in the list, j was the second thing in the list. So we have a predicate which says in that list of two elements is the sum of the CAR and the CDR prime.
And we filter that collection of pairs we just built.
So those are the pairs we want.
Now we go ahead and we take the result of that filter and we map along it, generating the list i and j and i plus j.
And that's our procedure prime-sum-pairs.
And then just to flash it up, here's the whole procedure.
A map, a filter, a flatmap.
There's the whole thing, even though this isn't particularly readable.
It's just expanding that flatmap.
So there's an example which illustrates the general point that nested loops in this procedure start looking like compositions of flatmaps of flatmaps of flatmaps of maps and things.
So not only can we enumerate individual things, but by using flatmaps, we can do what would correspond to nested loops in most other languages.
Of course, it's pretty awful to keep writing these flatmaps of flatmaps of flatmaps.
Prime-sum-pairs you saw looked fairly complicated, even though the individual pieces were easy.
So what you can do, if you like, is introduced some syntactic sugar that's called collect.
And collect is just an abbreviation for that nest of flatmaps and filters arranged in that particular way.
Here's prime-sum-pairs again, written using collect.
It says to find all those pairs, I'm going to collect together a result, which is the list i, j, and i plus j, that's going to be generated as i runs through the interval from 1 to n and as j runs through the interval from 1 to i minus 1, such that i plus j is prime.
So I'm not going to say what collect does in general.
You can look at that by looking at it in the book.
But pretty much, you can see that the pieces of this are the pieces of that original procedure I wrote.
And this collect is just some syntactic sugar for automatically generating that nest of flatmaps and flatmaps.
OK, well, let me do one more example that shows you the same kind of thing.
Here's a very famous problem that's used to illustrate a lot of so-called backtracking computer algorithms. This is the eight queens problem.
This is a chess board.
And the eight queens problem says, find a way to put down eight queens on a chess board so that no two are attacking each other.
And here's a particular solution to the eight queens problem.
So I have to make sure to put down queens so that no two are in the same row or the same column or sit along the same diagonal.
Now, there's sort of a standard way of doing that.
Well, first we need to do is below the surface, at George's level.
We have to find some way to represent a board, and represent positions.
And we'll not worry about that.
But let's assume that there's a predicate called safe.
And what safe is going to do is going to say given that I have a bunch of queens down on the chess board, is it OK to put a queen in this particular spot?
So safe is going to take a row and a column.
That's going to be a place where I'm going to try and put down the next queen, and the rest of positions.
And what safe will say is given that I already have queens down in these positions, is it safe to put another queen down in that row and that column?
And let's not worry about that.
That's George's problem. and it's not hard to write.
You just have to check whether this thing contains any things on that row or that column or in that diagonal.
Now, how would you organize the program given that?
And there's sort of a traditional way to organize it called backtracking.
And it says, well, let's think about all the ways of putting the first queen down in the first column.
There are eight ways.
Well, let's say try the first column.
Try column 1, row 1.
These branches are going to represent the possibilities at each level.
So I'll try and put a queen down in the first column.
And now given that it's in the first column, I'll try and put the next queen down in the first column.
I'll try and put the first queen, the one in the first column, down in the first row.
I'm sorry.
And then given that, we'll put the next queen down in the first row.
And that's no good.
So I'll back up to here.
And I'll say, oh, can I put the first queen down in the second row?
Well, that's no good.
Oh, can I put it down in the third row?
Well, that's good.
Well, now can I put the next queen down in the first column?
Well, I can't visualize this chess board anymore, but I think that's right.
And I try the next one.
And at each place, I go as far down this tree as I can.
And I back up.
If I get down to here and find no possibilities below there, I back all the way up to here, and now start again generating this sub-tree.
And I sort of walk around.
And finally, if I ever manage to get all the way down, I've found a solution.
So that's a typical sort of paradigm that's used a lot in AI programming.
It's called backtracking search.
And it's really unnecessary.
You saw me get confused when I was visualizing this thing.
And you see the complication.
This is a complicated thing to say.
Why is it complicated?
Its because somehow this program is too inordinately concerned with time.
It's too much-- I try this one, and I try this one, and I go back to the last possibility.
And that's a complicated thing.
If I stop worrying about time so much, then there's a much simpler way to describe this.
It says, let's imagine that I have in my hands the tree down to k minus 1 levels.
See, suppose I had in my hands all possible ways to put down queens in the first k columns.
Suppose I just had that.
Let's not worry about how we get it.
Well, then, how do I extend that?
How do I find all possible ways to put down queens in the next column?
It's really easy.
For each of these positions I have, I think about putting down a queen in each row to make the next thing.
And then for each one I put down, I filter those by the ones that are safe.
So instead of thinking about this tree as generated step by step, suppose I had it all there.
And to extend it from level k minus 1 to level k, I just need to extend each thing in all possible ways and only keep the ones that are safe.
And that will give me the tree to level k.
And that's a recursive strategy for solving the eight queens problem.
All right, well, let's look at it.
To solve the eight queens problem on a board of some specified size, we write a sub-procedure called fill-columns.
Fill-columns is going to put down queens up through column k.
And here's the pattern of the recursion.
I'm going to call fill-columns with the size eventually.
So fill-columns says how to put down queens safely in the first k columns of this chess board with a size number of rows in it.
If k is equal to 0, well, then I don't have to put anything down.
So my solution is just an empty chess board.
Otherwise, I'm going to do some stuff.
And I'm going to use collect.
And here's the collect.
I find all ways to put down queens in the first k minus 1 columns.
And this was just what I set for.
Imagine I have this tree down to k minus 1 levels.
And then I find all ways of trying a row, that's just each of the possible rows.
They're size rows, so that's enumerate interval.
And now what I do is I collect together the new row I'm going to try and column k with the rest of the queens.
I adjoin a position.
This is George's problem.
An adjoined position is like safe.
It's a thing that takes a row and a column and the rest of the positions and makes a new position collection.
So I adjoin a position of a new row and a new column to the rest of the queens, where the rest of the queens runs through all possible ways of solving the problem in k minus 1 columns.
And the new row runs through all possible rows such that it was safe to put one there.
And that's the whole program.
There's the whole procedure.
Not only that, that doesn't just solve the eight queens problem, it gives you all solutions to the eight queens problem.
When you're done, you have a stream.
And the elements of that stream are all possible ways of solving that problem.
Why is that simpler?
Well, we threw away the whole idea that this is some process that happens in time with state.
And we just said it's a whole collection of stuff.
And that's why it's simpler.
We've changed our view.
Remember, that's where we started today.
We've changed our view of what it is we're trying to model.
we stop modeling things that evolve in time and have steps and have state.
And instead, we're trying to model this global thing like the whole flight of the chalk, rather than its state at each instant.
Any questions?
AUDIENCE: It looks to me like backtracking would be searching for the first solution it can find, whereas this recursive search would be looking for all solutions.
And it seems that if you have a large enough area to search, that the second is going to become impossible.
PROFESSOR: OK, the answer to that question is the whole rest of this lecture.
It's exactly the right question.
And without trying to anticipate the lecture too much, you should start being suspicious at this point, and exactly those kinds of suspicions.
It's wonderful, but isn't it so terribly inefficient?
That's where we're going.
So I won't answer now, but I'll answer later.
OK, let's take a break.
Well, by now you should be starting to get suspicious.
See, I've showed your this simple, elegant way of putting programs together, very unlike these other traditional programs that sum the odd squares or compute the odd Fibonacci numbers.
Very unlike these programs that mix up the enumerator and the filter and the accumulator.
And by mixing it up, we don't have all of these wonderful conceptual advantages of these streams pieces, these wonderful mix and match components for putting together lots and lots of programs.
On the other hand, most of the programs you've seen look like these ugly ones.
Why's that?
Can it possibly be that computer scientists are so obtuse that they don't notice that if you'd merely did this thing, then you can get this great programming elegance?
There's got to be a catch.
And it's actually pretty easy to see what the catch is.
Let's think about the following problem.
Suppose I tell you to find the second prime between 10,000 and 1 million, or if your computer's larger, say between 10,000 and 100 billion, or something.
And you say, oh, that's easy.
I can do that with a stream.
All I do is I enumerate the interval from 10,000 to 1 million.
So I get all those integers from 10,000 to 1 million.
I filter them for prime-ness, so test all of them and see if they're prime.
And I take the second element.
That's the head of the tail.
Well, that's clearly pretty ridiculous.
We'd not even have room in the machine to store the integers in the first place, much less to test them.
And then I only want the second one.
See, the power of this traditional programming style is exactly its weakness, that we're mixing up the enumerating and the testing and the accumulating.
So we don't do it all.
So the very thing that makes it conceptually ugly is the very thing that makes it efficient.
It's this mixing up.
So it seems that all I've done this morning so far is just confuse you.
I showed you this wonderful way that programming might work, except that it doesn't.
Well, here's where the wonderful thing happens.
It turns out in this game that we really can have our cake and eat it too.
And what I mean by that is that we really can write stream programs exactly like the ones I wrote and arrange things so that when the machine actually runs, it's as efficient as running this traditional programming style that mixes up the generation and the test.
Well, that sounds pretty magic.
The key to this is that streams are not lists.
We'll see this carefully in a second, but for now, let's take a look at that slide again.
The image you should have here of this signal processing system is that what's going to happen is there's this box that has the integers sitting in it.
And there's this filter that's connected to it and it's tugging on them.
And then there's someone who's tugging on this stuff saying what comes out of the filter.
And the image you should have is that someone says, well, what's the first prime, and tugs on this filter.
And the filter tugs on the integers.
And you look only at that much, and then say, oh, I really wanted the second one.
What's the second prime?
And that no computation gets done except when you tug on these things.
Let me try that again.
This is a little device.
This is a little stream machine invented by Eric Grimson who's been teaching this course at MIT.
And the image is here's a stream of stuff, like a whole bunch of the integers.
And here's some processing elements.
And if, say, it's filter of filter of map, or something.
And if I really tried to implement that with streams as lists, what I'd say is, well, I've got this list of things, and now I do the first filter.
So do all this processing.
And I take this and I process and I process and I process and I process.
And now I'm got this new stream.
Now I take that result in my hand someplace.
And I put that through the second one.
And I process the whole thing.
And there's this new stream.
And then I take the result and I put it all the way through this one the same way.
That's what would happen to these stream programs if streams were just lists.
But in fact, streams aren't lists, they're streams. And the image you should have is something a little bit more like this.
I've got these gadgets connected up by this data that's flowing out of them.
And here's my original source of the streams. It might be starting to generate the integers.
And now, what happens if I want a result?
I tug on the end here.
And this element says, gee, I need some more data.
So this one comes here and tugs on that one.
And it says, gee, I need some more data.
And this one tugs on this thing, which might be a filter, and says, gee, I need some more data.
And only as much of this thing at the end here gets generated as I tugged.
And only as much of this stuff goes through the processing units as I'm pulling on the end I need.
That's the image you should have of the difference between implementing what we're actually going to do and if streams were lists.
Well, how do we make this thing?
I hope you have the image.
The trick is how to make it.
We want to arrange for a stream to be a data structure that computes itself incrementally, an on-demand data structure.
And the basic idea is, again, one of the very basic ideas that we're seeing throughout the whole course.
And that is that there's not a firm distinction between programs and data.
So what a stream is going to be is simultaneously this data structure that you think of, like the stream of the leaves of this tree.
But at the same time, it's going to be a very clever procedure that has the method of computing in it.
Well, let me try this.
It's going to turn out that we don't need any more mechanism.
We already have everything we need simply from the fact that we know how to handle procedures as first-class objects.
Well, let's go back to the key.
The key is, remember, we had these operations.
CONS-stream and head and tail.
When I started, I said you can think about this as CONS and think about this as CAR and think about that as CDR, but it's not.
Now, let's look at what they really are.
Well, CONS-stream of x and y is going to be an abbreviation for the following thing.
CONS form a pair, ordinary CONS, of x to a thing called delay of y.
And before I explain that, let me go and write the rest. The head of a stream is going to be just the CAR.
And the tail of a stream is going to be a thing called force the CDR of the stream.
Now let me explain this.
Delay is going to be a special magic thing.
What delay does is take an expression and produce a promise to compute that expression when you ask for it.
It doesn't do any computation here.
It just gives you a rain check.
It produces a promise.
And CONS-stream says I'm going to put together in a pair x and a promise to compute y.
Now, if I want the head, that's just the CAR that I put in the pair.
And the key is that the tail is going to be-- force calls in that promise.
Tail says, well, take that promise and now call in that promise.
And then we compute that thing.
That's how this is going to work.
That's what CONS-stream, head, and tail really are.
Now, let's see how this works.
And we'll go through this fairly carefully.
We're going to see how this works in this example of computing the second prime between 10,000 and a million.
OK, so we start off and we have this expression.
The second prime-- the head of the tail of the result of filtering for primality the integers between 10,000 and 1 million.
Now, what is that?
What that is, that interval between 10,000 and 1 million, well, if you trace through enumerate interval, there builds a CONS-stream.
And the CONS-stream is the CONS of 10,000 to a promise to compute the integers between 10,001 and 1 million.
So that's what this expression is.
Here I'm using the substitution model.
And we can use the substitution model because we don't have side effects and state.
So I have CONS of 10,000 to a promise to compute the rest of the integers.
So only one integer, so far, got enumerated.
Well, I'm going to filter that thing for primality.
Again, you go back and look at the filter code.
What the filter will first do is test the head.
So in this case, the filter will test 10,000 and say, oh, 10,000's not prime.
Therefore, what I have to do recursively is filter the tail.
And what's the tail of it, well, that's the tail of this pair with a promise in it.
Tail now comes in and says, well, I'm going to force that.
I'm going to force that promise, which means now I'm going to compute the integers between 10,001 and 1 million.
OK, so this filter now is looking at that.
That enumerate itself, well, now we're back in the original enumerate situation.
The enumerate is the CONS of the first thing, 10,001, onto a promise to compute the rest.
So now the primality filter is going to go look at 10,001.
It's going to decide if it likes that or not.
It turns out 10,001 isn't prime.
So it'll force it again and again and again.
And finally, I think the first prime it hits is 10,009.
And at that point, it'll stop.
And that will be the first prime, and then eventually, it'll need the second prime.
So at that point, it will go again.
So you see what happens is that no more gets generated than you actually need.
That enumerator is not going to generate any more integers than the filter asks it for as it's pulling in things to check for primality.
And the filter is not going to generate any more stuff than you ask it for, which is the head of the tail.
You see, what's happened is we've put that mixing of generation and test into what actually happens in the computer, even though that's not apparently what's happening from looking at our programs.
OK, well, that seemed easy.
All of this mechanism got put into this magic delay.
So you're saying, gee, that must be where the magic is.
But see there's no magic there either.
You know what delay is.
Delay on some expression is just an abbreviation for--  well, what's a promise to compute an expression?
Lambda of nil, procedure of no arguments, which is that expression.
That's what a procedure is.
It says I'm going to compute an expression.
What's force?
How do I take up a promise?
Well, force of some procedure, a promise, is just run it.
Done.
So there's no magic there at all.
Well, what have we done?
We said the old style, traditional style of programming is more efficient.
And the stream thing is more perspicuous.
And we managed to make the stream procedures run like the other procedures by using delay.
And the thing that delay did for us was to de-couple the apparent order of events in our programs from the actual order of events that happened in the machine.
That's really what delay is doing.
That's exactly the whole point.
We've given up the idea that our procedures, as they run, or as we look at them, mirror some clear notion of time.
And by giving that up, we give delay the freedom to arrange the order of events in the computation the way it likes.
That's the whole idea.
We de-couple the apparent order of events in our programs from the actual order of events in the computer.
OK, well there's one more detail.
It's just a technical detail, but it's actually an important one.
As you run through these recursive programs unwinding, you'll see a lot of things that look like tail of the tail of the tail.
That's the kind of thing that would happen as I go CONSing down a stream all the way.
And if each time I'm doing that, each time to compute a tail, I evaluate a procedure which then has to go re-compute its tail, and re-compute its tail and recompute its tail each time, you can see that's very inefficient compared to just having a list where the elements are all there, and I don't have to re-compute each tail every time I get the next tail.
So there's one little hack to slightly change what delay is, and make it a thing which is-- I'll write it this way.
The actual implementation, delay is an abbreviation for this thing, memo-proc of a procedure.
Memo-proc is a special thing that transforms a procedure.
What it does is it takes a procedure of no arguments and it transforms it into a procedure that'll only have to do its computation once.
And what I mean by that is, you give it a procedure.
The result of memo-proc will be a new procedure, which the first time you call it, will run the original procedure, remember what result it got, and then from ever on after, when you call it, it just won't have to do the computation.
It will have cached that result someplace.
And here's an implementation of memo-proc.
Once you have the idea, it's easy to implement.
Memo-proc is this little thing that has two little flags in there.
It says, have I already been run?
And initially it says, no, I haven't already been run.
And what was the result I got the last time I was run?
So memo-proc takes a procedure called proc, and it returns a new procedure of no arguments.
Proc is supposed to be a procedure of no arguments.
And it says, oh, if I'm not already run, then I'm going to do a sequence of things.
I'm going to compute proc, I'm going to save that.
I'm going to stash that in the variable result.
I'm going to make a note to myself that I've already been run, and then I'll return the result.
So that's if you compute it if it's not already run.
If you call it and it's already been run, it just returns the result.
So that's a little clever hack called memoization.
And in this case, it short circuits having to re-compute the tail of the tail of the tail of the tail of the tail.
So there isn't even that kind of inefficiency.
And in fact, the streams will run with pretty much the same efficiency as the other programs precisely.
And remember, again, the whole idea of this is that we've used the fact that there's no really good dividing line between procedures and data.
We've written data structures that, in fact, are sort of like procedures.
And what that's allowed us to do is take an example of a common control structure, in this place iteration.
And we've built a data structure which, since itself is a procedure, kind of has this iteration control structure in it.
And that's really what streams are.
OK, questions?
AUDIENCE: Your description of tail-tail-tail, if I understand it correctly, force is actually execution of a procedure, if it's done without this memo-proc thing.
And you implied that memo-proc gets around that problem.
Doesn't it only get around it if tail-tail-tail is always executing exactly the same-- PROFESSOR: Oh, that's-- sure.
AUDIENCE: I guess I missed that point.
PROFESSOR: Oh, sure.
I mean the point is--  yeah.
I mean I have to do a computation to get the answer.
But the point is, once I've found the tail of the stream, to get the tail of the tail, I shouldn't have had to re-compute the first tail.
See, and if I didn't use memo-proc, that re-computation would have been done.
AUDIENCE: I understand now.
AUDIENCE: In one of your examples, you mentioned that we were able to use the substitution model because there are no side effects.
What if we had a single processing unit-- if we had a side effect, if we had a state?
Could we still practically build the stream model?
PROFESSOR: Maybe.
That's a hard question.
I'm going to talk a little bit later about the places where substitution and side effects don't really mix very well.
But in general, I think the answer is unless you're very careful, any amount of side effect is going to mess up everything.
AUDIENCE: Sorry, I didn't quite understand the memo-proc operation.
When do you execute the lambda?
In other words, when memo-proc is executed, just this lambda expression is being generated.
But it's not clear to me when it's executed.
PROFESSOR: Right.
What memo-proc does-- remember, the thing that's going into memo-proc, the thing proc, is a procedure of no arguments.
And someday, you're going to call it.
Memo-proc translates that procedure into another procedure of no arguments, which someday you're going to call.
That's that lambda.
So here, where I initially built as my tail of the stream, say, this procedure of no arguments, which someday I'll call.
Instead, I'm going to have the tail of the stream be memo-proc of it, which someday I'll call.
So that lambda of nil, that gets called when you call the memo-proc, when you call the result of that memo-proc, which would be ordinarily when you would have called the original thing that you set it.
AUDIENCE: OK, the reason I ask is I had a feeling that when you call memo-proc, you just return this lambda.
PROFESSOR: That's right.
When you call memo-proc, you return the lambda.
You never evaluate the expression at all, until the first time that you would have evaluated it.
AUDIENCE: Do I understand it right that you actually have to build the list up, but the elements of the list don't get evaluated?
The expressions don't get evaluated?
But at each stage, you actually are building a list.
PROFESSOR: That's-- I really should have said this.
That's a really good point.
No, it's not quite right.
Because what happens is this.
Let me draw this as pairs.
Suppose I'm going to make a big stream, like enumerate interval, 1 through 1 billion.
What that is, is a pair with a 1 and a promise.
That's exactly what it is.
Nothing got built up.
When I go and force this, and say, what happens?
Well, this thing is now also recursively a CONS.
So that this promise now is the next thing, which is a 2 and a promise to do more.
And so on and so on and so on.
So nothing gets built up until you walk down the stream.
Because what's sitting here is not the list, but a promise to generate the list. And by promise, technically I mean procedure.
So it doesn't get built up.
Yeah, I should have said that before this point.
OK.
Thank you.
Let's take a break.