[MUSIC PLAYING]
PROFESSOR: Well, so far in this
course we've been talking
目前为止 我们这门课讨论的都是过程
about procedures, and then just
to remind you of this
而我想提醒大家的是 我们介绍的这个框架
framework that we introduced for
talking about languages,
是用来讨论语言的
we talked about the primitive
things that are
我们讨论内建于系统中的基本元素
built into the system.
We mentioned some means of
combination by which you take
我们介绍了一些组合的方法
the primitive things and you
make more complicated things.
用来组合基本元素 使你能够构造更复杂的东西
And then we talked about the
means of abstraction, how you
然后我们讨论了抽象的方法
can take those complicated
things and name them so you
你如果去取用这些复杂的东西
can use them as simple
building blocks.
并且给它们命名 使得可以像简单单元那样使用它  # TBD
And then last time you saw
we went even beyond that.
我们在课程的最后甚至想要做更超前的东西
We saw that by using higher
order procedures, you can
我们看到 通过使用高阶过程
actually express general methods
for computing things.
我们甚至可以表达计算的通用方法
Like the method of doing
something by fixed points, or
这就像求不动点的方法和牛顿法
Newton's method, and so the
incredible expressive power
你可以通过组合这些抽象的方法
you can get just by combining
these means of abstraction.
来得到这种难以执行的表达力 # TBD
And the crucial idea in all of
this is the one that we build
而这些的中心观点则是
a layered system.
我们要构造一个层次系统 # TBD
So for instance, if we're
writing the square root
譬如说 如果我们编写平方根过程
procedure, somewhere the square
root procedure uses a
而这个平方根过程又用到了
procedure called good-enough,
and between those there is
一个叫good-enough的过程
some sort of abstraction
boundary.
而这两者之间就有某种抽象边界 # TBD
It's almost as if we go out and
in writing square root, we
这大概就像是我们开始编写平方根程序
go and make a contract with
George, and tell George that
而先要与George订好“合同”
his job is to write good-enough,
and so long as
告诉他 他的工作是编写good-enough过程
good-enough works, we don't
care what it does.
因此只要good-enough按我们的预期运作
We don't care exactly how
it's implemented.
我们就不管是如果运作的
There are levels of detail here
that are George's concern
我们不管心（它的内部）实现
and not ours.
这里的实现层面是Goerge操心的 和我们无关
So for instance, George might
use an absolute value
譬如说 George如果用了
procedure that's written by
Harry, and we don't much care
Harry写的绝对值过程 我们不会去关心这些
about that or even know that,
maybe, Harry exists.
甚至可能还不知道有Harry这个人
So the crucial idea is that when
we're building things, we
关键点是当我们在构造东西时
divorce the task of building
things from the task of
我们将构造整体的任务划分为了
implementing the parts.
实现部件的任务
And in a large system, of
course, we have abstraction
当然 在一个大型系统中
barriers like this at lots, and
lots, and lots of levels.
我们有像这样的抽象屏障 在很高很高很高层次上的抽象屏障
And that's the idea that we've
been using so far over and
这也是我们到目前为止一直在使用的思想
over in implementing
procedures.
贯彻到每次编写过程之中
Well, now what we're going
to do is look at the
书归正传 我们将要
same issues for data.
在数据中看到同样的问题
We're going to see that the
system has primitive data.
我们将看到系统中有基本数据
In fact, we've already
seen that.
实际上我们已经看到了
We've talked about numbers
as primitive data.
我们已经看到了作为基本对象的数字
And then we're going to
see their means of
我们将看到适用于数据的组合方法
combination for data.
There's glue that allows you to
put primitive data together
有种“胶水” 让你把基本数据粘合在一起
to make more complicated,
kind of compound data.
来构造一种更复杂的复合数据
And then we're going to see a
methodology for abstraction
然后我们将看到一种用于抽象的方法
that's a very good thing to use
when you start building up
这种方法十分好用 尤其是
data in terms of simpler data.
当你开始用简易的数据构造复杂数据时
And again, the key idea is that
you're going to build the
再次强调 中心思想是要建立层次化的系统
system in layers and set up
abstraction barriers that
建立抽象屏障将细节隔离在低层
isolate the details at the lower
layers from the thing
将细节与你要做的事所在的高层隔离开  # TBD
that's going on at
the upper layers.
The details at the
lower layers, the
低层的细节
ideas, they won't matter.
低层的思想 都不重要
They're going to be George's
concern because he signed this
那是George该操心的
contract with us for how the
stuff that he implements
因为他跟我们“签了合同”
behaves, and how he implements
the thing is his problem.
他负责实现这些行为 怎么实现都是他的事
All right, well let's
look at an example.
好了 来看一个实例吧
And the example I'm going to
talk about is a system that
我们将会讨论一个系统
does arithmetic on
rational numbers.
一个在有理数域上做算术运算的系统
And what I have in mind is that
we should have something
我现在所想到的是
in the computer that allows us
to ask it, like, what's the
计算机中应该有某种东西
sum of 1/2 and 1/4, and somehow
the system should say,
使得我们可以查询 比如说1/2加上1/4的和是多少
yeah, that's 3/4.
系统就会说 是3/4
Or we should be able to say
what's 3/4 times 2/3, and the
我们也可以查询3/4乘以2/3的积
system should be able to
say, yeah, that's 1/2.
系统因该能够回答 结果是1/2
Right?
对吧？
And you know what
I have in mind.
你知道我想表达的 #TBD
And you also know how to do this
from, I don't know, fifth
我不太确定你们是多久掌握这些运算的
grade or sixth grade.
五年级或者六年级吧？
There are these formulas that
say if I have some fraction
这有一些公式说
which is a numerator over a
denominator, and I want to add
一个分数是分子除以分母 # TBD
that to some other fraction
which is another numerator
而如果我要将这个分数与另一个分数相加的话
over another denominator, then
the answer is the numerator of
当然 这个分数也是分子除以分母 那么结果将会是
the first times the denominator
of the second,
第一个分数的分子乘以第二个分数的分母
plus the numerator of the second
times the denominator
加上第二个分数的分子乘以第一个分数的分母
of the first. That's the
numerator of the answer, and
当然 这只是答案的分子
the denominator is the product
of the two denominators.
答案的分母是两个分数的分母之积
Right?
对吧？
So there's something from fifth
or sixth grade fraction
这大概就是五、六年级教授的分数算术
arithmetic.
And then similarly, if I want
to multiply two things, n1
与之相似的 如果我想要将两个数乘起来
over d1 multiplied by n2 over
d2 is the product of the
n1除以d1的商 乘以 n2除以d2的商
numerators over the product
of the denominators.
就是两个分数的分子之积除以两个分母之积的商
So it's no problem at all, but
it's absolutely no problem to
所以这些都不构成问题
think about what computation you
want to make in adding and
multiplying these fractions.
But as soon as we go
to implement it, we
但是当我们实现这个功能的时候 我们似乎错过了什么 # TBD
run up across something.
We don't have what a
rational number is.
我们连有理数都没有
So we said that the system gives
us individual numbers,
系统只给了我们单个的数字
so we can have 5 and 3, but
somehow we don't have a way of
比如5和3 但我们没有去表达一个
saying there's a thing that has
both a 3 and a 4 in it, or
同时具有一个3和一个4的东西
both a 2 and a 3.
或者一个2和一个3的东西
It's almost as if we'd like to
imagine that somehow there are
但只要我们去想象
these clouds, and a cloud
somehow has both a numerator
我们就会看到一些云彩
and a denominator in it, and
that's what we'd like to work
某个云彩不知咋的同时具有分子和分母
in terms of.
这就是我们想有的语言形式 #TBD
Well, how are we going to
solve that problem?
那么 我们要怎么解决这个问题呢？
We're going to solve that
problem by using this
我们将使用一种强大的设计策略来解决这个问题
incredibly powerful design
strategy that you've already
这种策略我们已经反复使用过了
seen us use over and over.
And that's the strategy
of wishful thinking.
Just like before when we didn't
have a procedure, we
就像我们之前并没有任何过程一样
said, well, let's imagine that
that procedure already exists.
我们就想象确实存在着过程这个东西
We'll say, well, let's imagine
that we have these clouds.
那么 我们就来想象我们有了（有理数）这些云彩吧
Now more precisely what I mean
is let's imagine that we have
更准确一点来说
three procedures, one
called make-RAT.
让我们假设我们有了三个过程 其一为MAKE-RAT
make-RAT is going to take as
arguments two numbers, so I'll
MAKE-RAT有两个参数
call them numerator and
denominator, and it'll return
我们分别把它们叫作分子和分母
for us a cloud--
它给我们返回一朵云彩——
one of these clouds.
我们需要的云彩
I don't really know
what a cloud is.
我并不知道云彩是什么
It's whatever make-RAT returns,
that's its business.
无论MAKE-RAT返回什么 那都是它的事
And then we're going to say,
suppose we've got one of these
并且我们将会说 假设我们有了一个这种云彩
clouds, we have a procedure
called numer, which takes in a
我们有个叫NUMBER的过程
cloud that has an n and a d in
it, whatever a cloud is, and I
这个过程需要我们传递有n和a的云彩
don't know what it is,
and returns for us
不管这个云彩是什么 我不知道这个云彩是什么
the numerator part.
但NUMBER过程会返回（云彩的）分子部分
And then we'll assume we have a
procedure denom, which again
我们也会假设我们有个叫DENOM的过程
takes in a cloud, whatever a
cloud is, and returns for us
该过程需要我们传递一个云彩 不管云彩是什么
the denominator [? required. ?] #TBD
并返回（云彩的）分母部分
This is just like before, when
if we're building a square
就像先前我们构造平方根过程一样
root, we assume that we
have good enough.
我们假设我们有GOOD-ENOUGH过程
Right?
对吧？
And what we'll say is, we'll go
find George, and we'll say
我们会找到George 对他说
to George, well, it's your
business to make us these
好吧 你的任务就是实现这三个过程
procedures.
And how you choose to implement
these clouds, that's
你选择如何实现这些云彩
your problem.
就是你的事了
We don't want to know.
我们不想知道
Well, having pushed this task
off onto George, then it's
那么 把这些杂事都推给George后
pretty easy to do
the other part.
完成其它部分就相当容易了
Once we've got the clouds, it's
pretty easy to write the
一旦我们有了这些云彩后 编写那些
thing that does say addition
of rational numbers.
把有理数加起来的程序就变得容易多了
You can just say define,
well, let's say +RAT.
你可以定义 这么说吧 定义+RAT
Define +RAT, which will
take in two rational
定义+RAT过程 该过程需要两个有理数参数 x和y
numbers, x and y.
x and y are each these clouds.
x和y就是这些云彩
And what does it do?
这个过程干些啥呢？
Well, it's going to return
for us a rational number.
它将返回给我们一个有理数
What rational number is it?
这个有理数是怎么得来的呢？
Well, we've got the
formulas there.
依据我们这里的公式
The numerator of it is the
sum of the product of the
结果的分子的一部分为
numerator of x and the
denominator of y.
x的分子与y的分母之积
It's one thing in the sum.
这只是结果的分子的一部分
And the other thing in the
numerator is the product of
结果的分子剩下的一部分是
the numerator of y and
the denominator of x.
y的分子与x的分母之积
The star, close the plus.
闭合* 闭合+
Right, that's the first argument
to make-RAT, which is
好了 这是MAKE-RAT的第一个参数
the numerator of the thing
I'm constructing.
这是我将要构造的云彩的分子
And then the rest of the thing
goes into make-RAT is the
而MAKE-RAT剩下的参数
denominator of the answer, which
is the product of the
则是结果的分母
denominator of x and the
denominator of y.
也就是x的分母乘以y的分母
Like that.
像这样
OK?
好
So there is the analog of doing
这就是对有理数加法的一个模拟
rational number addition.
And it's no problem at
all, assuming that
在假设我们有了这些云彩后
we have these clouds.
就变得完全没有问题
And of course, we can do
当然 我们可以用同样的方法把它们乘起来
multiplication in the same way.
Define how to get the product
of two rational
我们把将两个有理数乘起来的过程
numbers, call it *RAT.
定义为*RAT
Takes in two of these clouds, x
and y, it returns a rational
该过程需要两朵云彩 x和y
number, make-RAT, whose
numerator is the product of
返回一个用MAKE-RAT构造的有理数
the numerators--
这个有理数的分子是
numerator of x times
the numerator of y.
x的分子与y的分子之积
And the denominator of the thing
it's going to return is
而这个有理数的分母则是
the product of the
denominators.
x的分母与y的分母之积
Well, except that I haven't
told you what these clouds
are, that's all there
is to it.
See, what did I do?
I assumed by wishful thinking
that I had a new
我按照我的期许假设我有
kind of data object.
一种新的数据类型
And in particular, I assumed I
had ways of creating these
特别的 我假设我有创建这些数据类型的能力
data objects.
Make-RAT creates one
of these things.
这里的MAKE-RAT就创建了一个新的数据类型
This is called a constructor.
这叫作“构造函数”
All right, I have a thing that
constructs such data objects.
我现在有了可以构造这些数据类型的东西了
And then I assume I have things
that, having made these
然后我假设我有某些东西 有了这些东西后
things, I have ways of getting
the parts out.
我就可以从中抽取部分信息的方法了
Those are called selectors.
这些叫作“选择函数”
And so formally, what I said is
I assumed I had procedures
把之前我所说的更加正式化一点 就是说
that are constructors and
selectors for these data
我假设我有了用于处理这些数据类型的构造函数和选择函数
objects, and then I went
off and used them.
那我就可以使用它们 # TBD - Went off
That's no different in kind from
saying I assume I have a
这就和我说我假设
procedure good-enough,
and I go use it to
我有GOOD-ENOUGH?过程 并用它来
implement square root.
实现平方根这种做法没有区别
OK, well before we go on, let's
ask the question of why
好 在我们继续之前
do we want to do this
in the first place?
让我们来想想 为什么我们首先就在这个地方实现了这些东西？
See, why do we want a procedure
like +RAT that takes
为什么我们需要一个像+RAT一样的过程
in two rational numbers and
returns a rational number?
一个需要两个有理数作为参数并返回一个有理数的过程
See, another way to think about
this is, well, here's
换一种想法就是
this formula.
我们实现的是这里的这个公式
And I've also got to implement
something that
这里我也实现了用于
adds rational numbers.
加和两个有理数的东西
One other way to think about is,
well, there's this thing,
再换一种想法就是 这有这么一个东西
and I type in four numbers,
an n1, and a d1, and
可以让我输入四个数 n1 d1
an n2, and a d2.
n2 d2
And it sets some registers in
the machine to this numerator
然后这个东西就修改机器里的寄存器
and this denominator.
来代表分子和分母
So I might say, well, why don't
I just add rational
所以你大概会问
numbers by I type in four
numbers, numerators and
你为什么不用四个分别代表分子和分母的数
denominators, and get out two
numbers, which is a numerator
来做有理数加法
and a denominator.
这个加法返回两个数 分别代表分子和分母
Why are we worrying
about building
我们为什么要关心像这样构造东西？ #TBD
things like this anyway?
Well, the answer is, suppose
you want to think about
呃 那是因为
expressing something like this,
suppose I'd like to
假设你想表达像这样的东西
express the idea of taking two
rational numbers, x plus y,
假设我想表达“采用”两个有理数的思想
say, and multiplying that
by the sum of two
x加y的和乘以s加上t的和
other rational numbers.
Well, the way I do it, having
things like +RAT and *RAT, is
然而 当我有了像+RAT和*RAT这样的东西后
I'd say, oh yeah, what that
is is just the product.
我就会将其考虑为乘积
That's *RAT of the sum of x and
y and the sum of s and t.
就是将*RAT应用于x和y的和以及s和t的和上
So except for syntax, I get an
expression that looks like the
除了语法 我还能得到一个表达式 # TBD
way I want to think about
it mathematically.
这个表达式看起来像是按照数学思想表达的
I want to say there
are two numbers.
我说这有两个数
There's a thing which is the
sum of them, and there's a
这个东西代表了这两个数的和
thing which is the
sum of these two.
然而这个东西又代表了另两个数的和
That's this and this.
就是这个和这个
And then I multiply them.
然后我把它们乘起来
So I get an expression that
matches this expression.
所以我有了一个和这里的表达式相匹配的表达式
If I did the other thing, if I
said, well, the way I want to
而如果我用其它的方式去表达
think about this is I type into
my machine four numbers,
我表达为 我传递向机器传递四个数
which are the numerators and the
denominators of x and y,
四个分别代表x和y的分子、分母的数
and then four more numbers,
which are the numerators and
然后又是四个分别代表s和t的分子、分母的数
denominators of s and t.
And then what I'd be sitting
with is, well,
what would I do?
I'd add these, and somehow I'd
have to have two temporary
我把这些加起来 不知咋的我们就得到了两个临时变量
variables, which are the
numerators and denominators of
分别代表了和的分子、分母
this sum, and I'd go off and
store them someplace.
我又得去找个地方把它们存储起来
And then I'd go over here, I'd
type in four more numbers, I'd
然后到了这里 我又传入了四个数
get two more temporary
variables, which are the
我又有了两个临时变量
numerators and denominators
of s and t.
分别代表了s和t之和的分子和分母
And then finally, I put those
together by multiplying them.
最后 我通过把它们乘起来来将其结合在一起
You see, what's starting to
happen, there are all these
如你所见 麻烦出来了
temporary variables, which are
sort of the guts of the
这里满是临时变量
internals of these rational
numbers that start hanging out
这些应该是这些有理数内部的“内脏”吧
all over the system.
但却显露在我们的系统中
And of course, if I had more
and more complicated
当然 随着表达式变得越来越复杂
expressions, there'd be more and
more guts hanging out that
这些“内脏”就会显露得越来越多
confuse my programming.
使我编程时感到困惑
And those of you who sort of
programmed things like that,
像这样写程序的人
where you're just adding numbers
in assembly language,
你只是在用汇编语言的思想来加和两数
you sort of see you have to
suddenly be concerned with
these temporary variables.
而这些对我大脑造成的困惑
But more importantly than
confusing my programming,
要比对编程造成的困惑更严重
they're going to confuse
my mind.
Because the whole name of this
game is that we'd like the
programming language to express
the concepts that we
我们希望程序设计语言能够表达
have in our heads, like rational
numbers are things
我们脑中的概念 有理数就是这些概念
that you can add and then take
that result and multiply them.
我们可以先把它们加起来然后再乘起来
Let's break for questions.
有疑问吗？
Yeah?
恩
AUDIENCE: I don't quite see the
need- when we had make-RAT
学生：我不太明白为什么
with the numerator and
denominator, we had to have
既然我们有MAKE-RAT过程了
the numerator and denominator
to pass as parameters to
我们将传递两个参数作为分子和分母来构造一朵云彩
create the cloud, and then we
extracted to get back what we
但最后我们又从中将这些东西给抽取出来
had to have originally.
PROFESSOR: That's right.
教授：非常正确
So the question is, I sort of
have the numerator and the
我们的问题是 既然我们是用分子和分母构造云彩
denominator, why am I worrying
about having the cloud given
但我为什么又想从云彩里面把它们取出来呢？
that I have to get
the pieces out?
That's sort of what I tried to
say at the end, but let me try
这个是我在后面提到过的
and say it again,
because that's
不过让我再说一次吧
really the crucial question.
这个问题非常关键
The point is, I want to carry
this numerator and denominator
关键点就是
around together all the time.
我想让分子和分母总是在一起
And it's almost as if I want
to know, yeah, there's a
这里面有分子和分母
numerator and denominator in
there, but also, I would like
同样的 我也想表达
to say, fine, but from another
point of view, that's x.
但是 从另一个角度来看 这就是x
And I carry x around, and I name
it as x, and I hold it.
我可以取用x 我给它命名为x hold # TBD
And I can say things like, the
sum of x and y, rather than
然后我就可以说 x加上y的和
just have-- see, it's not so bad
when I only think about x,
我只考虑一个x的时候 使用代表分子和分母的数并无大碍
but if I have a system with 10
rational numbers, suddenly I
但是当我有10个有理数时
have 20 numerators and
denominators, which are not
如果我不把它们联系起来
necessarily--
我一下子就有了20个不必要的分子和分母
if I don't link them, then it's
just 20 arbitrary numbers
它们只是20个没有以一种特定方式联系起来的任意数而已
that are not linked in
any particular way.
它们只是20个没有以一种特定方式联系起来的任意数而已
It's a lot like saying, well, I
have these instructions that
这就像是说 这里我有
are the body of the procedures,
why do I want to
这些过程体的指令 为什么我把它们
package them and say
it's the procedure?
封装起来作为一个过程
It's exactly the same idea.
这是一码子事儿
No?
没问题了
OK.
好吧
Let's break, let's just stretch
and get somebody--
那休息一下 活动一下吧
[INAUDIBLE]
[听不清]
[MUSIC PLAYING]
[音乐]
OK, well, we've been working
on this rational number
好吧 回到我们的有理数算术系统来
arithmetic system, and then
what we did, the important
而我们所做的 最重要的则是
thing about what we did, is we
thought about the problem by
我们我们把这个问题分解为了两部分
breaking it into two pieces.
We said, assume there is this
contract with George, and
我们假设我们跟George“签了合同”
George has figured out the way
to how to construct these
George已经给出了如何去构造这些云彩
clouds, provided us procedures
make-RAT, which was a
他给我们提供了一个作为构造函数的MAKE-RAT过程
constructor, and selectors,
which are numerator and
相应的 用于提取分子和分母的选择函数
denominator.
And then in terms of that, we
went off and implemented
然后 我们用这些东西
addition and multiplication
of rational numbers.
我们实现了有理数的加法和乘法
Well, now let's go look
at George's problem.
好了 我们来看看George面临的问题吧
How can we go and package
together a numerator and a
我们如何来把分子和分母给封装起来
denominator and actually make
one of these clouds?
并把它们放在“云彩”里
See, what we need is a kind of
glue, a glue for data objects
我们需要的是一种胶水
that allows us to put
things together.
一种可以让我们把数据结合在一起的胶水
And Lisp provides such
a glue, and that glue
Lisp提供了这样的胶水
is called list structure.
我们把它叫作“表结构”
List structure is a way of
gluing things together, and
表结构是一种将数据粘合在一起的工具
more precisely, Lisp provides
a way of constructing things
说得更准确一点 就是Lisp提供了一种叫序对的构造方法 #TBD
called pairs.
There's a primitive operator
in Lisp called cons.
Lisp里面有一个叫CONS的基本过程
We can take a look at it.
让我们来看一下
There's a thing called cons.
这个就是CONS
Cons is an operator which takes
in two arguments called
CONS是一个运算符 它需要两个参数X和Y
x and y, and it returns for
us a thing called a pair.
它返回给我们一个叫作“序对”的东西
All right, so a thing called a
pair that has a first part a
而所谓的“序对” 就是指它有“首部分”和“次部分” #TBD
second part.
So cons takes two objects.
这也解释了为什么CONS需要两个参数
There's a thing called a pair.
如果我们有一个序对的话
The first part of the cons
is x, and the second part
X就是首部分 而Y就是次部分
of the cons is y.
And that's what it builds.
这就是它的构造方式
And then we also assume
we have ways of
我们同样也有把东西取出来的方法
getting things out.
If you're given a pair, there's
a thing called car,
给定一个序对 我们有一个叫CAR的东西
and car of a pair, p, gives
you out the first part
使得 序对P的CAR就是序对P的首部分
of the pair, p.
And there's a thing called cdr,
and cdr of the pair, p,
也有一个叫CDR的东西
gives you the second part
of the pair, p.
而序对P的CDR 就返回序对P的次部分
OK, so that's how we
construct things.
这些就是我们构造数据的方法
There's also a conventional
way of drawing pictures of
在将这些数据用图画表示时
these things.
我们也有一种俗成的方法
Just like we write down that
as the conventional way of
writing Plato's idea of two,
the way we could draw a
diagram to represent cons of
two and three is like this.
We draw a little box.
先画个小盒子
And so here's the box we're
talking about, and this box
这个就是我们讨论的（序对）
has two arrows coming
out of it.
它用两个从中放出的箭头 #TBD
And say the first part of this
pair is 2, and the second part
我们说 这个序对的首部分是2
of this pair is 3.
而这个序对的次部分是3
And this notation has
a name, it's called
这种记法叫作
box and pointer notation.
“盒子—指针”记法
By the way, let me say right now
that a lot of people get
顺带一提 我现在就来说说
confused that there's some
significance to the geometric
way I drew these pointers,
the directions.
Like some people think it'd be
different if I took this
一些人可能会认为 如果我这样画箭头
pointer and turned it up here,
and put the 3 out here.
并把3放在这里 结果会不一样
That has no significance.
这实际上是没区别的
All right?
能理解吗？
It's merely you have a bunch
of arrows, these
pointers, and the boxes.
The only issue is how they're
connected, not the geometric
唯一的区别就在于它们是如何链接的
arrangement of whether
I write the pointer
而不是我把它们怎么放置
across, or up, or down.
譬如向上放 向下放 或者交叉放
Now it's completely un-obvious,
probably, why
that's called list structure.
We're not actually going to
talk about that today.
我们今天不会讨论这个问题
We'll see that next time.
我们下次再讨论吧
So those are pairs, there's
cons that constructs them.
所以 我们可以用CONS构造序对
And what I'm going to know about
cons, and car, and cdr,
is precisely that if I have any
x and y, all right, if I
have any things x and y, and I
use cons to construct a pair,
对任意的X和Y 我可以用CONS来构造一个序对
then the car of that pair is
going to be x, the thing I put
那么该序对的CAR就是X 就是我的构造时的一个输入
in, and the cdr of that
pair is going to be y.
而该序对的CDR就是Y
That's the behavior of these
operators, cons, car, and cdr.
这就是CONS、CAR、CDR这些运算符的行为
Given them, it's pretty clear
how George can go off and
有了这些东西 George构造有理数就明了多了
construct his rational
numbers.
After all, all he has to do--
言归正传
remember George's problem was
to implement make-RAT,
记得吗 George的任务是实现MAKE-RAT、
numerator, and denom.
NUMER、DENOM过程
So all George has to do is
say define make-RAT of
George这样编写代码
some n and a d--
定义用N和D来MAKE-RAT
so all I have to do
is cons them.
就是将CONS应用于这二者
That's cons of n and d.
也就是(CONS N D)
And then if I want to get the
numerator out, I would say
而如果我想取出分子
define the numerator, numer,
of some rational number, x.
代码我这样写 定义有理数X的NUMER
If the rational number's
implemented as a pair, then
如果我们是用序对来实现有理数的话
all I have to do is get
out the car of x.
我只需要用CAR来获得X的首部分
And then similarly, define the
denom is going to be the cdr,
类似的 DENOM就是用CDR运算符了
the other thing I put
into the pair.
也就是我用于构造序对的另一个数据
Well, now we're in business.
That's a complete
这就是有理数的一种实现
implementation of rational numbers.
Let's use it.
我们来实践一下
Suppose I want to say, so I want
to think about how to add
假设我想要
1/2 plus 1/4 and watch
the system work.
我想要求取1/2加上1/4 并观察系统是怎么运作的
Well, the way I'd use that is
I'd say, well, maybe define a.
那么 我或许会定义一个A
I have to make a 1/2.
我需要构造一个1/2
Well, that's a rational number
with numerator 1 and
也就是一个分子为1 分母为2的有理数
denominator 2, so a will
be make-RAT of 1 and 2.
也就是 A为(MAKE-RAT 1 2)
And then I'll construct
the 1/4.
然后我来构造1/4
I'll say define d to be
make-RAT of 1 and 4.
我定义B为(MAKE-RAT 1 4)
And if I'd like to look
at the answer--
如果我想解得答案的话
well, assuming I don't have a
special thing that prints
先假设我们没有一个专门用于打印有理数的东西
rational numbers, or
I could make one--
我可以自己编写一个
I could say, for instance,
define the answer to be +RAT
比如说 我可以这样写 定义答案为(+RAT A B)
of a and b, and now I can
say, what's the answer?
那么我就可以问 答案是多少？
What are the numerators and
denominators of the answer?
答案的分子和分母分别是多少？
So if I'm adding 1/2 and 1/4,
I'll say, what is the
因此 我把1/2和1/4加起来后 我会问
numerator of the answer?
答案的分子是多少？
And the system is going
to type out, well, 6.
这个系统就应该打印出 6
Bad news.
糟糕了
And if I say what's the
denominator of the answer, the
而如果我问答案的分母是多少
system's going to type out 8.
系统就应该打印出8
So instead of what I would
really like, which is for it
我们本来希望能得到
to say that 1/2 and 1/4 is 3/4,
this foolish machine is
1/2加1/4是3/4
going to say, no, it's 6/8.
但这台愚蠢的机器却说 不 应该是6/8
Well, that's sort of bad news.
恩 这的确有点糟糕
Where's the bug?
问题在哪里呢？
Why does it do that,
after all?
Well, it's the way that
we just had +RAT.
问题出在+RAT上
+RAT just took the--
+RAT只是
it said you add the numerator
times the denominator, you add
把A的分子和B分母之积与
that to the numerator times the
denominator, and put that
B的分子和A的分母之积加在一起
over the product of the two
denominators, and that's why
并把它们除以两分母之积
you get 6/8.
这就是为什么得到6/8的原因
So what was wrong with our
implementation of +RAT?
那么 我们的+RAT实现有什么问题呢？
What's wrong with that rational
number arithmetic
我们在此之前所做的
stuff that we did before
the break?
有理数算术又有什么错误呢？
Well, the answer is one way to
look at it is absolutely
当然 从一方面来看
nothing's wrong.
这一点都没有错
That's perfectly good
implementation.
这其实是一个相当好的实现
It follows the sixth grade,
fifth grade mathematic for
这个实现完完全全遵守了分数加法法则
adding fractions.
One thing we can say is, well,
that's George's problem.
我们可以这样说 这就是George的问题了
Like, boy, wasn't George dumb
to say that he can make a
rational number simply by
sticking together the
numerator and the denominator?
Wouldn't it be better for
George, when he made a
在构造有理数时 如果George把这些东西化到最简
rational number, to reduce the
stuff to lowest terms?
难道不是会跟好一点吗？
And what I mean is, wouldn't
it be better for George,
我想说的是 对George来说
instead of using this version
of make-RAT, to use this one
用这个版本的MAKE-RAT 难道会比幻灯片上的这个好么？
on the slide?
Or instead of just saying cons
together n and d, what you do
不是简单的通过CONS 把N和D结合起来
is compute the greatest common
divisor of n and d, and gcd is
我们先寻找N和D的最大公约数
the procedure which, well, for
all we care is a primitive,
我们用GCD过程来找 我们只需知道GCD是一个基本过程
which computes the greatest
common divisor of two numbers.
它返回的是两个数的最大公约数
So the way I can construct a
rational number is get the
因此 这种构造有理数的方法就是
greatest common divisor of the
two numbers, and I'm going to
先找到两数的最大公约数
call that g, and then instead
of consing together n and d,
先用G来表示吧 不是简单通过CONS结合N、D
I'll divide them through.
而是先让它们除以G
I'll cons together the quotient
of n by the the gcd
然后我再用CONS结合N/G和D/G的商
and the quotient of
d by the gcd.
And that will reduce the
rational number to lowest
这样就把我们的有理数化到了最简
terms. So when I do
this addition,
因此 当我在做加法时
when +RAT calls make-RAT--
当+RAT调用MAKE-RAT过程时
and for the definition of +RAT
it had a make-RAT in there--
just by the fact that it's
constructing that, the thing
will get reduced to lowest
terms automatically.
OK, that is a complete system.
For rational number arithmetic,
let's look at what
we've done.
All right, we said we want
to build rational number
arithmetic, and we had
a thing called +RAT.
We implemented that.
And I showed you multiplying
rational numbers, and although
I didn't put them up there,
presumably we'd like to have
something that subtracts
rational numbers, and I don't
know, all sorts of things.
Things that test equality in
division, and maybe things
that print rational numbers
in some particular way.
And we implemented those
in terms of pairs.
These pairs, cons, car, and cdr
that are built into Lisp.
But the important thing is that
between these and these,
we set up an abstraction
barrier.
We set up a layer
of abstraction.
And what was that layer
of abstraction?
That layer of abstraction was
precisely the constructor and
the selectors.
This layer was make-RAT,
and numer, and denom.
This methodology, another way
to say what it's doing, is
that we are separating the way
something is used, separating
the use of data objects,
from the
representation of data objects.
So up here, we have the way
that rational numbers are
used, do arithmetic on them.
Down here, we have the way that
they're represented, and
they're separated by
this boundary.
The boundary is the constructors
and selectors.
And this methodology
has a name.
This is called data
abstraction.
Data abstraction is sort of the
programming methodology of
setting up data objects by
postulating constructors and
selectors to isolate use
from representation.
Well, so why?
I mean, after all, we didn't
have to do it this way.
It's perfectly possible to do
rational number addition
without having any compound data
objects, and here on the
slide is one example.
We certainly could have defined
+RAT, which takes in
things x and y, and we'll say,
well what are these rational
numbers really?
So really, they're just pairs,
and the numerator's the car
and the denominator's the cdr.
So what we'll do is we'll take
the car of x times the cdr
of y, multiply them.
Take the car of y times the
cdr of x, multiply them.
Add them.
Take the cdr of x and the cdr of
y, multiply them, and then
constitute together.
Well, that sort of does
the same thing.
But this ignores the problem of
reducing things to lowest
terms, but let's not worry
about that for a minute.
But so what?
Why don't we do it that way?
Right?
After all, there are sort of
fewer procedures to define,
and it's a lot more
straightforward.
It saves all this self-righteous
BS about
talking about data
abstraction.
We just sort of do it.
I mean, who knows, maybe it's
even marginally more efficient
depending on whatever compiler
were using for this.
What's the point of isolating
the use from the
representation?
Well, it goes back to this
notion of naming.
Remember, one of the most
important principles in
programming is the same as
one of the most important
principles in sorcery,
all right?
That's if you have the name
of the spirit, you get
control over it.
And if you go back and look at
the slide, you see what's in
there is we have this thing
+RAT, but nowhere in the
system, if I have a +RAT and a
-RAT and a *RAT, and things
that look like that, nowhere
in the system do I have a
thing that I can point at which
is a rational number.
I don't have, in a system like
that, the idea of rational
number as a conceptual entity.
Well, what's the advantage
of that?
What's the advantage of
isolating the idea of rational
numbers as a conceptual entity,
and really naming it
with make-RAT, numerator,
and denominator.
Well, one advantage is you might
want to have alternative
representations.
See, before I showed you that
one way George can solve this
things not reduced to lowest
terms problem, is when you
build a rational number, you
divide up by the greatest
common denominator.
Another way to do that
is shown over here.
I can have an alternative
representation for rational
numbers where when you make
a rational number,
you just cons them.
However, when you go to select
out the numerator, at that
point you compute the gcd of
the stuff that's sitting in
that pair, and divide
out by the gcd.
And similarly, when I get the
denominator, at that point
when I go to get the
denominator, I'll divide out
by the gcd.
So the difference would be in
the old representation, when
ans was constructed here, say
what's 6 and 8, in the first
way, the 6 and 8 would have
got reduced when they got
stuck into that pair, numerator
would select out 3.
And in the way I just showed
you, well, ans would get 6 and
8 put in, and then at the point
where I said numerator,
some computation would
get done to put out
3 instead of 6.
So those are two different
ways I might do it.
Which one's better?
Well, it depends, right?
If I'm making a system where
I am mostly constructing
rational numbers and hardly
ever looking at them, then
it's probably better not to do
that gcd computation when I
construct them.
If I'm doing a system where I
look at things a lot more than
I construct them, then it's
probably better to do the work
when I construct them.
So there's a choice there.
But the real issue is that you
might not be able to decide at
the moment you're worrying about
these rational numbers.
See, in general, as systems
designers, you're forced with
the necessity to make decisions
about how you're
going to do things, and in
general, the way you'd like to
retain flexibility is to never
make up your mind about
anything until you're
forced to do it.
The problem is, there's a very,
very narrow line between
deferring decisions and outright
procrastination.
So you'd like to make progress,
but also at the same
time, never be bound by the
consequences of your decisions.
Data abstraction's one
way of doing this.
What we did is we used
wishful thinking.
See, we gave a name
to the decision.
We said, make-RAT, numerator,
and denominator will stand for
however it's going to be done,
and however it's going to be
done is George's problem.
But really, what that was doing
is giving a name to the
decision of how we're going to
do it, and then continuing as
if we made the decision.
And then eventually, when we
really wanted it to work,
coming back and facing what
we really had to do.
And in fact, we'll see a couple
times from now that you
may never have to choose any
particular representation,
ever, ever.
Anyway, that's a very powerful
design technique.
It's the key to the reason
people use data abstraction.
And we're going to see that
idea again and again.
Let's stop for questions.
AUDIENCE: What does this
decision making through
abstraction layers do to the
axiom of do all your design
before any of your code?
PROFESSOR: Well, that's
someone's axiom, and I bet
that's the axiom of someone who
hasn't implemented very
large computer systems
very much.
I said that computer science is
a lot like magic, and it's
sort of good that
it's like magic.
There's a bad part of
computer science
that's a lot like religion.
And in general, I think people
who really believe that you
design everything before you
implement it basically are
people who haven't designed
very many things.
The real power is that you can
pretend that you've made the
decision and then later on
figure out which one is right,
which decision you ought
to have made.
And when you can do that, you
have the best of both worlds.
AUDIENCE: Can you explain
the difference
between let and define?
PROFESSOR: Oh, OK.
Let is a way to establish
local names.
Let me give you sort
of the half answer.
And I'll say, later on we can
talk about the whole very
complicated thing.
But the big difference for now
is that, see, when you're
typing at Lisp, you're typing
in this environment where
you're making definitions.
And when you say define a to be
5, if I say define a to be
5, then from then on the thing
will remember that a is 5.
Let is a way to set up a local
context where there's a
definition.
So if I type something like,
saying let a-- no, I
shouldn't say a--
if I said let z be 10, and
within that context, tell me
what the sum of z and z is.
So if I typed in this expression
to Lisp, and then
this would put out 20.
However, then if I said what's
z, the computer would say
that's an unbound variable.
So let is a way of setting up
a context where you can make
definitions.
But those definitions are
local to this context.
And of course, if I'd said a
in here, I'd still get 20.
But this a would not interfere
at all with this one.
So if I type this, and then type
this, and then say what's
a? a will still be 5.
So there's some other subtle
differences between let and
define, but that's the
most important one.
All right, well, we've looked
at implementing this little
system for doing arithmetic on
rational numbers as an example
of this methodology of
data abstraction.
And that's a way of controlling
complexity in
large systems. But, see, like
procedure definition, and like
all the ways we're going to
talk about for controlling
complexity, the real power of
these things show up not when
you sort of do these things in
themselves, like it's not such
a great thing that we've done
rational number arithmetic,
it's that you can use these as
building blocks for making
more complicated things.
So it's no wonderful idea that
you can just put two numbers
together to form a pair.
If that's all you ever wanted to
do, there are tons of ways
that you can do that.
The real issue is can you do
that in such a way so that the
things that you build become
building blocks for doing
something even more complex?
So whenever someone shows you
a method for controlling
complexity, you should say,
yeah, that's great, but what
can I build with it?
So for example, let me just
run through another thing
that's a lot like the
rational number one.
Suppose we would like to
represent points in the plane.
You sort of say, well, there's
a point, and we're going to
call that point p.
And that point might have
coordinates, like this might
be the point 1 comma 2.
The x-coordinate might
be 1, and it's
y-coordinate might be 2.
And we'll make a little system
for manipulating
points in the plane.
And again, we can do
that-- here's a
little example of that.
It can represent vectors, the
same as points in the plane,
and we'll say, yep, there's
a constructor called
make-vector, make-vector's going
to take two coordinates,
and here we can implement them
if we like as pairs, but the
important thing is that
there's a constructor.
And then given some vector, p,
we can find its x-coordinate,
or we can get its
y-coordinate.
So there's a constructor
and selectors for
points in the plane.
Well, given points in the plane,
we might want to use
them to build something.
So for instance, we might want
to talk about, we might have a
point, p, and a point, q, and p
might be the point 1, 2, and
q might be the point 2, 3.
And we might want to talk about
the line segment that
starts at p and ends at q.
And that might be
the segment s.
So we might want to build points
for vectors in terms of
numbers, and segments
in terms of vectors.
So we can represent
line segments in
exactly the same way.
All right, so the line segment
from p to q, we'll say there's
a constructor, make-segment.
And make up names for the
selectors, the starting point
of the segment and the ending
point of the segment.
And again, we can implement a
segment using cons as a pair
of points, and car and cdr get
out the two points that we put
together to get the segment.
Well, now having done that,
we can have some
operations on them.
Like we could say, what's the
midpoint of a line segment?
So here's the midpoint of a line
segment, that's going to
be the points whose coordinates
are the averages
of the coordinates
of the endpoints.
OK, there's the midpoint.
So to get the midpoint of a line
segment, s, we'll just
say grab the starting point to
the segment, grab the ending
point of the segment, and
now make a vector--
make a point whose coordinates
are the average of the
x-coordinate of the first point
and the x-coordinate of
the second point, and whose
y-coordinate is the average of
the y-coordinates.
So there's an implementation
of midpoint.
And then similarly, we can
build something like the
length of the segment.
The length of the segment
is a thing whose--
use Pythagoras's rule, the
length of the segment is the
square root of the d x squared
plus d y squared.
We'll say to get the length of
a line segment, we'll let dx
be the difference of the
x-coordinate of one endpoint
and the x-coordinate of the
other endpoint, and we'll let
dy be the difference of
the y-coordinates.
And then we'll take the square
root of the sum of the squares
of dx and dy, that's
what this says.
All right, so there's an
implementation of length.
And again, what we built
is a layered system.
We built a system which
has, well, say up
here there's segments.
And then there's an abstraction
barrier.
The abstraction barrier
separates the implementation
of segments from the
implementation of vectors and
points, and what that
abstraction barrier is are the
constructors and selectors.
It's make-segment, and
segment-start, and
segment-end.
And then there are vectors.
And vectors in turn are built
on top of pairs and numbers.
So I'll say pairs and numbers.
And that has its own abstraction
barrier, which is
make-vector, and x-coordinate,
and y-coordinate.
So we have, again,
a layered system.
You're starting to see that
there are layers here.
I ought to mention, there is a
very important thing that I
kind of took for granted.
And it's sort of so natural, but
on the other hand it's a
very important thing.
Notice that in order to
represent this segment s, I
said this segment is
a pair of points.
And a point is a pair
of numbers.
And if I were going to draw the
box and pointers structure
for that, I would say, oh, the
segment is, given those
particular representations that
I showed you, I'd say
this segment s is a pair, and
the first thing in the pair is
a vector, and the vector
is a pair of numbers.
And that's this, that's p.
And the other thing in the
segment is q, which is itself
a pair of numbers.
So I almost took it for granted
when I said that cons
allows you to put
things together.
But it's very easy to not
appreciate that, because
notice, some of the things
I can put together can
themselves be pairs.
And let me introduce a word that
I'll talk about more next
time, it's one of my favorite
words, called closure.
And by closure I mean that the
means of combination in your
system are such that when you
put things together using
them, like we make a pair, you
can then put those together
with the same means
of combination.
So I can have not only a pair
of numbers, but I can have a
pair of pairs.
So for instance, making arrays
in a language like Fortran is
not a closed means of
combination, because I can
make an array of numbers,
but I can't
make an array of arrays.
And one of the things that you
should ask, one of your tests
of quality for a means of
combination that someone shows
you, is gee, are the things
you make closed under that
means of combination?
So pairs would not be nearly so
interesting if all I could
do was make a pair of numbers.
I couldn't build very much
structure at all.
OK, well, we'll come
back to that.
I just wanted to
mention it now.
You'll hear a lot about
closure later on.
You can also see the potential
for losing control of
complexity as you have a layered
system if you don't
use data abstraction.
Let's go back and look at
this slide for length.
Length works and is a simple
thing because I can say, when
I want to get this value, I
can say, oh, that is the
x-coordinate of the first
endpoint of the segment.
And each of these things,
each of these selectors,
x-coordinate and endpoint, stand
for a decision choice
whose details I don't
have to look at.
So I could perfectly well,
again, just like rational
numbers I did before, I could
say, oh well, gee, a segment
really is a pair of pairs.
And the x-coordinate of the
first endpoint or the segment
really is the--
well, what is it?
It's the car of the car
of the segment.
So I could perfectly well
go and redefine length.
I could say, define the length
of some segment s.
And I could start off writing
something like, well, we'll
let dx be-- well, what's
it have to be?
It's got to be the difference
of the two coordinates, so
that's the difference of, the
first one is the car of the
car of s, subtracted from the
first one, the car of the
other half of it,
the cdr of s.
All right, and then
dy would be--
well, let's see, I'd get the
y-coordinate, so it'd be the
difference of the cdr of the car
of s, and the cdr of the
cdr of s, sort of go on.
You can see that's much harder
to read than the
program I had before.
But worse than that,
suppose you'd gone
and implemented length?
And then the next day, George
comes to you and says, I'm
sorry, I changed my mind.
I want to write points with the
x-coordinate first. So you
come back you stare at
this code and say, oh
gee, what was that?
That was the car, so I have to
change this to cdr, and this
is cdr, and this now
has to be car.
And this has to be car.
And you sort of do that, and
then the next day George comes
back and says, sorry, the guys
designing the display would
like lines to be painted in the
opposite direction, so I
have to write the endpoint
first in the order.
And then you come back and you
stare at this code, and say,
gee, what was it
talking about?
Oh yeah, well I've got to change
this one to cdr, and
this one becomes car, this one
comes car, and this becomes
cdr.
And you go up and do that, and
then the next day, George
comes back and says, I'm sorry,
what I really meant is
that the segments always have
to be painted from left to
right on the screen.
And then you sort of, it's
clear, you just go and punch
George in the mouth
at that point.
But you see, as soon as we have
a 10 layer system, you
see how that complexity
immediately builds up to the
point where even something like
this gets out of control.
So again, the way we've gotten
out of that is we've named
that spirit.
We built a system where there
is a thing, which is the
representation choice
for how you're going
to talk about vectors.
And choices about that
representation are localized
right there.
They don't have their guts
spilling over into things like
how you compute the length and
how you compute the midpoint.
And that's the real power
of this system.
OK, we're explicit about
them, so that we have
control over them.
All right, questions?
AUDIENCE: What happens in the
case where you don't want to
be treating objects
in terms of pairs?
For instance, in
three-dimensional space, you'd
have three coordinates.
Or even in the case
where you have
n-dimensional space, what happens?
PROFESSOR: Right, OK.
Well, this is a preview of
what I'll say tomorrow.
But the point is, once you have
two things, you have as
many things as you want.
All right?
Because if I want to make three
things, I could start
making things like a pair whose
first thing is 1, and
whose second thing is another
pair that, say,
has 2 and 3 in it.
And so on, a hundred things.
I can nest them out of pairs.
I made a pretty arbitrary
decision about how to do it,
and you can immediately
see there are lots
of ways to do that.
What we'll start talking about
next time are conventions for
how to do things like that.
But notice that what this really
depends on is I can
make pairs of pairs.
If all I could do was
make pairs of
numbers, I'd be stuck.
OK.
Let's break.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
All right, well, we've just gone
off and done a couple of
simple examples of
data abstraction.
Now I want to do something
more complicated.
We're going to talk about
what it means.
And this will be harder, because
it's always much
harder in computer programming
to talk about what something
means than to go
off and do it.
But let's go back to almost
the very beginning.
Let's go back to the point where
I said, we just assumed
that there were procedures,
make-RAT,
and numer, and denom.
Let's go back to where we had
this, at the very beginning,
constructors and selectors,
and when often defined the
rational number arithmetic.
And remember, I said at that
point we were sort of done,
except for George.
Well, what is it that we'd
actually done at that point?
What was it that was done?
Well, what I want to say is,
what was done after we'd
implemented the operations and
terms of these, was that we
had defined a rational number
representation in terms of
abstract data.
What do I mean by
abstract data?
Well, the idea is that at that
point, when we had our +RAT
and our *RAT, that any
implementation of make-RAT,
and numerator, and denominator
that George supplied us with,
could be the basis for
a rational number
representation.
Like, it wasn't our concern
where you divided through to
get the greatest common
denominator, or any of that.
So the idea is that what we
built is a rational arithmetic
system that would sit on top
of any representation.
What do I mean by any
representation?
I mean, certainly it can't be
the case that all I mean is
George can reach in a bag and
pull out three arbitrary
procedures and say, well,
fine, now that's the
implementation.
That can't be what I mean.
What I've got to mean is that
there's some way of saying
whether three procedures are
going to be suitable as a
basis for rational number
representation.
If we think about it, what
suitable might mean is if I
have to assume something like
this, I have to say that if x
is the result of say, doing
make-RAT of n and d, then the
numerator of x divided by
the denominator of x is
equal to n over d.
See, what that is is that's
George's contract.
What we mean by writing a
contract for rational numbers,
if you think about it, this
is the right thing.
And the two ones we showed
do the right thing.
See, if I'm taking out greatest
common divisors, it
doesn't matter whether I take
them out or not, or the place
where I take them, because
the idea is I'm
going to divide through.
But see, this is George's
contract.
So what we really say to George
is your business is to
go off and find us three
procedures, make-RAT, and
numerator, and denominator, that
fulfill this contract for
any choice of n and d.
And that's what we mean by we
can use that as the basis for
a rational number
representation.
And other than that, it fulfills
this contract.
We don't care how he does it.
It's not our business.
It's below the layer
of abstraction.
In fact, if we want
to say, what is a
rational number really?
See, what's it really, without
having to talk about going
below the layer of abstraction,
what we're forced
into saying is a rational number
really is sort of this
axiom, is three procedures,
make-RAT, numerator, and
denominator, that satisfy
this axiom.
In some sense, abstractly,
that's what a
rational number is really.
That's sort of easy words to
listen to, because what you
have in your head, of course,
is well, for all this thing
about saying that's what a
rational number is really, you
actually just saw that we
built rational numbers.
See, what we really did
is we built rational
numbers on top of pairs.
So for all I'm saying
abstractly, we can say a
rational number really
is just this axiom.
You can listen to that
comfortably, because you're
saying, well, yeah, but really
it's actually pairs, and I'm
just annoying you by trying
to be abstract.
Well, let me, as an antidote for
that, let me do something
that I think is really
going to terrify you.
I mean, it's really going to
bring you face to face with
the sort of existential reality
of this abstraction
that we're talking about.
And what I'm going
to talk about is,
what are pairs really?
See, what did I tell
you about pairs?
I tricked you, right?
I said that Lisp has this
primitive called cons that
builds pairs.
But what did I really
tell you about?
If you go back and said, let's
look on this slide, all I
really told you about pairs is
that there happens to be this
property, these properties of
cons, car, and cdr. And all I
really said about pairs is that
there's a thing called
cons, and a thing called car,
and a thing called cdr.
And it is the case that if I
build cons of x, y and take
car of it, I get x.
And if I build cons of x, y and
get cdr of it, I get y.
And even though I lulled you
into thinking that there's
something in Lisp that does
that, so you pretended you
knew what it was, in fact, I
didn't tell you any more about
pairs than this tells you
about rational numbers.
It's just some axiom
for pairs.
Well, to drive that home, let me
really scare you, and show
you what we might build
pairs in terms of.
And what you're going to see is
that we can build rational
numbers, and line segments, and
vectors, and all of this
stuff in terms of pairs, and
we're going to see below here
that pairs can be built
out of nothing at all.
Pure abstraction.
So let me show you on this slide
an implementation of
cons, car, and cdr. And we'll
look at it again in a second,
but notice that their procedure
definitions of cons,
car, and cdr, you don't see any
data in there, what you
see is a lambda.
So cons here is going to
return-- is a procedure that
returns a procedure, just like
average [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
Cons of a and b returns a
procedure of an argument
called pick, and it says, if
pick is equal to 1, I'm going
to return a, and if pick is
equal to 2, I'm going to
return b, and that's what
cons is going to be.
Car of a thing x, car of a
pair x, is going to be x
applied to 1.
And notice that makes sense.
You might not understand why or
how I'm doing such a thing,
but at least it makes sense,
because the thing constructed
by cons is a procedure, and
car applies that to 1.
And similarly, cdr applies
that thing to 2.
OK, now I claimed that this is a
representation of cons, car,
and cdr, and notice there's
no data in it.
All right, it's built
out of air.
It's just procedures.
There's no data objects at all
in that representation.
Well, what could that
possibly mean?
Well, if you really believe this
stuff, then you have to
believe that in order to show
that that's a representation
for cons, car, and cdr, all I
have to do is show that it
satisfies the axiom.
See, all I should have to
convince you of is, for
example, that gee, that car of
cons of 37 and 49 is 37 for
arbitrary values of 37 and 49.
And cdr the same way.
See, if I really can demonstrate
to you that that
weird procedure definition, in
terms of [? air ?], has the
property that it satisfies this,
then you just have to
grant me that that is a possible
implementation of
cons, car, and cdr, on which I
can build everything else.
Well, let's look at that.
And this will be practice in
the substitution model.
How could we check this?
We sort of know how
to do that.
It's just the same substitution
model.
Let's look.
We start out, and we
say, what's car of
cons of 37 and 49?
What do we do?
Cons is some procedure.
Its value is cons was a
procedure of a and b.
The thing returned by cons is
its procedure body with 37 and
49 substituted for
the parameters.
It'll be 37 substituted for a
and 49 substituted for b.
So this expression has the
same meaning as this
expression.
Its car of, and the body of
cons was this thing that
started with lambda.
And it says, so if pick is equal
to 1, where pick is this
other argument, if pick is equal
to 1, it's 37, that's
where a was, and if pick
is equal to 2, it's 49.
So that's the first step.
I'm just going through
mechanical substitution.
And remember, at this point in
the course, if you're confused
about what things mean, go
mechanically through the
substitution model.
Well, what is this reduced to?
Car said, take your argument,
which in this case is this,
and apply it to 1.
That was the definition
of car.
So if I look at car, if I do
that, the answer is, well,
it's that argument, this
was the argument to
car, applied to 1.
Well, what does that mean?
I take 1, and I substitute it
in the body here for this
value of pick, which
is the name of the
argument, what do I get?
Well, I get the thing that says
if 1 equals 1 it's 37,
and if 1 equals 2 it's 49,
so the answer's 37.
And similarly, if I'd taken cdr,
that would apply it to 2,
and I'd get 49.
So you see, what I've
demonstrated is that that
completely weird implementation
of cons, car,
and cdr, satisfies the axioms.
So it's a perfectly valid way
of building, in fact, all of the
data objects we're going
to see in Lisp.
So they all, if you like,
can be built on sort of
existential nothing.
And as far as you know,
that's how it works.
You couldn't tell.
If all you're ever going to do
with pairs is construct them
with cons and look at them with
car and cdr, you couldn't
possibly tell how this
thing works.
Now, it might give you a sort
of warm feeling inside if I
say, well, yeah, in fact, for
various reasons there happens
to be a primitive called cons,
car, and cdr, and if it's too
scary, if this kind of stuff is
too scary, you don't have
to look inside of it.
So that might make you feel
better, but the point is, it
really could work this way,
and it wouldn't make any
difference to the
system at all.
So in some sense, we don't
need data at all to build
these data abstractions.
We can do everything in
terms of procedures.
OK, well, why did I terrify
you in this way?
First, I really want to
reinforce this idea of
abstraction, that you really
can do these things
abstractly.
Secondly, I want to introduce
an idea we're going to see
more and more of in this course,
which is we're going
to blur the line between
what's data
and what's a procedure.
See, in this funny
implementation it turned out
that cons of something happened
to be represented in
terms of a procedure, even
though we think of it as data.
While here that's sort of a
mathematical trick, but one of
the things we'll see is that
a lot of the very important
programming techniques that
we're going to get to sort of
depend very crucially on
blurring this traditional line
between what you consider
a procedure and what you
consider data.
We're going to see more
and more of that,
especially next time.
OK, questions?
AUDIENCE: If you asked
the system to print
a, what would happen?
PROFESSOR: The question is, what
would happen if I asked
the system to print a.
Given this representation, you
already know the answer.
The answer is compound
procedure a,
just like last time.
It'd say compound procedure.
It might say a little
bit more.
It might say compound procedure
lambda or something
or other, depending on details
of how I named it.
But it's a procedure.
And the only reason for that is
I haven't told the system
anything special about how
to print such things.
Now, it's in fact true that with
the actual implementation
of cons that to be built in
the system, it would print
something else.
It would print, say,
this is a pair.
AUDIENCE: When you define cons,
and then you pass it
into values, how does it know
where to look for the cons,
because you can use cons
over and over again?
How does it know where to look
to know which a and b it's
supposed to pull back out?
I don't know if I'm expressing
that quite right.
Where is it stored?
PROFESSOR: OK, the question is,
I sort of have a cons with
a 37 and a 49, and I might make
another cons with a 1 and
a 2, and I might have one
called a, and I might
have one called b.
And the question is,
how does it know?
And why don't they
get confused?
And that's a very
good question.
See, you have to really believe
that the procedures
are objects.
It's sort of like saying--
let's try
another simpler example.
Suppose I ask for the
square root of 3.
So I asked for the square root
of 5, and then I ask for the
square of 20.
You're probably not the least
bit bothered that I can take
square root and apply it to 5,
and then I can take square
root and apply it to 20.
And there's sort of no issue,
gee, doesn't it get confused
about whether it's working
on 5 or 20?
There's no issue about that
because you're thinking of a
procedure which goes off
and does something.
Now, in some sense you're asking
me the same question.
But it's really bothering you,
and it's bothering you for a
really good reason.
Because when I write that,
you're saying gee, this is, I
know, sort of a procedure.
But it's not a procedure
that's just running.
It's just sort of a procedure
sitting there.
And how can it be that sometimes
this procedure has
37 and 49, and there might be
another one which has 5 and 6
in there, and why don't
they get confused?
So there's something very,
very important that's
bothering you.
And it's really crucial
to what's going on.
We're suddenly saying that
procedures are not just the
act of doing something.
Procedures are conceptual
entities, objects, and if I
built cons of 37 and 49, that's
a particular procedure
that sits there.
And it's different from
cons of 3 and 4.
That's another procedure
that sits there.
AUDIENCE: Both of them
exist independently.
PROFESSOR: And exists
independently.
AUDIENCE: And they both can be
referenced by car and cdr.
PROFESSOR: And they both would
be referenced by car and cdr.
Just like I could increment
this, and I
could increment that.
They're objects.
And that's sort of where
we're going.
See, the fact that you're asking
the question shows that
you're really starting to think
about the implications
of what's going on.
It's the difference between
saying a procedure is just the
act of doing something.
And a procedure is a real object
that has existence.
AUDIENCE: So when the procedure
gets built, the
actual values are now
substituted for a and b--
PROFESSOR: That's right.
AUDIENCE: And then that
procedure exists as lambda,
and pick is what's actually
passed in.
PROFESSOR: Yes, when cons gets
called, and the result of cons
is a new procedure that's
constructed, that new
procedure has an argument
that's called pick.
AUDIENCE: But it no longer
has an a and b.
The a and b are the
actual values
that are passed through.
PROFESSOR: And it has-- right,
according to the substitution
model, what it now has is not
those arbitrary names a and b,
it somehow has that 37
and 49 in there.
But you're right, that's a hard
thing to think about it,
and it's different from the way
you've been thinking about
procedures.
AUDIENCE: And if I have again
cons of 37 and 49, it's a
different [UNINTELLIGIBLE]?
PROFESSOR: And if you make
another cons of 37 and 49,
you're into a wonderful
philosophical problem, which
is going to be what the lecture
about halfway through
this course is about.
Which is, if I cons 37 and 49,
and I do it again, is that the
same thing, or is it
a different thing?
And how could you tell?
And when could it
possibly matter?
And that's sort of like
saying, is that the
same thing as this?
Or is this the same
thing as that?
It's the same kind
of question.
And that's a very, very
deep question.
And I can't answer in
less than an hour.
But we will.