[MUSIC PLAYING]
PROFESSOR: Last time, we took a
look at an explicit control
evaluator for Lisp, and that
bridged the gap between all
these high-level languages
like Lisp and the query
language and all of that stuff,
bridged the gap between
that and a conventional
register machine.
And in fact, you can think of
the explicit control evaluator
either as, say, the code for a
Lisp interpreter if you wanted
to implement it in the assembly
language of some
conventional register transfer
machine, or, if you like, you
can think of it as the microcode
of some machine
that's going to be specially
designed to run Lisp.
In either case, what we're
doing is we're taking a
machine that speaks some
low-level language, and we're
raising the machine to a
high-level language like Lisp
by writing an interpreter.
So for instance, here,
conceptually, is a special
purpose machine for computing
factorials.
It takes in five and
puts out 120.
And what this special purpose
machine is is actually a Lisp
interpreter that's configured
itself to run factorials,
because you fit into
it a description of
the factorial machine.
So that's what an
interpreter is.
It configures itself to emulate
a machine whose
description you read in.
Now, inside the Lisp
interpreter, what's that?
Well, that might be your general
register language
interpreter that configures
itself to behave like a Lisp
interpreter, because you
put in a whole bunch of
instructions in register
language.
This is the explicit
control evaluator.
And then it also has some sort
of library, a library of
primitive operators and Lisp
operations and all sorts of
things like that.
That's the general strategy
of interpretation.
And the point is, what we're
doing is we're writing an
interpreter to raise the machine
to the level of the
programs that we
want to write.
Well, there's another strategy,
a different one,
which is compilation.
Compilation's a little
bit different.
Here--here we might have
produced a special purpose
machine for, for computing
factorials, starting with some
sort of machine that speaks
register language, except
we're going to do a different
strategy.
We take our factorial program.
We use that as the source
code into a compiler.
What the compiler will do is
translate that factorial
program into some register
machine language.
And this will now be not the
explicit control evaluator for
Lisp, this will be some
register language for
computing factorials.
So this is the translation
of that.
That will go into some sort of
loader which will combine this
code with code selected from the
library to do things like
primitive multiplication.
And then we'll produce a load
module which configures the
register language machine
to be a special
purpose factorial machine.
So that's a, that's a
different strategy.
In interpretation, we're raising
the machine to the
level of our language,
like Lisp.
In compilation, we're taking our
program and lowering it to
the language that's spoken
by the machine.
Well, how do these two
strategies compare?
The compiler can produce code
that will execute more
efficiently.
The essential reason for that is
that if you think about the
register operations that are
running, the interpreter has
to produce register operations
which, in principle, are going
to be general enough to execute
any Lisp procedure.
Whereas the compiler only has
to worry about producing a
special bunch of register
operations for, for doing the
particular Lisp procedure
that you've compiled.
Or another way to say that is
that the interpreter is a
general purpose simulator, that
when you read in a Lisp
procedure, then those can
simulate the program described
by that, by that procedure.
So the interpreter is worrying
about making a general purpose
simulator, whereas the compiler,
in effect, is
configuring the thing to
be the machine that the
interpreter would have
been simulating.
So the compiler can be faster.
On the other hand, the
interpreter is a nicer
environment for debugging.
And the reason for that is that
we've got the source code
actually there.
We're interpreting it.
That's what we're
working with.
And we also have the
library around.
See, the interpreter--the
library sitting there is part
of the interpreter.
The compiler only pulls out from
the library what it needs
to run the program.
So if you're in the middle of
debugging, and you might like
to write a little extra program
to examine some run
time data structure or to
produce some computation that
you didn't think of when you
wrote the program, the
interpreter can do that
perfectly well, whereas the
compiler can't.
So there are sort of dual,
dual advantages.
The compiler will produce code
that executes faster.
The interpreter is a better
environment for debugging.
And most Lisp systems end up
having both, end up being
configured so you have an
interpreter that you use when
you're developing your code.
Then you can speed it
up by compiling.
And very often, you can arrange
that compiled code and
interpreted code can
call each other.
We'll see how to do that.
That's not hard.
In fact, the way we'll--
in the compiler we're going to
make, the way we'll arrange
for compiled coding and
interpreted code to call, to
call each other, is that we'll
have the compiler use exactly
the same register conventions
as the interpreter.
Well, the idea of a compiler is
very much like the idea of
an interpreter or evaluator.
It's the same thing.
See, the evaluator walks over
the code and performs some
register operations.
That's what we did yesterday.
Well, the compiler essentially
would like to walk over the
code and produce the register
operations that the evaluator
would have done were it
evaluating the thing.
And that gives us a model
for how to implement a
zeroth-order compiler, a
very bad compiler but
essentially a compiler.
A model for doing that is you
just take the evaluator, you
run it over the code, but
instead of executing the
actual operations, you
just save them away.
And that's your compiled code.
So let me give you an
example of that.
Suppose we're going to
compile--suppose we want to
compile the expression f of x.
So let's assume that we've got
f of x in the x register and
something in the environment
register.
And now imagine starting
up the evaluator.
Well, it looks at the expression
and it sees that
it's an application.
And it branches to a place in
the evaluator code we saw
called ev-application.
And then it begins.
It stores away the operands and
unev, and then it's going
to put the operator in exp,
and it's going to go
recursively evaluate it.
That's the process that
we walk through.
And if you start looking at
the code, you start seeing
some register operations.
You see assign to unev the
operands, assign to exp the
operator, save the environment,
generate
that, and so on.
Well, if we look on the overhead
here, we can see, we
can see those operations
starting to be produced.
Here's sort of the first real
operation that the evaluator
would have done.
It pulls the operands out of the
exp register and assigns
it to unev. And then it assigns
something to the
expression register, and it
saves continue, and it saves
env.
And all I'm doing here is
writing down the register
assignments that the evaluator
would have done in
executing that code.
And can zoom out a little bit.
Altogether, there are about
19 operations there.
And this is the--this will be
the piece of code up until the
point where the evaluator
branches off to
apply-dispatch.
And in fact, in this compiler,
we're not going to worry about
apply-dispatch at all.
We're going to have
everything--we're going to
have both interpreted code
and compiled code.
Always evaluate procedures,
always apply procedures by
going to apply-dispatch.
That will easily allow
interpreted code and compiled
code to call each other.
Well, in principle, that's
all we need to do.
You just run the evaluator.
So the compiler's a lot
like the evaluator.
You run it, except it stashes
away these operations instead
of actually executing them.
Well, that's not, that's
not quite true.
There's only one little
lie in that.
What you have to worry about is
if you have a, a predicate.
If you have some kind of test
you want to do, obviously, at
the point when you're compiling
it, you don't know
which branch of these--of a
conditional like this you're
going to do.
So you can't say which one the
evaluator would have done.
So all you do there
is very simple.
You compile both branches.
So you compile a structure
that looks like this.
That'll compile into something
that says, the code, the code
for P. And it puts its results
in, say, the val register.
So you walk the interpreter over
the predicate and make
sure that the result would
go into the val register.
And then you compile an
instruction that says, branch
if, if val is true, to a place
we'll call label one.
Then we, we will put the
code for B to walk the
interpreter--walk the
interpreter over B. And then
go to put in an instruction
that says, go to the next
thing, whatever, whatever was
supposed to happen after this
thing was done.
You put in that instruction.
And here you put label one.
And here you put the
code for A. And you
put go to next thing.
So that's how you treat
a conditional.
You generate a little
block like that.
And other than that, this
zeroth-order compiler is the
same as the evaluator.
It's just stashing away the
instructions instead of
executing them.
That seems pretty simple,
but we've gained
something by that.
See, already that's
going to be more
efficient than the evaluator.
Because, if you watch the
evaluator run, it's not only
generating the register
operations we wrote down, it's
also doing things to decide
which ones to generate.
So the very first thing it does,
say, here for instance,
is go do some tests and decide
that this is an application,
and then branch off to the
place that, that handles
applications.
In other words, what the
evaluator's doing is
simultaneously analyzing the
code to see what to do, and
running these operations.
And when you--
if you run the evaluator a
million times, that analysis
phase happens a million times,
whereas in the compiler, it's
happened once, and then you
just have the register
operations themselves.
Ok, that's a, a zeroth-order
compiler, but it is a
wretched, wretched compiler.
It's really dumb.
Let's--let's go back and, and
look at this overhead.
So look at look at some
of the operations
this thing is doing.
We're supposedly looking
at the operations and
interpreting f of x.
Now, look here what
it's doing.
For example, here it
assigns to exp the
operator in fetch of exp.
But see, there's no reason to
do that, because this is--
the compiler knows that the
operator, fetch of exp, is f
right here.
So there's no reason why this
instruction should say that.
It should say, we'll
assign to exp, f.
Or in fact, you don't
need exp at all.
There's no reason it should
have exp at all.
What, what did exp
get used for?
Well, if we come down here,
we're going to assign to val,
look up the stuff in exp
in the environment.
So what we really should do is
get rid of the exp register
altogether, and just change
this instruction to say,
assign to val, look up the
variable value of the symbol f
in the environment.
Similarly, back up here, we
don't need unev at all,
because we know what the
operands of fetch of exp are
for this piece of code.
It's the, it's the list x.
So in some sense, you don't
want unev and exp at all.
See, what they really are in
some sense, those aren't
registers of the actual machine
that's supposed to run.
Those are registers that have to
do with arranging the thing
that can simulate
that machine.
So they're always going to hold
expressions which, from
the compiler's point of view,
are just constants, so can be
put right into the code.
So you can forget about all the
operations worrying about
exp and unev and just
use those constants.
Similarly, again, if we go, go
back and look here, there are
things like assign to
continue eval-args.
Now, that has nothing
to do with anything.
That was just the evaluator
keeping track of where it
should go next, to evaluate the
arguments in some, in some
application.
But of course, that's irrelevant
to the compiler,
because you--
the analysis phase will have
already done that.
So this is completely
irrelevant.
So a lot of these, these
assignments to continue have
not to do where the running
machine is supposed to
continue in keeping track
of its state.
It has to, to do with where the
evaluator analysis should
continue, and those are
completely irrelevant.
So we can get rid of them.
Ok, well, if we, if we simply
do that, make those kinds of
optimizations, get rid, get rid
of worrying about exp and
unev, and get rid of these
irrelevant register
assignments to continue, then we
can take this literal code,
these sort of 19 instructions
that the, that the evaluator
would have done, and
then replace them.
Let's look at the,
at the slide.
Replace them by--we get rid
of about half of them.
And again, this is just sort
of filtering what the
evaluator would have done
by getting rid of
the irrelevant stuff.
And you see, for instance, here
the--where the evaluator
said, assign val, look up
variable value, fetch of exp,
here we have put in
the constant f.
Here we've put in
the constant x.
So there's a, there's a little
better compiler.
It's still pretty dumb.
It's still doing a lot
of dumb things.
Again, if we go look at the
slide again, look at the very
beginning here, we see a save
the environment, assign
something to the val register,
and restore the environment.
Where'd that come from?
That came from the evaluator
back here saying, oh, I'm in
the middle of evaluating
an application.
So I'm going to recursively
call eval dispatch.
So I'd better save the thing I'm
going to need later, which
is the environment.
This was the result
of recursively
calling eval dispatch.
It was evaluating the symbol
f in that case.
Then it came back from eval
dispatch, restored the
environment.
But in fact, the actual thing
it ended up doing in the
evaluation is not going to hurt
the environment at all.
So there's no reason to be
saving the environment and
restoring the environment
here.
Similarly, here I'm saving the
argument list. That's a piece
of the argument evaluation
loop, saving the argument
list, and here you restore it.
But the actual thing that you
ended up doing didn't trash
the argument list. So there
was no reason to save it.
So another way to say, another
way to say that is that the,
the evaluator has to be
maximally pessimistic, because
as far from its point of view
it's just going off to
evaluate something.
So it better save what it's
going to need later.
But once you've done the
analysis, the compiler is in a
position to say, well, what
actually did I need to save?
And doesn't need to do any--
it doesn't need to be as
careful as the evaluator,
because it knows what it
actually needs.
Well, in any case, if we do that
and eliminate all those
redundant saves and restores,
then we can
get it down to this.
And you see there are actually
only three instructions that
we actually need, down from the
initial 11 or so, or the
initial 20 or so in
the original one.
And that's just saying, of those
register operations,
which ones did we
actually need?
Let me just sort of summarize
that in another way, just to
show you in a little
better picture.
Here's a picture of starting--
This is looking at all the
saves and restores.
So here's the expression, f
of x, and then this traces
through, on the bottom here,
the various places in the
evaluator that were passed when
the evaluation happened.
And then here, here
you see arrows.
Arrow down means
register saved.
So the first thing that
happened is the
environment got saved.
And over here, the environment
got restored.
And these-- so there are all the
pairs of stack operations.
Now, if you go ahead and say,
well, let's remember that we
don't--that unev, for instance,
is a completely
useless register.
And if we use the constant
structure of the code, well,
we don't need, we don't need
to save unev. We don't need
unev at all.
And then, depending on how we
set up the discipline of
the--of calling other things
that apply, we may or may not
need to save continue.
That's the first step I did.
And then we can look and see
what's actually, what's
actually needed.
See, we don't-- didn't really
need to save env or
cross-evaluating f, because
it wouldn't, it
wouldn't trash it.
So if we take advantage of that,
and see the evaluation
of f here, doesn't really need
to worry about, about hurting
env. And similarly, the
evaluation of x here, when the
evaluator did that it said, oh,
I'd better preserve the
function register around that,
because I might need it later.
And I better preserve
the argument list.
Whereas the compiler is now in
a position to know, well, we
didn't really need
to save-- to do
those saves and restores.
So in fact, all of the stack
operations done by the
evaluator turned out to be
unnecessary or overly
pessimistic.
And the compiler is in a
position to know that.
Well that's the basic idea.
We take the evaluator, we
eliminate the things that you
don't need, that in some sense
have nothing to do with the
compiler at all, just the
evaluator, and then you see
which stack operations
are unnecessary.
That's the basic structure of
the compiler that's described
in the book.
Let me just show you
how that examples a
little bit too simple.
To see how you, how you actually
save a lot, let's
look at a little bit more
complicated expression.
F of G of X and 1.
And I'm not going to go
through all the code.
There's a, there's a
fair pile of it.
I think there are, there are
something like 16 pairs of
register saves and restores
as the evaluator
walks through that.
Here's a diagram of them.
Let's see.
You see what's going on.
You start out by--the evaluator
says, oh, I'm about
to do an application.
I'll preserve the environment.
I'll restore it here.
Then I'm about to do
the first operand.
Here it recursively goes
to the evaluator.
The evaluator says, oh, this is
an application, I'll save
the environment, do the operator
of that combination,
restore it here.
This save--this restore matches
that save. And so on.
There's unev here, which turns
out to be completely
unnecessary, continues getting
bumped around here.
The function register is
getting, getting saved across
the first operands, across
the operands.
All sorts of things
are going on.
But if you say, well, what of
those really were the business
of the compiler as opposed to
the evaluator, you get rid of
a whole bunch.
And then on top of that, if
you say things like, the
evaluation of F doesn't hurt the
environment register, or
simply looking up the symbol X,
you don't have to protect
the function register
against that.
So you come down to just
a couple of, a
couple of pairs here.
And still, you can do
a little better.
Look what's going on here with
the environment register.
The environment register comes
along and says, oh, here's a
combination.
This evaluator, by the way,
doesn't know anything about G.
So here it says, so it says,
I'd better save the
environment register, because
evaluating G might be some
arbitrary piece of code that
would trash it, and I'm going
to need it later, after
this argument, for
doing the second argument.
So that's why this one didn't go
away, because the compiler
made no assumptions about
what G would do.
On the other hand, if you look
at what the second argument
is, that's just looking
up one.
That doesn't need this
environment register.
So there's no reason
to save it.
So in fact, you can get
rid of that one, too.
And from this whole pile of, of
register operations, if you
simply do a little bit of
reasoning like that, you get
down to, I think, just two pairs
of saves and restores.
And those, in fact, could go
away further if you, if you
knew something about G.
So again, the general idea is
that the reason the compiler
can be better is that the
interpreter doesn't know what
it's about to encounter.
It has to be maximally
pessimistic in saving things
to protect itself.
The compiler only has
to deal with what
actually had to be saved.
And there are two reasons
that something might
not have to be saved.
One is that what you're
protecting it against, in
fact, didn't trash the register,
like it was just a
variable look-up.
And the other one is, that the
thing that you were saving it
for might turn out not
to actually need it.
So those are the two basic
pieces of knowledge that the
compiler can take advantage
of in making
the code more efficient.
Let's break for questions.
AUDIENCE: You kept saying that
the uneval register, unev
register didn't need
to be used at all.
Does that mean that you
could just map a
six-register machine?
Or is that, in this particular
example, it
didn't need to be used?
PROFESSOR: For the compiler,
you could generate code for
the six-register, five, right?
Because that exp
goes away also.
Assuming--yeah, you can get
rid of both exp and unev,
because, see, those are data
structures of the evaluator.
Those are all things that would
be constants from the
point of view of the compiler.
The only thing is this
particular compiler is set up
so that interpreted code and
compiled code can coexist.
So the way to think about it is,
is maybe you build a chip
which is the evaluator, and what
the compiler might do is
generate code for that chip.
It just wouldn't use two
of the registers.
All right, let's take a break.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
We just looked at what the
compiler is supposed to do.
Now let's very briefly look
at how, how this gets
accomplished.
And I'm going to give
no details.
There's, there's a giant pile of
code in the book that gives
all the details.
But what I want to do is
just show you the, the
essential idea here.
Worry about the details
some other time.
Let's imagine that we're
compiling an expression that
looks like there's some
operator, and
there are two arguments.
Now, the--
what's the code that the
compiler should generate?
Well, first of all, it should
recursively go off and compile
the operator.
So it says, I'll compile
And where I'm going to need that
is to be in the function
register, eventually.
So I'll compile some
instructions that will compile
the operator and end up
with the result in
the function register.
The next thing it's going to do,
another piece is to say,
well, I have to compile
the first argument.
So it calls itself
recursively.
And let's say the result
will go into val.
And then what it's going to need
to do is start setting up
the argument list. So it'll say,
assign to argl cons of
fetch-- so it generates this
literal instruction--
fetch of val onto empty list.
However, it might
have to work--
when it gets here, it's going
to need the environment.
It's going to need whatever
environment was here in order
to do this evaluation of
the first argument.
So it has to ensure that the
compilation of this operand,
or it has to protect the
function register against
whatever might happen in the
compilation of this operand.
So it puts a note here and says,
oh, this piece should be
done preserving the environment
register.
Similarly, here, after it gets
done compiling the first
operand, it's going to say,
I better compile--
I'm going to need to know
the environment
for the second operand.
So it puts a little note here,
saying, yeah, this is also
done preserving env. Now it goes
on and says, well, the
next chunk of code is the one
that's going to compile the
second argument.
And let's say it'll compile
it with a targeted to
val, as they say.
And then it'll generate the
literal instruction, building
up the argument list. So it'll
say, assign to argl cons of
the new value it just got onto
the old argument list.
However, in order to have the
old argument list, it better
have arranged that the argument
list didn't get
trashed by whatever
happened in here.
So it puts a little note here
and says, oh, this has to be
done preserving argl.
Now it's got the argument
list set up.
And it's all ready to go
to apply dispatch.
It generates this literal
instruction.
Because now it's got the
arguments in argl and the
operator in fun, but wait, it's
only got the operator in
fun if it had ensured that
this block of code didn't
trash what was in the
function register.
So it puts a little note here
and says, oh, yes, all this
stuff here had better
be done preserving
the function register.
So that's the little--so when
it starts ticking--so
basically, what the compiler
does is append a whole bunch
of code sequences.
See, what it's got in it is
little primitive pieces of
things, like how to look up
a symbol, how to do a
conditional.
Those are all little
pieces of things.
And then it appends them
together in this sort of
discipline.
So the basic means of combining
things is to append
two code sequences.
That's what's going on here.
And it's a little bit tricky.
The idea is that it appends
two code sequences, taking
care to preserve a register.
So the actual append operation
looks like this.
What it wants to
do is say, if--
here's what it means to append
two code sequences.
So if sequence one
needs register--
I should change this.
Append sequence one
to sequence two,
preserving some register.
Let me say, and.
So it's clear that sequence
one comes first.
So if sequence two needs the
register and sequence one
modifies the register, then
the instructions that the
compiler spits out are,
save the register.
Here's the code.
You generate this code.
Save the register, and then you
put out the recursively
compiled stuff for
sequence one.
And then you restore
the register.
And then you put out the
recursively compiled stuff for
sequence two.
That's in the case where
you need to do it.
Sequence two actually needs the
register, and sequence one
actually clobbers it.
So that's sort of if.
Otherwise, all you spit out is
sequence one followed by
sequence two.
So that's the basic operation
for sticking together these
bits of code fragments,
these bits of
instructions into a sequence.
And you see, from this point
of view, the difference
between the interpreter and the
compiler, in some sense,
is that where the compiler has
these preserving notes, and
says, maybe I'll actually
generate the saves and
restores and maybe I won't,
the interpreter being
maximally pessimistic always has
a save and restore here.
That's the essential
difference.
Well, in order to do this, of
course, the compiler needs
some theory of what code
sequences need
and modifier registers.
So the tiny little fragments
that you put in, like the
basic primitive code fragments,
say, what are the
operations that you do when
you look up a variable?
What are the sequence of things
that you do when you
compile a constant or
apply a function?
Those have little notations in
there about what they need and
what they modify.
So the bottom-level
data structures--
Well, I'll say this.
A code sequence to the compiler
looks like this.
It has the actual sequence
of instructions.
And then, along with
it, there's the set
of registers modified.
And then there's the set
of registers needed.
So that's the information the
compiler has that it draws on
in order to be able to
do this operation.
And where do those come from?
Well, those come from, you might
expect, for the very
primitive ones, we're going
to put them in by hand.
And then, when we combine two
sequences, we'll figure out
what these things should be.
So for example, a very primitive
one, let's see.
How about doing a register
assignment.
So a primitive sequence might
say, oh, it's code fragment.
Its code instruction is assigned
to R1, fetch of R2.
So this is an example.
That might be an example of a
sequence of instructions.
And along with that, it'll
say, oh, what I need to
remember is that that modifies
R1, and then it needs R2.
So when you're first building
this compiler, you put in
little fragments of
stuff like that.
And now, when it combines two
sequences, if I'm going to
combine, let's say, sequence
one, that modifies a bunch of
registers M1, and needs a
bunch of registers N1.
And I'm going to combine
that with sequence two.
That modifies a bunch of
registers M2, and needs a
bunch of registers N2.
Then, well, we can
reason it out.
The new code fragment,
sequence one, and--
followed by sequence two, well,
what's it going to modify?
The things that it will modify
are the things that are
modified either by sequence
one or sequence two.
So the union of these
two sets are what
the new thing modifies.
And then you say, well, what is
this--what registers is it
going to need?
It's going to need the things
that are, first of all, needed
by sequence one.
So what it needs is
sequence one.
And then, well, not quite all of
the ones that are needed by
sequence one.
What it needs are the ones that
are needed by sequence
two that have not been set
up by sequence one.
So it's sort of the union of the
things that sequence two
needs minus the ones that
sequence one modifies.
Because it worries about
setting them up.
So there's the basic structure
of the compiler.
The way you do register
optimizations is you have some
strategies for what needs
to be preserved.
That depends on a
data structure.
Well, it depends on the
operation of what it means to
put things together.
Preserving something, that
depends on knowing what
registers are needed
and modified
by these code fragments.
That depends on having little
data structures, which say, a
code sequence is the actual
instructions, what they modify
and what they need.
That comes from, at
the primitive
level, building it in.
At the primitive level, it's
going to be completely obvious
what something needs
and modifies.
Plus, this particular way that
says, when I build up bigger
ones, here's how I generate
the new set of registers
modified and the new set
of registers needed.
And that's the whole--
well, I shouldn't say that's
the whole thing.
That's the whole thing except
for about 30 pages of details
in the book.
But it is a perfectly usable
rudimentary compiler.
Let me kind of show
you what it does.
Suppose we start out with
recursive factorial.
And these slides are going to
be much too small to read.
I just want to flash through
the code and show you about
how much it is.
That starts out with--here's a
first block of it, where it
compiles a procedure entry and
does a bunch of assignments.
And this thing is basically up
through the part where it sets
up to do the predicate
and test whether
the predicate's true.
The second part is what
results from--
in the recursive call to
fact of n minus one.
And this last part is coming
back from that and then taking
care of the constant case.
So that's about how
much code it
would produce for factorial.
We could make this compiler
much, much better, of course.
The main way we could make
it better is to allow the
compiler to make any assumptions
at all about what
happens when you call
a procedure.
So this compiler, for instance,
doesn't even know,
say, that multiplication
is something that
could be coded in line.
Instead, it sets up this
whole mechanism.
It goes to apply-dispatch.
That's a tremendous waste,
because what you do every time
you go to apply-dispatch is
you have to concept this
argument list, because it's
a very general thing
you're going to.
In any real compiler, of course,
you're going to have
registers for holding
arguments.
And you're going to start
preserving and saving the way
you use those registers
similar to the
same strategy here.
So that's probably the very main
way that this particular
compiler in the book
could be fixed.
There are other things like
looking up variable values and
making more efficient primitive
operations and all
sorts of things.
Essentially, a good Lisp
compiler can absorb an
arbitrary amount of effort.
And probably one of the reasons
that Lisp is slow with
compared to languages like
FORTRAN is that, if you look
over history at the amount of
effort that's gone into
building Lisp compilers, it's
nowhere near the amount of
effort that's gone into
FORTRAN compilers.
And maybe that's something that
will change over the next
couple of years.
OK, let's break.
Questions?
AUDIENCE: One of the very
first classes--
I don't know if it was during
class or after class- you
showed me the, say, addition has
a primitive that we don't
see, and-percent add or
something like that.
Is that because, if you're doing
inline code you'd want
to just do it for two
operators, operands?
But if you had more operands,
you'd want to
do something special?
PROFESSOR: Yeah, you're looking
in the actual scheme
implementation.
There's a plus, and a plus
is some operator.
And then if you go look inside
the code for plus, you see
something called--
I forget-- and-percent plus
or something like that.
And what's going on there is
that particular kind of
optimization.
Because, see, general
plus takes an
arbitrary number of arguments.
So the most general plus says,
oh, if I have an argument
list, I'd better cons it up in
some list and then figure out
how many there were or
something like that.
That's terribly inefficient,
especially since most of the
time you're probably
adding two numbers.
You don't want to really have to
cons this argument list. So
what you'd like to do is build
the code for plus with a bunch
of entries.
So most of what it's
doing is the same.
However, there might be a
special entry that you'd go to
if you knew there were
only two arguments.
And those you'll put
in registers.
They won't be in an argument
list and you won't have to
[UNINTELLIGIBLE].
That's how a lot of
these things work.
OK, let's take a break.
[MUSIC PLAYING]