教授: 上节课 我们学习了 PROFESSOR: Last time, we took a look at
一个Lisp 显式控制求值器 an explicit control evaluator for Lisp
它在如Lisp或查询语言等高级语言 and that bridged the gap between all these high-level languages
与传统的寄存器机器之间架起了桥梁 bridged the gap between that and a conventional register machine.
事实上 你可以将显式控制求值器 And in fact, you can think of the explicit control evaluator either as, say
#TBD  the code for a Lisp interpreter if you wanted to implement it in the assembly language of some conventional register transfer machine, or, if you like, you can think of it as the microcode of some machine that's going to be specially designed to run Lisp.
在任何一种情况下 我们得到一种能够处理低级语言的机器 In either case, what we're doing is we're taking a machine that speaks some low-level language
通过写一个解释器来让它能够执行像Lisp之类的高级语言 and we're raising the machine to a high-level language like Lisp by writing an interpreter.
来看个例子 So for instance
这是一个概念上的 用于计算阶乘的专用机器  here, conceptually, is a special purpose machine for computing factorials.
输入5 输出120  It takes in five and puts out 120.
这个专用机器实际上是一个Lisp解释器 And what this special purpose machine is actually a Lisp interpreter
它将自己设置为运行阶乘 that's configured itself to run factorials
因为你喂给它了阶乘机器的描述 because you feed into it a description of the factorial machine.
这就是解释器 So that's what an interpreter is.
它将自己设置为 模拟你所输入描述的机器 It configures itself to emulate a machine whose description you read in.
在Lisp解释器里是什么?  Now, inside the Lisp interpreter, what's that?
里面可能是通用的寄存器语言解释器 Well, that might be your general register language interpreter
它将自己设置为像Lisp解释器一样工作 that configures itself to behave like a Lisp interpreter
因为你输入了一系列寄存器语言编写的指令 because you put in a whole bunch of instructions in register language.
这就是显式控制求值器 This is the explicit control evaluator.
它也有某种TBD And then it also has some sort of library
a library of primitive operators and Lisp operations and all sorts of things like that.
这是解释执行的通常策略 That's the general strategy of interpretation.
事实上，我们所做的是写了一个解释器 And the point is, what we're doing is we're writing an interpreter
将机器提升到能理解我们写的程序的层次 to raise the machine to the level of the programs that we want to write.
也有另一种逻辑 Well, there's another strategy
一种不同的策略，就是编译 a different one, which is compilation.
编译有一些不同 Compilation's a little bit different.
这里 Here--
我们可能已经制造了 here we might have produced
一个特定用途的机器，用来计算阶乘 a special purpose machine for, for computing factorials
从某种讲寄存器语言的机器开始 starting with some sort of machine that speaks register language
除此之外，我们将让它执行不同的策略TBD except we're going to do a different strategy.
我们拿来阶乘程序 We take our factorial program.
我们把这些源代码输入编译器 We use that as the source code into a compiler.
编译器将会做的是 What the compiler will do
把这个阶乘程序翻译成某种寄存器机器语言 is translate that factorial program into some register machine language.
现在它并不是Lisp的显式控制求值器 And this will now be not the explicit control evaluator for Lisp
它现在是某种用来计算阶乘的寄存器语言 this will be some register language for computing factorials.
这就是翻译的过程 So this is the translation of that.
它将进入某种加载器 That will go into some sort of loader
并与从库中选取的乘法之类的代码组合到一起 which will combine this code with code selected from the library to do things like primitive multiplication.
随后我们将生成一个加载模块 And then we'll produce a load module
它把寄存器语言机器配置成 which configures the register language machine
一个专门用来计算阶乘的机器 to be a special purpose factorial machine.
这就是不同的策略 So that's a, that's a different strategy.
在解释中 In interpretation, we're raising
我们将机器提升到我们语言的层次，如Lisp the machine to the level of our language, like Lisp.
在编译中 In compilation
我们将我们的程序降到机器语言的层次 we're taking our program and lowering it to the language that's spoken by the machine.
那么，这两个策略有什么区别呢？ Well, how do these two strategies compare?
编译器可以生成执行起来更有效率的代码 The compiler can produce code that will execute more efficiently.
The essential reason for that is that
if you think about the register operations that are running
the interpreter has to produce register operations
which, in principle, are going to be general enough to execute any Lisp procedure.
Whereas the compiler only has to worry about producing a special bunch of register operations for
for doing the particular Lisp procedure that you've compiled.
换一种说法 Or another way to say that
解释器是一种通用的模拟器 is that the interpreter is a general purpose simulator
当你输入一个Lisp过程时 that when you read in a Lisp procedure
它们就会模拟被那个过程解释的程序 then those can simulate the program described by that, by that procedure.
所以解释器关注的是做出一个通用模拟器 So the interpreter is worrying about making a general purpose simulator
TBD所以解释器关注的是做出一个通用意图的模拟器，而编译器，in effect将东西配置成解释器将要去模拟的机器 whereas the compiler, in effect, is configuring the thing to be the machine that the interpreter would have been simulating.
所以编译器可以运行得更快 So the compiler can be faster.
另一方面 OK, On the other hand
解释器更适合用来排查错误 the interpreter is a nicer environment for debugging.
因为 And the reason for that is that we've got the
我们的源代码实际上就在那里 the source code actually there.
我们正在解释它们 We're interpreting it That's what we're working with.
并且库就在这里 And we also have the library around.
看，这里的库是解释器的一部分 See, the interpreter--the library sitting there is part of the interpreter.
而编译器只会把运行程序所需要的代码从库中拉出来 The compiler only pulls out from the library what it needs to run the program.
所以，如果你在排查错误的途中 So if you're in the middle of debugging
可能你想写一些 and you might like to write
额外的代码来考察运行过程中的数据类型 a little extra program to examine some run time data structure
或者做一些你在写程序时没有想到的运算 or to produce some computation that you didn't think of when you wrote the program
解释器可以完美搞定这些 the interpreter can do that perfectly well
而编译器不行 whereas the compiler can't.
所以它们各有优点 So there are sort of dual, dual advantages.
编译器将生成运行更快的代码 The compiler will produce code that executes faster.
而解释器是一种更适合debug的环境 The interpreter is a better environment for debugging.
大多数Lisp系统最终将二者都实现了 And most Lisp systems end up having both
你可以在开发代码是使用解释器 end up being configured so you have an interpreter that you use when you're developing your code.
随后通过编译代码来使运行更快 Then you can speed it up by compiling.
通常你能做到让被编译的代码和被解释的代码互相调用 And very often, you can arrange that compiled code and interpreted code can call each other.
我们将学习如何做到这一点，其实不难 We'll see how to do that, That's not hard.
OK
In fact, the way we'll--
in the compiler we're going to make
the way we'll arrange for compiled coding and interpreted code to call
to call each other
is that we'll have the compiler
use exactly the same register conventions as the interpreter.
编译器的思路和解释器或执行器很像 Well, the idea of a compiler is very much like the idea of an interpreter or evaluator.
它们是相同的东西 It's the same thing.
求值器读取代码 See, the evaluator walks over the code
产生一些寄存器操作 and performs some register operations.
就是我们昨天做的事情 That's what we did yesterday.
而编译器会读取代码 Well, the compiler essentially would like to walk over the code
生成一些求值器在求值时所做事情的寄存器操作 and produce the register operations that the evaluator would have done were it evaluating the thing.
这给我们了实现一个zeroth-order编译器的模型 And that gives us a model for how to implement a zeroth-order compiler
一个很差的编译器，但TBD大体上是个编译器 a very bad compiler but essentially a compiler.
这种模型就是，你用求值器把代码跑一遍 A model for doing that is you just take the evaluator, you run it over the code
但不去执行实际的操作 but instead of executing the actual operations
只是把它们保存下来 you just save them away.
这就是你编译后的代码 举个例子 And that's your compiled code. So let me give you an example of that.
假设我们要编译 Suppose we're going to compile--
假设我们要编译，假设我们想编译这个表达式(F X)
So let's assume that we've got f of x in the x register and something in the environment register.
想象我们启动了执行器 And now imagine starting up the evaluator.
它读取了表达式，它认为这是个应用 Well, it looks at the expression and it sees that it's an application.
它分叉到求值器的一个地方，我们之前见过的叫ev-application的地方 And it branches to a place in the evaluator code we saw called ev-application.
它将操作数和unev保存 And then it begins. It stores away the operands and unev
然后之后它将操作符放在exp里，用来递归执行 and it's going to go recursively evaluate it.
这就是我们经历的过程 That's the process that we walk through.
你如果看代码，会看到一些寄存器操作 And if you start looking at the code, you start seeing some register operations.
你会看到对unev的操作数TBD You see assign to unev the operands
TBD引用exp的操作符，保存环境，生成它，之类的 assign to exp the operator, save the environment, generate that, and so on.
如果我们研究这里的性能消耗 Well, if we look on the overhead here
会发现这些操作被生成出来 we can see those operations starting to be produced.
这是求值器第一个本来要做的实际操作 Here's sort of the first real operation that the evaluator would have done.
它将操作数从 exp 寄存器里拿出来 It pulls the operands out of the exp register
并将它赋值给unev and assigns it to unev.
然后它将某些东西绑定到表达式寄存器, 保存continue  And then it assigns something to the expression register, and it saves continue
保存env and it saves env.
我们在这做的就是写下 And all I'm doing here is writing down the register assignments
在求值时会进行的寄存器赋值操作 that the evaluator would have done in executing that code.
我们缩小画面看看 And can zoom out a little bit.
总计有19个操作 Altogether, there are about 19 operations there.
And this is the--this will be the piece of code
up until the point where the evaluator branches off to apply-dispatch.
事实上，在这个编译器中 And in fact, in this compiler
我们不需要再关心apply-dispatch了 we're not going to worry about apply-dispatch at all.
我们有所有东西We're going to have everything
我们拥有解释后代码和编译后代码 we're going to have both interpreted code and compiled code.
通常求值过程，通常应用过程是由apply-dispatch处理的 Always evaluate procedures, always apply procedures by going to apply-dispatch.
这将让被解释后代码与编译后代码很很容易互相调用 That will easily allow interpreted code and compiled code to call each other.
从原则上来说，这就是我们要做的一切 Well, in principle, that's all we need to do.
你只是运行求值器 You just run the evaluator.
因而编译器非常像求值器 So the compiler's a lot like the evaluator.
你运行它，唯一不同是你把操作存下来，而不是实际执行它们You run it, except it stashes away these operations instead of actually executing them.
这其实不完全正确 Well, that's not, that's not quite true.
这里面我们撒了个小谎 There's only one little lie in that.
你需要关心的是如果你有 What you have to worry about is if you have a, a predicate.
如果你有某种测试需要做 If you have some kind of test you want to do
显然，在你编译时 obviously, at the point when you're compiling it
你并不能知道哪个分支需要执行 you don't know which branch of these--of a conditional like this you're going to do.
所以你不能确定求值器将执行哪个 So you can't say which one the evaluator would have done.
在这里要做的很简单 So all you do there is very simple.
你编译全部分支 You compile both branches.
因此你编译一个这样的结构 So you compile a structure that looks like this.
他们都会被编译成P的代码 That'll compile into something that says, the code, the code for P.
And it puts its results in, say, the val register.
So you walk the interpreter over the predicate
and make sure that the result would go into the val register.
And then you compile an instruction that says
branch if, if val is true
to a place we'll call label one.
Then we, we will put the code for B to walk the interpreter--walk the interpreter over B.
And then go to put in an instruction that says, go to the next thing, whatever
whatever was supposed to happen after this thing was done.
你放入那个指令 You put in that instruction.
这里你放入label one And here you put label one.
And here you put the code for A.
And you put go to next thing.
这就是处理条件分支的办法 So that's how you treat a conditional.
你生成这样一小块代码 You generate a little block like that.
除此之外 And other than that
编译器与求值器一模一样 this zeroth-order compiler is the same as the evaluator.
它只是把指令存起来而不是执行它们 It's just stashing away the instructions instead of executing them.
看起来肯简单，但我们已经因此有了一些收获 That seems pretty simple, but we've gained something by that.
它会比求值器更有效率 See, already that's going to be more efficient than the evaluator.
因为，如果你观察求值器的运行 Because, if you watch the evaluator run
它并不只是生成我们写下的注册操作 it's not only generating the register operations we wrote down
它还会决定生成哪个 it's also doing things to decide which ones to generate.
它做的第一件事就是 So the very first thing it does, say
here for instance, is go do some tests and decide that this is an application
and then branch off to the place that, that handles applications.
换句话说，求值器做的事情是 In other words, what the evaluator's doing
在分析代码看看需要做什么的同时 is simultaneously analyzing the code to see what to do
运行这些操作 and running these operations.
当你运行求值器一百万次 And when you-- if you run the evaluator a million times
这个分析过程就进行一百万次 that analysis phase happens a million times
而在编译器中它只会进行一次 whereas in the compiler, it's happened once
之后就只有寄存器操作了 and then you just have the register operations themselves.
这就是零阶编译器TBD Ok, that's a, a zeroth-order compiler
但它是个很挫的编译器 but it is a wretched, wretched compiler.
它很蠢 It's really dumb.
让我们回来，TBD Let's--let's go back and, and look at this overhead.
看看这个东西做的一些操作 So look at look at some of the operations this thing is doing.
我们想看看 (F  X) 的操作和解释过程 We're supposedly looking at the operations and interpreting f of x.
这里就是它做了什么 Now, look here what it's doing.
举个例子，这里 For example, here
它将(operator (fetch exp))赋值给 exp it assigns to exp the operator in fetch of exp.
看，没理由干这个 But see, there's no reason to do that, because this is--
因为编译器知道(operator (fetch exp))在这里就是F the compiler knows that the operator, fetch of exp, is f right here.
因此这个指令没理由存在 So there's no reason why this instruction should say that.
它应该表达，我们要把F赋值给exp It should say, we'll assign to exp, f.
或者实际上，你完全不需要exp Or in fact, you don't need exp at all.
没有理由显示需要exp There's no reason it should have exp at all.
exp是用来做什么的？我们看这里 What, what did exp get used for? Well, if we come down here
我们对val赋值 we're going to assign to val
在环境里的exp里寻找东西 look up the stuff in exp in the environment.
因此在这里我们实际上要做的是TBD So what we really should do is get rid of the exp register altogether
只修改指令为，引用val and just change this instruction to say, assign to val
在环境中查找符号f的值 look up the variable value of the symbol f in the environment.
类似地 Similarly
回到这里，我们完全不需要unev back up here, we don't need unev at all
因为我们知道 because we know
因为我们知道这一块代码要从exp中找的操作数 what the operands of fetch of exp are for this piece of code.
就是列表x It's the, it's the list x.
从某种意义上来说 So in some sense
你想完全抛掉unev和exp you don't want unev and exp at all.
See, what they really are in some sense
它们不是它们实际运行机器的寄存器 those aren't registers of the actual machine that's supposed to run.
它们是用来模拟那台机器的寄存器 Those are registers that have to do with arranging the thing that can simulate that machine.
So they're always going to hold expressions which
from the compiler's point of view, are just constants, so can be put right into the code.
所以你可以忘掉对于exp和unev的操作，只用那些常量 So you can forget about all the operations worrying about exp and unev and just use those constants.
与之相似，如果我们回顾这里 Similarly, again, if we go, go back and look here
there are things like assign to continue eval-args.
现在它没啥事情需要做了 Now, that has nothing to do with anything.
它只是求值器维护了下一步需要去哪 That was just the evaluator keeping track of where it should go next
to evaluate the arguments in some, in some application.
当然，这与编译器没关系 But of course, that's irrelevant to the compiler, because you--
因为这个分析过程已经被编译器干完了the analysis phase will have already done that.
这与我们的主题完全无关 So this is completely irrelevant.
So a lot of these, these assignments to continue have not to do where the running machine is supposed to continue in keeping track of its state.
It has to, to do with where the evaluator analysis should continue
TBD它们是完全无关的，所以我的可以去掉它们 and those are completely irrelevant. So we can get rid of them.
Ok, well, if we, if we simply do that
make those kinds of optimizations
get rid, get rid of worrying about exp and unev
and get rid of these irrelevant register assignments to continue
then we can take this literal code
these sort of 19 instructions that the
that the evaluator would have done
and then replace them.
大家看幻灯片 Let's look at the, at the slide.
我们去掉其中一半 Replace them by--we get rid of about half of them.
同样，这就是求值器做的某种过滤 And again, this is just sort of filtering
把无关的东西去掉 what the evaluator would have done by getting rid of the irrelevant stuff.
你看 And you see, for instance
here the--where the evaluator said, assign val, look up variable value
fetch of exp, here we have put in the constant f.
这里我的放了常量x Here we've put in the constant x.
因此这是个稍好一些的编译器 So there's a, there's a little better compiler.
但它还是比较蠢 It's still pretty dumb.
它仍会做很多蠢事 It's still doing a lot of dumb things.
我们再看幻灯片 Again, if we go look at the slide again
看最开头的地方 look at the very beginning here
能发现保存环境 we see a save the environment
把某些东西赋值给val寄存器 assign something to the val register
然后恢复环境and restore the environment.
它是从哪来的 Where'd that come from?
它来自求值器的这个地方 That came from the evaluator back here saying
哦，我在求值一个应用的过程中 oh, I'm in the middle of evaluating an application.
所以我要递归调用eval dispatch So I'm going to recursively call eval dispatch.
我最好把接下来要用到的东西存下来，存到环境里 So I'd better save the thing I'm going to need later, which is the environment.
这就是递归调用eval dispatch的结果 This was the result of recursively calling eval dispatch.
在刚才这个例子中是对符号f进行求值 It was evaluating the symbol f in that case.
从eval dispatch中返回，将环境恢复 Then it came back from eval dispatch, restored the environment.
实际上，这个求值过程中的进行的操作 But in fact, the actual thing it ended up doing
完全不会影响环境 in the evaluation is not going to hurt the environment at all.
所以这里没必要保存环境再恢复环境 So there's no reason to be saving the environment and restoring the environment here.
与之类似 Similarly
这里我们保存了参数列表 here I'm saving the argument list.
那是一个参数求值循环，保存参数列表 That's a piece of the argument evaluation loop, saving the argument list
在这里恢复参数列表 and here you restore it.
事实上最后 But the actual thing that you ended up doing
并没有变更参数列表 didn't trash the argument list.
所以不需要保存它 So there was no reason to save it.
So another way to say, another way to say that
求值器不得不最大限度的保持悲观 is that the, the evaluator has to be maximally pessimistic
因为，从它的视角来看，只知道接下来是要对某些东西进行求值 because as far from its point of view it's just going off to evaluate something.
所以最好把后面要用到的都存下来 So it better save what it's going to need later.
一旦你完成了分析，编译器就是从另一种视角看问题了 But once you've done the analysis, the compiler is in a position to say
哪些是我真正需要存下来的？ well, what actually did I need to save?
它不需要像求值器一样小心翼翼 And doesn't need to do any-- it doesn't need to be as careful as the evaluator
因为它知道哪些才是真正需要的 because it knows what it actually needs
在任何情况下，如果我们Well, in any case, if we do that
去除所有多余的保存和恢复 and eliminate all those redundant saves and restores
那么我们可以把它记下来TBD then we can get it down to this.
可以发现，只有三个指令是必须的 And you see there are actually only three instructions that we actually need
down from the initial 11 or so
or the initial 20 or so in the original one.
对于这些寄存器操作 And that's just saying, of those register operations
哪些是必需的？ which ones did we actually need?
我们换个方式概括，来看看稍好一些的图片 Let me just sort of summarize that in another way, just to show you in a little better picture.
Here's a picture of starting--
This is looking at all the saves and restores.
So here's the expression, f of x
and then this traces through, on the bottom here
the various places in the evaluator
that were passed when the evaluation happened.
在这，你可以看到箭头 And then here, here you see arrows.
向下的箭头表示register保存了 Arrow down means register saved.
所以发生的第一件事就是保存环境 So the first thing that happened is the environment got saved.
在这，环境恢复了 And over here, the environment got restored.
这些，都是成对的栈操作 And these-- so there are all the pairs of stack operations.
Now, if you go ahead and say
well, let's remember that we don't--that unev
unev是个完全无用的registerfor instance, is a completely useless register.
如果我们用固定结构的代码 And if we use the constant structure of the code
我们就不需要保存unev，我们完全不需要unev well, we don't need, we don't need to save unev.
And then, depending on how we set up the discipline of the--
of calling other things that apply, we may or may not need to save continue.
这就是我们做的第一件事 That's the first step I did.
然后我们可以看看，什么是真正需要的 And then we can look and see what's actually, what's actually needed.
我们其实不需要保存env See, we don't-- didn't really need to save env
or cross-evaluating f
because it wouldn't, it wouldn't trash it.
因此，如果我们可以借助这一特点 So if we take advantage of that
这里对f的求值 and see the evaluation of f here
完全不需要担心会破坏env doesn't really need to worry about, about hurting env.
类似地，对于x的求值 And similarly, the evaluation of x here
当求值器进行求值时，它会说: 噢 when the evaluator did that it said
我最好保存好与之有关的函数寄存器 I'd better preserve the function register around that
因为我过会可能会需要它们 because I might need it later.
我最好保存参数列表 And I better preserve the argument list.
然而，在这如果是编译器的话 Whereas the compiler is now in a position to know
它会知道我们实际上不需要进行那些保存和恢复 well, we didn't really need to save-- to do those saves and restores.
事实上，求值器做的所有栈操作 So in fact, all of the stack operations
都是不必要的或过于悲观的 done by the evaluator turned out to be unnecessary or overly pessimistic.
而编译器在这里是知道的 And the compiler is in a position to know that.
这是最基础的想法 Well that's the basic idea.
我们拿来求值器 We take the evaluator
去除你不需要的东西 we eliminate the things that you don't need
去除那些对于编译器完全无用的东西， that in some sense have nothing to do with the compiler at all
只剩下求值器 just the evaluator
然后你可以看到哪些栈操作是不必要的 and then you see which stack operations are unnecessary.
这就是书中说的编译器的基本结构 That's the basic structure of the compiler that's described in the book.
我给你展示一下这个例子有多简单？？ Let me just show you how that examples a little bit too simple.
为了展示你是如何保存了多余的东西 To see how you, how you actually save a lot
我们来看看这个稍复杂的表达式 let's look at a little bit more complicated expression.
(F (G X) 1)
我们不会浏览所有的代码 And I'm not going to go through all the code.
因为代码有点多 There's a, there's a fair pile of it.
I think there are, there are something like 16 pairs of register saves and restores as the evaluator walks through that.
这有一张图表 Here's a diagram of them.
你可以看到发生了什么 Let's see. You see what's going on.
你从这里开始-- You start out by--
我即将进行应用 the evaluator says, oh, I'm about to do an application.
我要保存环境, 从这里恢复环境 I'll preserve the environment. I'll restore it here.
然后我要进行第一个操作 Then I'm about to do the first operand.
这是一个调用求值器的递归 Here it recursively goes to the evaluator.
求值器说，这是一个应用，我要保存环境 The evaluator says, oh, this is an application, I'll save the environment
进行组合操作，在这恢复环境 do the operator of that combination, restore it here.
这个保存，这个恢复与这个保存相匹配 This save--this restore matches that save.
以此类推 And so on.
这里的unev完全没有必要存在 There's unev here, which turns out to be completely unnecessary
continues getting bumped around here.
The function register is getting, getting saved across the first operands, across the operands.
All sorts of things are going on.
But if you say, well, what of those really were the business of
the compiler as opposed to the evaluator
you get rid of a whole bunch.
And then on top of that, if you say things like
对F的求值不会破坏环境寄存器 the evaluation of F doesn't hurt the environment register,
或者对符号X的查找 or simply looking up the symbol X,
你不需要为了它们保护函数寄存器 you don't have to protect the function register against that.
因此你归结为这里的一对？   So you come down to just a couple of, a couple of pairs here.
然而，你还可以再优化一下 And still, you can do a little better.
看看这里的环境寄存器发生了什么 Look what's going on here with the environment register.
环境寄存器来了，说 The environment register comes along and says, oh,
噢，这是一个组合操作 oh, here's a combination.
这个求值器 This evaluator, by the way,
不知道关于G的任何事情 doesn't know anything about G.
所以在这，它说 So here it says, so it says,
我最好保存环境寄存器 I'd better save the environment register,
因为对G的求值可能有某些代码会破坏它 because evaluating G might be some arbitrary piece of code that would trash it
而我过一会可能会需要它 and I'm going to need it later,
在这个参数之后 after this argument,
处理第二个参数的时候 for doing the second argument.
这就是为什么这个东西没被干掉 So that's why this one didn't go away,
因为编译器没有对G将要做的事情做任何假设 because the compiler made no assumptions about what G would do.
另一方面 On the other hand,
如果你看看这里的第二个参数 if you look at what the second argument is,
它只是一次查找 that's just looking up one.
的确不需要这个环境寄存器 That doesn't need this environment register.
因此没必要保存它 So there's no reason to save it.
这一堆寄存器操作 And from this whole pile of, of register operations,
如果你像之前一样做些简单的推理 if you simply do a little bit of reasoning like that,
只会剩下两对保存和恢复 you get down to, I think, just two pairs of saves and restores.
而这些，如果你知道关于G的某些信息？？ And those, in fact, could go away further if you, if you knew something about G.
通常的想法是 So again, the general idea is
编译器更好的原因是 that the reason the compiler can be better
解释器对于即将遇到的东西一无所知 is that the interpreter doesn't know what it's about to encounter.
它不得不以最悲观的方式保存东西，来保护它自己 It has to be maximally pessimistic in saving things to protect itself.
而编译器只需要处理真正需要保存的东西 The compiler only has to deal with what actually had to be saved.
某个东西不需要保存，有两种可能 And there are two reasons that something might not have to be saved.
一种可能是 One is that what you're protecting it against,
你保存的东西事实上不会修改寄存器 in fact, didn't trash the register,
例如对变量的查找 like it was just a variable look-up.
另一种可能是 And the other one is,
你存的东西最后并不会被用到 that the thing that you were saving it for might turn out not to actually need it.
这就是 So those are the
编译器能让代码运行更有效率的两个基本知识 two basic pieces of knowledge that the compiler can take advantage of in making the code more efficient.
谁要提问吗？ Let's break for questions.
学生：你一直在说非求值寄存器 AUDIENCE: You kept saying that the uneval register,
unev寄存器完全不会被用到 unev register didn't need to be used at all.
这是否意味着你只需要map一个6个寄存器机器？ Does that mean that you could just map a six-register machine?
或者，只是在这个特殊的例子里，它不会被用到？ Or is that, in this particular example, it didn't need to be used?
教授：对于编译器 PROFESSOR: For the compiler,
你可以生成6个寄存器 you could generate code for the six-register,
其实是5个寄存器的代码，因为exp也被干掉了 five, right? Because that exp goes away also.
是的，你可以把exp和unev都去掉 Assuming--yeah, you can get rid of both exp and unev
因为这些是求值器的数据结构 because, see, those are data structures of the evaluator.
以编译器的视角来看，这些东西都是常量 Those are all things that would be constants from the point of view of the compiler.
The only thing is
this particular compiler is set up
因此被解释的代码和被编译的代码可以共存 so that interpreted code and compiled code can coexist.
可以这样看待它 So the way to think about it is,
你构建了一个芯片 is maybe you build a chip
它就是求值器 which is the evaluator,
而编译器可以做的事情是为这个芯片生成代码 and what the compiler might do is generate code for that chip.
It just wouldn't use two of the registers.
好，休息一会 All right, let's take a break.
音乐 [MUSIC PLAYING]
我们刚才研究了编译器会被用来做什么 We just looked at what the compiler is supposed to do.
现在我们来简略看看 Now let's very briefly look at how,
这些目标如何达成 how this gets accomplished.
而我不会给出细节 And I'm going to give no details.
在书中有一大堆代码，展示了所有细节 There's, there's a giant pile of code in the book that gives all the details.
我要做的 But what I want to do is just show you the,
是给你们展示关键的思想 the essential idea here.
换个时间再来关心细节 Worry about the details some other time.
设想我们正在编译表达式 Let's imagine that we're compiling an expression
这里有一些操作符 that looks like there's some operator
和两个参数 and there are two arguments.
现在 Now, the--
这个编译器会生成什么代码？ what's the code that the compiler should generate?
首先 Well, first of all,
它会递归运行 it should recursively go off
编译这些操作符 and compile the operator.
它说，我要编译这些操作符 So it says, I'll compile the operator.
最后我需要的是让它们在函数寄存器中 And where I'm going to need that is to be in the function register, eventually.
所以我编译一些指令 So I'll compile some instructions
它们会编译操作符 that will compile the operator
最后把结果放在函数寄存器中 and end up with the result in the function register.
接下来我要做的是 The next thing it's going to do,
另一个片段说 another piece is to say,
我要编译第一个参数 I have to compile the first argument.
因此它递归调用自己 So it calls itself recursively.
而结果会被放在val中 And let's say the result will go into val.
接下来需要做的是 And then what it's going to need to do is
建立起参数列表 start setting up the argument list.
然而 However,
当它到这里时 it might have to work--  when it gets here,
它可能需要环境 it's going to need the environment.
它需要环境 It's going to need whatever environment was here
为了对第一个参数的求值 in order to do this evaluation of the first argument.
因此它在这做了个标记说 So it puts a note here and says, oh,
这个片段需要保护环境寄存器 this piece should be done preserving the environment register.
与之类似 Similarly, here,
在完成第一个操作数的编译后 after it gets done compiling the first operand,
它会说 it's going to say,
我最好--我需要知道第二个操作数的环境 I better compile-- I'm going to need to know the environment for the second operand.
所以它在这做了个标记说 So it puts a little note here, saying,
这个也需要保护env yeah, this is also done preserving env.
现在它继续运行 Now it goes on and says, well,
下一段代码是要编译第二个参数 the next chunk of code is the one that's going to compile the second argument.
And let's say it'll compile it with a targeted to val, as they say.
随后它会生成一个字面指令 And then it'll generate the literal instruction,
building up the argument list.
So it'll say, assign to argl cons of the new value it just got onto the old argument list.
然而 However,
为了对旧参数列表的需要 in order to have the old argument list,
最好让在这发生的任何事情 it better have arranged that the argument list didn't get trashed
都不影响旧的参数列表 by whatever happened in here.
因此它在这做了个标记说 So it puts a little note here and says,
噢，这里需要保存argl oh, this has to be done preserving argl.
现在参数列表建立好了 Now it's got the argument list set up.
And it's all ready to go to apply dispatch.
它生成了这个字面指令 It generates this literal instruction.
因为现在参数在argl中 Because now it's got the arguments in argl
and the operator in fun,
but wait, it's only got the operator in fun
if it had ensured that this block of code didn't trash what was in the function register.
所以它在这做了个小标记 So it puts a little note here and says,
So that's the little--so when it starts ticking--
so basically, what the compiler does is append a whole bunch of code sequences.
See, what it's got in it is little primitive pieces of things
like how to look up a symbol,
how to do a conditional.
Those are all little pieces of things.
然后它将这些连接到一起 And then it appends them together in this sort of discipline.
组合的基本意思是 So the basic means of combining things
将两个代码序列连接到一起 is to append two code sequences.
就是这里发生的事情 That's what's going on here.
And it's a little bit tricky.
思路是，它连接两个代码序列 The idea is that it appends two code sequences,
小心保护寄存器 taking care to preserve a register.
附加操作看起来像这样 So the actual append operation looks like this.
What it wants to do is say, if--
here's what it means to append two code sequences.
如果序列1需要寄存器--我应该改一下这个 So if sequence one needs register--  I should change this.
将序列1附加到序列2后 Append sequence one to sequence two,
保护一些寄存器 preserving some register.
Let me say, and.
很清楚，序列1先来的 So it's clear that sequence one comes first.
如果序列2需要寄存器 So if sequence two needs the register
并且序列1修改了寄存器 and sequence one modifies the register,
then the instructions that the compiler spits out are, save the register.
这就是代码 Here's the code.
你生成了这段代码 You generate this code.
保存寄存器 Save the register,
and then you put out the recursively compiled stuff for sequence one.
然后你恢复寄存器 And then you restore the register.
然后你??由序列2递归编译得到的东西 And then you put out the recursively compiled stuff for sequence two.
这就是在这里你需要的东西 That's in the case where you need to do it.
实际上序列2需要寄存器 Sequence two actually needs the register,
而序列1改动了它 and sequence one actually clobbers it.
So that's sort of if. Otherwise,
all you spit out is sequence one followed by sequence two.
So that's the basic operation for sticking together these bits of code fragments,
these bits of instructions into a sequence.
从这个角度看 And you see, from this point of view,
解释器和编译器的区别 the difference between the interpreter and the compiler, in some sense,
是编译器有这些保存标记 is that where the compiler has these preserving notes,
上面记录着，哪些需要生成保存和恢复的代码，哪些不需要 and says, maybe I'll actually generate the saves and restores and maybe I won't,
而解释器会以最大限度的消极方式处理，总是会进行保存和恢复 the interpreter being maximally pessimistic always has a save and restore here.
这就是关键的区别 That's the essential difference.
为了实现这个 Well, in order to do this, of course,
the compiler needs some theory of what code sequences need and modifier registers.
所以你放入的小片段 So the tiny little fragments that you put in,
例如这个基础原始代码片段 like the basic primitive code fragments,
表达了，当你查找一个变量时要做哪些操作？ say, what are the operations that you do when you look up a variable?
当编译一个常量或应用一个函数时，你需要做哪些事情？ What are the sequence of things that you do when you compile a constant or apply a function?
这里有关于它们需要什么和它们会修改什么的这些小标识 Those have little notations in there about what they need and what they modify.
So the bottom-level data structures--
Well, I'll say this.
编译器的代码序列是这个样子的 A code sequence to the compiler looks like this.
它里面有实际上指令的序列 It has the actual sequence of instructions.
有一组被修改的寄存器和它在一起 And then, along with it, there's the set of registers modified.
然后这些是所需要的寄存器 And then there's the set of registers needed.
So that's the information the compiler has that it draws on in order to be able to do this operation.
它们从哪来呢 And where do those come from?
Well, those come from, you might expect, for the very primitive ones, we're going to put them in by hand.
And then, when we combine two sequences, we'll figure out what these things should be.
举一个非常原始的例子 So for example, a very primitive one, let's see.
做一个寄存器赋值 How about doing a register assignment.
所以原始序列会说，噢，它是个代码片段 So a primitive sequence might say, oh, it's code fragment.
Its code instruction is assigned to R1, fetch of R2.
这是个例子 So this is an example.
这是指令序列的一个例子 That might be an example of a sequence of instructions.
And along with that, it'll say,
oh, what I need to remember is that that modifies R1
and then it needs R2.
当你一开始构建编译器时 So when you're first building this compiler,
你放入这样的一个片段 you put in little fragments of stuff like that.
当它组合两个序列时 And now, when it combines two sequences,
if I'm going to combine,
let's say, sequence one, that modifies a bunch of registers M1,
and needs a bunch of registers N1.
And I'm going to combine that with sequence two.
That modifies a bunch of registers M2,
and needs a bunch of registers N2.
Then, well, we can reason it out.
新的代码片段，序列1 The new code fragment, sequence one,
后面是序列2 and-- followed by sequence two,
它要修改什么？ well, what's it going to modify?
它要修改的东西是会被序列1和序列2修改 The things that it will modify are the things that are modified either by sequence one or sequence two.
所以这两个集合的合集就是要被修改的东西 So the union of these two sets are what the new thing modifies.
然后你问 And then you say, well, what is this--
哪些寄存器是需要的？ what registers is it going to need?
需要这些寄存器的是 It's going to need the things that are,
首先，序列1需要 first of all, needed by sequence one.
So what it needs is sequence one.
然后，并不是所有都被序列1需要  And then, well, not quite all of the ones that are needed by sequence one.
What it needs are the ones that are needed by sequence two
that have not been set up by sequence one.
So it's sort of the union of the things that sequence two needs minus the ones that sequence one modifies.
因为它关心的是建立它们 Because it worries about setting them up.
这就是编译器的基本结构 So there's the basic structure of the compiler.
寄存器优化的方式是 The way you do register optimizations  is
你有一些策略应对需要保护的东西 you have some strategies for what needs to be preserved.
这取决于数据结构 That depends on a data structure.
这取决于将东西组合在一起的操作 Well, it depends on the operation of what it means to put things together.
想知道要保护哪些东西 Preserving something,
需要知道那些寄存器是需要的并且被这些代码片段修改 that depends on knowing what registers are needed and modified by these code fragments.
那取决于小数据结构 That depends on having little data structures,
which say, a code sequence is the actual instructions,
what they modify and what they need.
That comes from, at the primitive level, building it in.
在底层，哪些是被需要的，哪些是被修改的，是显而易见的事情 At the primitive level, it's going to be completely obvious what something needs and modifies.
另外 Plus,
显而易见，当我构建一个 bigger ones的时候 this particular way that says, when I build up bigger ones,
这是我如何生成被修改的寄存器的集合 here's how I generate the new set of registers modified
和被需要的寄存器的集合 and the new set of registers needed.
这就是全部的，我不应该说这就是全部内容 And that's the whole-- well, I shouldn't say that's the whole thing.
这就是除了书中30页关于细节的内容之外的全部内容 That's the whole thing except for about 30 pages of details in the book.
但它是一个完全可用的初级编译器 But it is a perfectly usable rudimentary compiler.
让我给你展示一下它能做什么 Let me kind of show you what it does.
假设我们从一个递归阶乘开始 Suppose we start out with recursive factorial.
这些幻灯片的字太小了 And these slides are going to be much too small to read.
我只想快速翻一下代码，让你们看看它有多少代码 I just want to flash through the code and show you about how much it is.
代码从这开始-- That starts out with--
这是代码的第一部分 here's a first block of it,
这里编译了一个过程入口，进行了一些赋值操作 where it compiles a procedure entry and does a bunch of assignments.
And this thing is basically up through the part where it sets up to do the predicate and test whether the predicate's true.
sets up to do the predicate
and test whether the predicate's true.
第二部分是 The second part is
递归调用n-1的阶乘的结果 is what results from-- in the recursive call to fact of n minus one.
最后一部分是 And this last part
is coming back from that and then taking care of the constant case.
这就是产生阶乘会生成的代码量 So that's about how much code it would produce for factorial.
我们当然可以把这个编译器做得更好 We could make this compiler much, much better, of course.
优化它的主要方式是 The main way we could make it better is
当你调用一个过程时允许编译器做任何假设 to allow the compiler to make any assumptions at all about what happens when you call a procedure.
So this compiler, for instance,
doesn't even know, say, that multiplication is something that could be coded in line.
它构建起整个机制 Instead, it sets up this whole mechanism.
It goes to apply-dispatch.
That's a tremendous waste,
because what you do every time you go to apply-dispatch
is you have to concept this argument list,
because it's a very general thing you're going to.
在任何真实的编译器中 In any real compiler, of course,
你会有寄存器来暂存参数 you're going to have registers for holding arguments.
And you're going to start preserving
saving the way you use those registers
similar to the same strategy here.
这可能是这个书中特定的编译器可以优化的最主要的方式 So that's probably the very main way that this particular compiler in the book could be fixed.
还有其他的一些方法 There are other things like
looking up variable values and making more efficient primitive operations, and all sorts of things.
本质上来说，一个好的Lisp编译器，可以吸收任何的努力成果 Essentially, a good Lisp compiler can absorb an arbitrary amount of effort.
可能这其中的一个原因是 And probably one of the reasons
lisp比其他如FORTRAN之类的语言运行要慢 Lisp is slow with compared to languages like FORTRAN
如果你研究人们为构建Lisp编译器所付出努力的历史 is that, if you look over history at the amount of effort that's gone into building Lisp compilers,
几乎与构建FORTRAN编译器差不多 it's nowhere near the amount of effort that's gone into FORTRAN compilers.
可能在接下来的几年情况会改变 And maybe that's something that will change over the next couple of years.
OK, let's break.
有问题吗 Questions?
学生: 很早的一个课时里-- AUDIENCE: One of the very first classes--
我不记得是课上还是课后-- I don't know if it was during class or after class-
you showed me the, say, addition has a primitive that we don't see, and-percent add or something like that.
Is that because,
if you're doing inline code you'd want to just do it for two operators, operands?
但如果你有更多操作数，你会做什么特殊的事情吗？ But if you had more operands, you'd want to do something special?
教授：你看了真实的scheme实现 PROFESSOR: Yeah, you're looking in the actual scheme implementation.
有一个plus，它是某种操作符 There's a plus, and a plus is some operator.
如果你看plus的源代码 And then if you go look inside the code for plus,
你会看到一些叫做-- you see something called--
我记不清了--可能叫and-percent plus或之类的东西 I forget-- and-percent plus or something like that.
这里做的就是那种特殊的优化 And what's going on there is that particular kind of optimization.
因为，通常plus接受任意数量的参数 Because, see, general plus takes an arbitrary number of arguments.
所以，最通常的plus So the most general plus
会认为如果我有一个参数列表 says, oh, if I have an argument list,
我最好将它们用cons连接到列表里 I'd better cons it up in some list
and then figure out how many there were or something like that.
这样的效率非常差 That's terribly inefficient,
因为大部分时间你在把两个数相加 especially since most of the time you're probably adding two numbers.
你不想真的把整个参数列表连接到一起 You don't want to really have to cons this argument list.
所以你想做的是 So what you'd like to do is
构建把一堆东西相加的代码 build the code for plus with a bunch of entries.
所以它做的大部分是请是一样的 So most of what it's doing is the same.
However, there might be a special entry that you'd go to if you knew there were only two arguments.
And those you'll put in registers.
They won't be in an argument list and you won't have to [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
That's how a lot of these things work.
下课 OK, let's take a break.
音乐 [MUSIC PLAYING]