现在，我们已经拥有了通过改变局部状态进行对象建模的力量，我想我们应该找点复杂的东西来演示一下这种力量是多么强大
假设，我们处在这样一个物理系统中，系统中的事物驱动彼此，全部的这些事物组成了世界
每一个事物都有其独立的局部状态
这决定了它属于一个事物
这个模型存在于我们的大脑里，当然它也可以存在于计算机中
我要做的是，把真实世界中事物，相应地在计算机中建立对象，真实世界中事物的联系，相应地在计算机建立对象间的关系，对象与关系与现实世界的事物与联系一一对应
这也就指引了我们如何去模块化
如果我们真的把世界想象成这样，由许多小的事物组成，我们就可以一一对其建模，这样就把世界的模块性传递到了我们的程序这中
这就是面向对象编程的原理所在
我所见过的最完美的对象
非常非常完美，那就是电气系统。电气系统真的是物理学家构造的非常非常好的一种对象
这里我有一些机器零件
确实是机器零件
有一个电线连接起了零件的两个部分
电气世界中有一个非常棒的特性，就是我可以说这是一个对象，这是一个对象，这两个对象连接起来，所有关系一目了然
而且，如果我没有用电线连接，它们便没有关系
比如我有一个灯泡，一个已经接在插座上的电源
关系非常明了
没有另外的关系表现形式
就算我把电线打个结，灯仍然是亮着的
没什么影响
在物理上，这种连接可以被抽象出来，至少在低频状态下是可以的
而且这就是全部的连接方式了
当然，我们来进一步讨论一种在电气系统中最为广泛的抽象，数字电路
这有一些对象元件
例如，在数字电路里我们有像非门这样的东西
还有与门
或门
我们用电线把它们连接起来，电线就是对01信号的抽象
我们不关心具体的物理因素，像电压啊，电流啊，元件怎么组合啊 等等
这些因素统一抽象为信号
我们用电路连接元件，构建系统
一会儿我要向你们介绍一种新的语言，像之前讲过的图形语言一样，都嵌入在LISP中，不是昨天那种模式匹配替换的语言
模式匹配替换的语言还需要用LISP编写另外的程序来解释
但是之前那种绘图语言我们可以随意使用，不管构造过程还是组合数据
举例来说，首先我要有一些原子对象，比如这个，这个
然后用电线去组合它们
(make-wire)构造一个电线
a就代表了一根电线
b也是
c也是
d也是
还有e
还有s
再来看元件，或门有两个输入a和b，一个输出d，就像这样
与门，a和b两个输入，一个输出c
就像这样来声明，我可以组合出任意的电路
我已经说明了原子元素，组合方法，然后就轮到抽象方法了
举例来说，这是一个半加器
如果你学过电路设计肯定知道这个东西
输入两个数a和b，输出“和”和进位
事实上，完全可以用我刚刚说的来组合电路
把半加器看成一个盒子，盒子的边界，抽象出的永远都是一个盒子
从盒子里引出A B S C四根线
这些是已经声明了的变量，我们就用它们来定义半加器
为了连接半加器里面的线路，我构造了电线D和E，E是这个，D是这个，内部连接的线路并没有引出盒子之外，就像这样连起来
你可以看的出来，这个语言非常有层次性
如果一个语言没有层次性，如果你不能把一个复合对象当成原子对象来使用，这个语言肯定是有问题的 -- 至少我这样觉得
之前我们都是从计算一些数字上的函数开始的，现在我们不那样做，我们从一些电路对象开始，构建更多的电路对象
用LISP里的lambda将其粘合起来
lambda是很有用的粘合剂
当然，两个半加器可以组成结构更为复杂的全加器，就像这里这个，把线路连在一起，还需要另外的电线如S，C1和C2，还有一个或门。全加器输入两个数，一个进位值，输出“和”和一个进位值
除此之外，还可以把全加器链起来组成更大的加法器
现在我们的语言有了原子元素，组合方法和抽象方法，才算完整
现在问题来了，如何实现这套语言？
其实并不难
首先来看原子元素
实现原子元素也是整个问题的根本所在
至于组合方法与抽象方法完全不用亲自实现，因为语言嵌入在LISP中可以直接使用LISP中的这种机制
好的，我们先来看一个原子元素
非门吧
非门有两个引脚，一个输入，一个输出
有信号输入的时候它要做点什么
它和输入的电线说 -- 我们开始讨论一些关于对象的东西，细节之处以后再谈 -- 它需要对作为输入的电线的说 “当你的值变的时候，告诉我一声”
所以非门可能会这样和这个输入对象交流， “Hi，我是George”
“我的工作就是，当你变化的时候对结果做一点修改”
“所以当你变化的时候，告诉我一声”
“因为我需要这个去做点别的”
我们在这里为in添加一个动作invert-in，它在这里定义，是一个无参数的过程，对线路上的信号取反
在一段延时之后，就是inverter-delay -- 每个电路对象都有延时 -- 我们再把输出设置为新的值
非常简单
你可以这样理解，这个作为输出的电线很有灵性，当信号改变的时候，它就奔走相告
“我的值已经改变啦”
所以当你把非门和与门或者其它的什么连在一起的时候，其中会有很多类似“奔走相告”的过程，确保信号以正确的方式传递
到了这里反而很平常
logical-not只是把0，1换成1，0罢了
与门就相对复杂一些
与门有两个输入A1，A2，输出是output
但是其结构和非门没有什么大的不同
当输入信号改变的时候，就执行过程and-action
And what it does, of course, is nothing more than compute the logical and of the signals on the inputs.
And after some delay, called the and-gate delay, calls this procedure, which sets a signal on the output to a new value.
Now, how I implement these things is all wishful thinking.
As you see here, I have an assignment operation.
It's not set.
It's a derived assignment operation in the same way we had functions that were derived from CAR and CDR. So I, by convention, label that with an exclamation point.
And over here, you see there's an action, which is to inform the wire, called A1 locally in this and-gate, to call the and-action procedure when it gets changed, and the wire A2 to call the and-action procedure when it gets changed.
All very simple.
Well, let's talk a little bit about this communication that must occur between these various parts.
Suppose, for example, I have a very simple circuit which contains an and with wires A and B. And that connects through a wire called C to an inverter which has a wire output called D. What are the comput...--here's the physical world.
It's an abstraction of the physical world.
Now I can buy these out of little pieces that you get at Radio Shack for a few cents.
And there are boxes that act like this, which have little numbers on them like LS04 or something.
Now supposing I were to try to say what's the computational model.
What is the thing that corresponds to that, that part of reality in the mind of us and in the computer?
Well, I have to assign for every object in the world an object in the computer, and for every relationship in the world between them a relationship in the computer.
That's my goal.
So let's do that.
Well, I have some sort of thing called the signal, A.
This is A. It's a signal.
It's a cloudy thing like that.
And I have another one down here which I'm going to call B. It's another signal.
Now this signal--these two signals are somehow going to have to hook together into a box, let's call it this, which is the and-gate, action procedure.
That's the and-gate's action procedure.
And it's going to produce--well, it's going to interact with a signal object, which we call C--a wire object, excuse me, we call C. And then the-- this is going to put out again, or connect to, another action procedure which is one associated with the inverter in the world, not.
And I'm going to have another--another wire, which we'll call D.
So here's my layout of stuff.
Now we have to say what's inside them and what they have to know to compute.
Well, every--every one of these wires has to know what the value of the signal that's on that wire is.
So there's going to be some variable inside here, we'll call it signal.
And he owns a value.
So there must be some environment associated with this.
And for each one of these, there must be an environment that binds signal.
And there must be a signal here, therefore.
And presumably, signal's a value that's either 1 or 0, and signal.
Now, we also have to have some list of people to inform if the signal here changes.
We're going to have to inform this.
So I've got that list. We'll call it the Action Procedures, AP.
And it's presumably a list. But the first thing on the list, in this case, is this guy.
And the action procedures of this one happens to have some list of stuff.
There might be other people who are sharing A, who are looking at it.
So there might be other guys on this list, like somebody over there that we don't know about.
It's the other guy attached to A.
And the action procedure here also has to point to that, the list of action procedures.
And of course, that means this one, its action procedures has to point up to here.
This is the things-- the people it has to inform.
And this guy has some too.
But I don't know what they are because I didn't draw it in my diagram.
It's the things connected to D.
Now, it's also the case that when the and-action procedure is awakened, saying one of the people who know that you've told--one of the people you've told to wake you up if their signal changes, you have to go look and ask them what's their signal so you can do the and, and produce a signal for this one.
So there has to be, for example, information here saying A1, my A1 is this guy, and my A2 is this guy.
And not only that, when I do my and, I'm going to have to tell this guy something.
So I need an output--  being this guy.
And similarly, this guy's going to have a thing called the input that he interrogates to find out what the value of the signal on the input is, when the signal wakes up and says, I've changed, and sends a message this way saying, I've changed.
This guy says, OK, what's your value now?
When he gets that value, then he's going to have to say, OK, output changes this guy, changes this guy.
And so on.
And so I have to have at least that much connected-ness.
Now, let's go back and look, for example, at the and-gate.
Here we are back on this slide.
And we can see some of these parts.
For any particular and-gate, there is an A1, there is an A2, and the output.
And those are, those are an environment that was created at the--those produce a frame at the time and-gate was called, a frame where A1, A2, and output are--have as their values, they're bound to the wires which, they are--which were passed in.
In that environment, I constructed a procedure-- this one right there.
And-action procedure was constructed in that environment.
That was the result of evaluating a lambda expression.
So it hangs onto the frame where these were defined.
Local--part of its local state is that.
The and-action procedure, therefore, has access to A1, A2, and output as we see here.
A1, A2, and output.
Now, we haven't looked inside of a wire yet.
That's all that remains.
Let's look at a wire.
Like the overhead, very good.
Well, the wire, again, is a, is a somewhat complicated mess.
Ooh, wrong one.
It's a big complicated mess, like that.
But let's look at it in detail and see what's going on.
Well, the wire is one of these.
And it has to have two things that are part of it, that it's state.
One of them is the signal we see here.
In other words, when we call make-wire to make a wire, then the first thing we do is we create some variables which are the signal and the action procedures for this wire.
And in that context, we define various functions--or procedures, excuse me, procedures.
One of them is called set-my-signal to a new value.
And what that does is takes a new value in.
If that's equal to my current value of my signal, I'm done.
Otherwise, I set the signal to the new value and call each of the action procedures that I've been, that I've been--what's the right word?--  introduced to.
I get introduced when the and-gate was applied to me.
I add action procedure at the bottom.
Also, I have to define a way of accepting an action procedure-- which is what you see here--- which increments my action procedures using set to the result of CONSing up a new process--a procedure, which is passed to me, on to my actions procedures list. And for technical reasons, I have to call that procedure one.
So I'm not going to tell you anything about that, that has to do with event-driven simulations and getting them started, which takes a little bit of thinking.
And finally, I'm going to define a thing called the dispatcher, which is a way of passing a message to a wire, which is going to be used to extract from it various information, like what is the current signal value?
What is the method of setting your signal?
I want to get that out of it.
How do I--how do I add another action procedure?
And I'm going to return that dispatch, that procedure as a value.
So the wire that I've constructed is a message accepting object which accepts a message like, like what's your method of adding action procedures?
In fact, it'll give me a procedure, which is the add action procedure, which I can then apply to an action procedure to create another action procedure in the wire.
So that's a permission.
So it's given me permission to change your action procedures.
And in fact, you can see that over here.
Next slide.
Ah.
This is nothing very interesting.
The call each of the action procedures is just a CDRing down a list. And I'm not going to even talk about that anymore.
We're too advanced for that.
However, if I want to get a signal from a wire, I ask the wire-- which is, what is the wire?
The wire is the dispatch returned by creating the wire.
It's a procedure.
I call that dispatch on the message get-signal.
And what I should expect to get is a method of getting a signal.
Or actually, I get the signal.
If I want to set a signal, I want to change a signal, then what I'm going to do is take a wire as an argument and a new value for the signal, I'm going to ask the wire for permission to set its signal and use that permission, which is a procedure, on the new value.
And if we go back to the overhead here, thank you, if we go back to the overhead here, we see that the method-- if I ask for the method of setting the signal, that's over here, it's set-my-signal, a procedure that's defined inside the wire, which if we look over here is the thing that says set my internal value called the signal, my internal variable, which is the signal, to the new value, which is passed to me as an argument, and then call each of the action procedures waking them up.
Very simple.
Going back to that slide, we also have the one last thing-- which I suppose now you can easily work out for yourself-- is the way you add an action.
You take a wire--a wire and an action procedure.
And I ask the wire for permission to add an action.
Getting that permission, I use that permission to give it an action procedure.
So that's a real object.
There's a few more details about this.
For example, how am I going to control this thing?
How do I do these delays?
Let's look at that for a second.
The next one here.
Let's see.
We know when we looked at the and-gate or the not-gate that when a signal changed on the input, there was a delay.
And then it was going to call the procedure, which was going to change the output.
Well, how are we going to do this?
We're going to make up some mechanism, a fairly complicated mechanism at that, which we're going to have to be very careful about.
But after a delay, we're going to do an action.
A delay is a number, and an action is a procedure.
What that's going to be is they're going to have a special structure called an agenda, which is a thing that organizes time and actions.
And we're going to see that in a while.
I don't want to get into that right now.
But the agenda has a moment at which--at which something happens.
We're setting up for later at some moment, which is the sum of the time, which is the delay time plus the current time, which the agenda thinks is now.
We're going to set up to do this action, and add that to the agenda.
And the way this machine will now run is very simple.
We have a thing called propagate, which is the way things run.
If the agenda is empty, we're done--if there's nothing more to be done.
Otherwise, we're going to take the first item off the agenda, and that's a procedure of no arguments.
So that we're going to see extra parentheses here.
We call that on no arguments.
That takes the action.
Then we remove that first item from the agenda, and we go around the propagation loop.
So that's the overall structure of this thing.
Now, there's a, a few other things we can look at.
And then we're going to look into the agenda a little while from now.
Now the overhead again.
Well, in order to set this thing going, I just want to show you some behavior out of this simulator.
By the way, you may think this simulator is very simple, and probably too simple to be useful.
The fact of the matter is that this simulator has been used to manufacture a fairly large computer.
So this is a real live example.
Actually, not exactly this simulator, because I'll tell you the difference.
The difference is that there were many more different kinds of primitives.
There's not just the word inverter or and-gate.
There were things like edge-triggered, flip-flops, and latches, transparent latches, and adders, and things like that.
And the difficulty with that is that there's pages and pages of the definitions of all these primitives with numbers like LS04.
And then there's many more parameters for them.
It's not just one delay.
There's things like set up times and hold times and all that.
But with the exception of that part of the complexity, the structure of the simulator that we use for building a real computer, that works is exactly what you're seeing here.
Well in any case, what we have here is a few simple things.
Like, there's inverter delays being set up and making a new agenda.
And then we can make some inputs.
There's input-1, input-2, a sum and a carry, which are wires.
I'm going to put a special kind of object called a probe onto, onto some of the wires, onto sum and onto carry.
A probe is a, can object that has the property that when you change a wire it's attached to, it types out a message.
It's an easy thing to do.
And then once we have that, of course, the way you put the probe on, the first thing it does, it says, the current value of the sum at time 0 is 0 because I just noticed it.
And the value of the carry at time 0, this is the time, is 0.
And then we go off and we build some structure.
Like, we can build a structure here that says you have a half-adder on input-1, input-2, sum, and carry.
And we're going to set the signal on input-1 to 1.
We do some propagation.
At time 8, which you could see going through this thing if you wanted to, the new value of sum became 1.
And the thing says I'm done.
That wasn't very interesting.
But we can send it some more signals.
Like, we set-signal on input-2 to be one.
And at that time if we propagate, then it carried at 11, the carry becomes 1, and at 16, the sum's new value becomes 0.
And you might want to work out that, if you like, about the digital circuitry.
It's true, and it works.
And it's not very interesting.
But that's the kind of behavior we get out of this thing.
So what I've shown you right now is a large-scale picture, how you, at a bigger, big scale, you implement an event-driven simulation of some sort.
And how you might organize it to have nice hierarchical structure allowing you to build abstract boxes that you can instantiate.
But I haven't told you any of the details about how this agenda and things like that work.
That we'll do next.
And that's going to involve change and mutation of data and things like that.
Are there any questions now, before I go on?
Thank you.
Let's take a break.
Well, we've been making a simulation.
And the simulation is an event-driven simulation where the objects in the world are the objects in the computer.
And the changes of state that are happening in the world in time are organized to be time in the computer, so that if something happens after something else in the world, then we have it happen after, after the corresponding events happen in the same order in the computer.
That's where we have assignments, when we make that alignment.
Right now I want to show you a way of organizing time, which is an agenda or priority queue, it's sometimes called.
We'll do some--we'll do a little bit of just understanding what are the things we need to be able to do to make agendas.
And so we're going to have--and so right now over here, I'm going to write down a bunch of primitive operations for manipulating agendas.
I'm not going to show you the code for them because they're all very simple, and you've got listings of all that anyway.
So what do we have?
We have things like make-agenda which produces a new agenda.
We can ask--we get the current-time of an agenda, which gives me a number, a time.
We can get--we can ask whether an agenda is empty, empty-agenda.
And that produces either a true or a false.
We can add an object to an agenda.
Actually, what we add to an agenda is an operation--an action to be done.
And that takes a time, the action itself, and the agenda I want to add it to.
That inserts it in the appropriate place in the agenda.
I can get the first item off an agenda, the first thing I have to do, which is going to give me an action.
And I can remove the first item from an agenda.
That's what I have to be able to do with agendas.
That is a big complicated mess.
From an agenda.
Well, let's see how we can organize this thing as a data structure a bit.
Well, an agenda is going to be some kind of list. And it's going to be a list that I'm going to have to be able to modify.
So we have to talk about modifying of lists, because I'm going to add things to it, and delete things from it, and things like that.
It's organized by time.
It's probably good to keep it in sorted order.
But sometimes there are lots of things that happen at the same time--approximate same time.
What I have to do is say, group things by the time at which they're supposed to happen.
So I'm going to make an agenda as a list of segments.
And so I'm going to draw you a data structure for an agenda, a perfectly reasonable one.
Here's an agenda.
It's a thing that begins with a name.
I'm going to do it right now out of list structure.
It's got a header.
There's a reason for the header.
We're going to see the reason soon.
And it will have a segment.
It will have--it will be a list of segments.
Supposing this agenda has two segments, they're the car's-- successive car's of this list. Each segment is going to have a time--  say for example, 10-- that says that the things that happen in this segment are at time 10.
And what I'm going to have in here is another data structure which I'm not going to describe, which is a queue of things to do at time 10.
It's a queue.
And we'll talk about that in a second.
But abstractly, the queue is just a list of things to do at a particular time.
And I can add things to a queue.
This is a queue.
There's a time, there's a segment.
Now, I may have another segment in this agenda.
Supposing this is stuff that happens at time 30.
It has, of course, another queue of things that are queued up to be done at time 30.
Well, there are various things I have to be able to do to an agenda.
Supposing I want to add to an agenda another thing to be done at time 10.
Well, that's not very hard.
I'm going to walk down here, looking for the segment of time 10.
It is possible that there is no segment of time 10.
We'll cover that case in a second.
But if I find a segment of time 10, then if I want to add another thing to be done at time 10, I just increase that queue-- "just increase" isn't such an obvious idea.
But I increase the things to be done at that time.
Now, supposing I want to add something to be done at time 20.
There is no segment for time 20.
I'm going to have to create a new segment.
I want my time 20 segment to exist between time 10 and time 30.
Well, that takes a little work.
I'm going to have to do a CONS.
I'm going to have to make a new element of the agenda list--list of segments.
I'm going to have to change.
Here's change.
I'm going to have to change the CDR of the CDR of the agenda to point that a new CONS of the new segment and the CDR of the CDR of the CDR of the agenda, the CD-D-D-DR.
And this is going to have a new segment now of time 20 with its own queue, which now has one element in it.
If I wanted to add something at the end, I'm going to have to replace the CDR of this, of this list with something.
We're going to have to change that piece of data structure.
So I'm going to need new primitives for doing this.
But I'm just showing you why I need them.
And finally, if I wanted to add a thing to be done at time 5, I'm going to have to change this one, because I'm going to have to add it in over here, which is why I planned ahead and had a header cell, which has a place.
If I'm going to change things, I have to have places for the change.
I have to have a place to make the change.
If I remove things from the agenda, that's not so hard.
Removing them from the beginning is pretty easy, which is the only case I have. I can go looking for the first, the first segment.
I see if it has a non-empty queue.
If it has a non-empty queue, well, I'm going to delete one element from the queue, like that.
If the queue ever becomes empty, then I have to delete the whole segment.
And then this, this changes to point to here.
So it's quite a complicated data structure manipulation going on, the details of which are not really very exciting.
Now, let's talk about queues.
They're similar.
Because each of these agendas has a queue in it.
What's a queue?
A queue is going to have the following primitive operations.
To make a queue, this gives me a new queue.
I'm going to have to be able to insert into a queue a new item.
I'm going to have to be able to delete from a queue the first item in the queue.
And I want to be able to get the first thing in the queue from some queue.
I also have to be able to test whether a queue is empty.
And when you invent things like this, I want you to be very careful to use the kinds of conventions I use for naming things.
Notice that I'm careful to say these change something and that tests it.
And presumably, I did the same thing over here.
OK, and there should be an empty test over here.
OK, well, how would I make a queue?
A queue wants to be something I can add to at the end of, and pick up the thing at the beginning of.
I should be able to delete from the beginning and add to the end.
Well, I'm going to show you a very simple structure for that.
We can make this out of CONSes as well.
Here's a queue.
It has--it has a queue header, which contains two parts-- a front pointer and a rear pointer.
And here I have a queue with two items in it.
The first item, I don't know, it's perhaps a 1.
And the second item, I don't know, let's give it a 2.
The reason why I want two pointers in here, a front pointer and a rear pointer, is so I can add to the end without having to chase down from the beginning.
So for example, if I wanted to add one more item to this queue, if I want to add on another item to be worried about later, all I have to do is make a CONS, which contains that item, say a 3.
That's for inserting 3 into the queue.
Then I have to change this pointer here to here.
And I have to change this one to point to the new rear.
If I wish to take the first element of the queue, the first item, I just go chasing down the front pointer until I find the first one and pick it up.
If I wish to delete the first item from the queue, delete-queue, all I do is move the front pointer along this way.
The new front of the queue is now this.
So queues are very simple too.
So what you see now is that I need a certain number of new primitive operations.
And I'm going to give them some names.
And then we're going to look into how they work, and how they're used.
We have set the CAR of some pair, or a thing produced by CONSing, to a new value.
And set the CDR of a pair to a new value.
And then we're going to look into how they work.
I needed setting CAR over here to delete the first element of the queue.
This is the CAR, and I had to set it.
I had to be able to set the CDR to be able to move the rear pointer, or to be able to increment the queue here.
All of the operations I did were made out of those that I just showed you on the, on the last blackboard.
Good.
Let's pause the time, and take a little break then.
When we originally introduced pairs made out of CONS, made by CONS, we only said a few axioms about them, which were of the form-- what were they-- for all X and Y, the CAR of the CONS of X and Y is X and the CDR of the CONS of X and Y is Y. Now, these say nothing about whether a CONS has an identity like a person.
In fact, all they say is something sort of abstract, that a CONS is the parts it's made out of.
And of course, two things are made out of the same parts, they're the same, at least from the point of view of these axioms.
But by introducing assignment-- in fact, mutable data is a kind of assignment, we have a set CAR and a set CDR-- by introducing those, these axioms no longer tell the whole story.
And they're still true if written exactly like this.
But they don't tell the whole story.
Because if I'm going to set a particular CAR in a particular CONS, the questions are, well, is that setting all CARs and all CONSes of the same two things or not?
If I--if we use CONSes to make up things like rational numbers, or things like 3 over 4, supposing I had two three-fourths.
Are they the same one-- or are they different?
Well, in the case of numbers, it doesn't matter.
Because there's no meaning to changing the denominator of a number.
What you could do is make a number which has a different denominator.
But the concept of changing a number which has to have a different denominator is sort of a very weird, and sort of not supported by what you think of as mathematics.
However, when these CONSes represent things in the physical world, then changing something like the CAR is like removing a piece of the fingernail.
And so CONSes have an identity.
Let me show you what I mean about identity, first of all.
Let's do some little example here.
Supposing I define A to the CONS of 1 and 2.
Well, what that means, first of all, is that somewhere in some environment I've made a symbol A to have a value which is a pair consisting of pointers to a 1 and a pointer to a 2, just like that.
Now, supposing I also say define B to be the CONS--  it doesn't matter, but I like it better, it's prettier-- of A and A.
Well, first of all, I'm using the name A twice.
At this moment, I'm going to think of CONSes as having identity.
This is the same one.
And so what that means is I make another pair, which I'm going to call B. And it contains two pointers to A. At this point, I have three names for this object.
A is its name.
The CAR of B is its name.
And the CDR of B is its name.
It has several aliases, they're called.
Now, supposing I do something like set-the-CAR, the CAR of the CAR of B to 3.
What that means is I find the CAR of B, that's this.
I set the CAR of that to be 3, changing this.
I've changed A. If I were to ask what's the CAR of A--of A now?
I would get out 3, even though here we see that A was the CONS of 1 and 2.
I caused A to change by changing B.
There is sharing here.
That's sometimes what we want.
Surely in the queues and things like that, that's exactly what we defined our--organized our data structures to facilitate-- sharing.
But inadvertent sharing, unanticipated interactions between objects, is the source of most of the bugs that occur in complicated programs. So by introducing this possibility of things having identity and sharing and having multiple names for the same thing, we get a lot of power.
But we're going to pay for it with lots of complexity and bugs.
So also, for example, if I just looked at this just to drive that home, the CADR of B, which has nothing to do with even the CAR of B, apparently.
The CADR of B, what's that?
Take that CDR of B and now take the CAR of that.
Oh, that's 3 also.
So I can have non-local interactions by sharing.
And I have to be very careful of that.
Well, so far, of course, it seems I've introduced several different assignment operators-- set, set CAR, set CDR. Well, maybe I should just get rid of set CAR and set CDR. Maybe they're not worthwhile.
Well, the answer is that once you let the camel's nose into the tent, the rest of him follows.
All I have to have is set, and I can make all of the--all of the bad things that can happen.
Let's play with that a little bit.
A couple of days ago, when we introduced compound data, you saw Hal show you a definition of CONS in terms of a message acceptor.
I'm going to show you even a more horrible thing, a definition of CONS in terms of nothing but air, hot air.
What is the definition of CONS, of the old functional kind, in terms of purely lambdic expressions, procedures?
Because I'm going to then modify this definition to get assignment to be only one kind of assignment, to get rid of the set CAR and set CDR in terms of set.
So what if I define CONS of X and Y to be a procedure of one argument called a message M, which calls that message on X and Y?
This [? idea ?] was invented by Alonzo Church, who was the greatest programmer of the 20th century, although he never saw a computer.
It was done in the 1930s.
He was a logician, I suppose at Princeton at the time.
Define CAR of X to be the result of applying X to that procedure of two arguments, A and D, which selects A. I will define CDR of X to be that procedure, to be the result of applying X to that procedure of A and D, which selects D.
Now, you may not recognize this as CAR, CDR, and CONS.
But I'm going to demonstrate to you that it satisfies the original axioms, just once.
And then we're going to do some playing of games.
Consider the problem CAR of CONS of, say, 35 and 47.
Well, what is that?
It is the result of taking car of the result of substituting 35 and 47 for X and Y in the body of this.
Well, that's easy enough.
That's CAR of the result of substituting into lambda of M, M of 35 and 47.
Well, what this is, is the result of substituting this object for X in the body of that.
So that's just lambda of M-- that's substituted, because this object is being substituted for X, which is the beginning of a list, lambda of M-- M of 35 and 47, applied to that procedure of A and D, which gives me A. Well, that's the result of substituting this for M here.
So that's the same thing as lambda of A, D, A, applied to 35 and 47.
Oh, well that's 35.
That's substituting 35 for A and for 47 for D in A. So I don't need any data at all, not even numbers.
This is Alonso Church's hack.
Well, now we're going to do something nasty to him.
Being a logician, he wouldn't like this.
But as programmers, let's look at the overhead.
And here we go.
I'm going to change the definition of CONS.
It's almost the same as Alonzo Church's, but not quite.
What do we have here?
The CONS of two arguments, X and Y, is going to be that procedure of one argument M, which supplies M to X and Y as before, but also to two permissions, the permission to set X to N and the permission to set Y to N, given that I have an N.
So besides the things that I had here in Church's definition, what I have is that the thing that CONS returns will apply its argument to not just the values of the X and Y that the CONS is made of, but also permissions to set X and Y to new values.
Now, of course, just as before, CAR is exactly the same.
The CAR of X is nothing more than applying X, as in Church's definition, to a procedure, in this case, of four arguments, which selects out the first one.
And just as we did before, that will be the value of X that was contained in the procedure which is the result of evaluating this lambda expression in the environment where X and Y are defined over here.
That's the value of CONS.
Now, however, the exciting part.
CDR, of course, is the same.
The exciting part, set CAR and set CDR. Well, they're nothing very complicated anymore.
Set CAR of a CONS X to a new value Y is nothing more than applying that CONS, which is the procedure of four--the procedure of one argument which applies its argument to four things, to a procedure which is of four arguments-- the value of X, the value of Y, permission to set X, the permission to set Y-- and using it--using that permission to set X to the new value.
And similarly, set-cdr is the same thing.
So what you've just seen is that I didn't introduce any new primitives at all.
Whether or not I want to implement it this way is a matter of engineering.
And the answer is of course I don't implement it this way for reasons that have to do with engineering.
However in principle, logically, once I introduced one assignment operator, I've assigned--I've introduced them all.
Are there any questions?
Yes, David.
AUDIENCE: I can follow you up until you get--I can follow all of that.
But when we bring in the permissions, defining CONS in terms of the lambda N, I don't follow where N gets passed.
PROFESSOR: Oh, I'm sorry.
I'll show you.
Let's follow it.
Of course, we could do it on the blackboard.
It's not so hard.
But it's also easy here.
Supposing I wish to set-cdr of X to Y. See that right there.
set-cdr of X to Y. X is presumably a CONS, a thing resulting from evaluating CONS.
Therefore X comes from a place over here, that that X is of the result of evaluating this lambda expression.
Right?
That when I evaluated that lambda expression, I evaluated it in an environment where the arguments to CONS were defined.
That means that as free variables in this lambda expression, there is the--there are in the frame, which is the parent frame of this lambda expression, the procedure resulting from this lambda expression, X and Y have places.
And it's possible to set them.
I set them to an N, which is the argument of the permission.
The permission is a procedure which is passed to M, which is the argument that the CONS object gets passed.
Now, let's go back here in the set-cdr The CONS object, which is the first argument of set-cdr gets passed an argument.
That--there's a procedure of four things, indeed, because that's the same thing as this M over here, which is applied to four objects.
The object over here, SD, is, in fact, this permission.
When I use SD, I apply it to Y, right there.
So that comes from this.
AUDIENCE: So what do you-- PROFESSOR: So to finish that, the N that was here is the Y which is here.
How's that?
AUDIENCE: Right, OK.
Now, when you do a set-cdr, X is the value the CDR is going to become.
PROFESSOR: The X over here.
I'm sorry, that's not true.
The X is--set-cdr has two arguments-- The CONS I'm changing and the value I'm changing it to.
So you have them backwards, that's all.
Are there any other questions?
Well, thank you.
It's time for lunch.