[MUSIC PLAYING]
PROFESSOR: Well, so far in this
course we've been talking
about procedures, and then just
to remind you of this
framework that we introduced for
talking about languages,
we talked about the primitive
things that are
built into the system.
We mentioned some means of
combination by which you take
the primitive things and you
make more complicated things.
And then we talked about the
means of abstraction, how you
can take those complicated
things and name them so you
can use them as simple
building blocks.
And then last time you saw
we went even beyond that.
We saw that by using higher
order procedures, you can
actually express general methods
for computing things.
Like the method of doing
something by fixed points, or
Newton's method, and so the
incredible expressive power
you can get just by combining
these means of abstraction.
And the crucial idea in all of
this is the one that we build
a layered system.
So for instance, if we're
writing the square root
procedure, somewhere the square
root procedure uses a
procedure called good-enough,
and between those there is
some sort of abstraction
boundary.
It's almost as if we go out and
in writing square root, we
go and make a contract with
George, and tell George that
his job is to write good-enough,
and so long as
good-enough works, we don't
care what it does.
We don't care exactly how
it's implemented.
There are levels of detail here
that are George's concern
and not ours.
So for instance, George might
use an absolute value
procedure that's written by
Harry, and we don't much care
about that or even know that,
maybe, Harry exists.
So the crucial idea is that when
we're building things, we
divorce the task of building
things from the task of
implementing the parts.
And in a large system, of
course, we have abstraction
barriers like this at lots, and
lots, and lots of levels.
And that's the idea that we've
been using so far over and
over in implementing
procedures.
Well, now what we're going
to do is look at the
same issues for data.
We're going to see that the
system has primitive data.
In fact, we've already
seen that.
We've talked about numbers
as primitive data.
And then we're going to
see their means of
combination for data.
There's glue that allows you to
put primitive data together
to make more complicated,
kind of compound data.
And then we're going to see a
methodology for abstraction
that's a very good thing to use
when you start building up
data in terms of simpler data.
And again, the key idea is that
you're going to build the
system in layers and set up
abstraction barriers that
isolate the details at the lower
layers from the thing
that's going on at
the upper layers.
The details at the
lower layers, the
ideas, they won't matter.
They're going to be George's
concern because he signed this
contract with us for how the
stuff that he implements
behaves, and how he implements
the thing is his problem.
All right, well let's
look at an example.
And the example I'm going to
talk about is a system that
does arithmetic on
rational numbers.
And what I have in mind is that
we should have something
in the computer that allows us
to ask it, like, what's the
sum of 1/2 and 1/4, and somehow
the system should say,
yeah, that's 3/4.
Or we should be able to say
what's 3/4 times 2/3, and the
system should be able to
say, yeah, that's 1/2.
Right?
And you know what
I have in mind.
And you also know how to do this
from, I don't know, fifth
grade or sixth grade.
There are these formulas that
say if I have some fraction
which is a numerator over a
denominator, and I want to add
that to some other fraction
which is another numerator
over another denominator, then
the answer is the numerator of
the first times the denominator
of the second,
plus the numerator of the second
times the denominator
of the first. That's the
numerator of the answer, and
the denominator is the product
of the two denominators.
Right?
So there's something from fifth
or sixth grade fraction
arithmetic.
And then similarly, if I want
to multiply two things, n1
over d1 multiplied by n2 over
d2 is the product of the
numerators over the product
of the denominators.
So it's no problem at all, but
it's absolutely no problem to
think about what computation you
want to make in adding and
multiplying these fractions.
But as soon as we go
to implement it, we
run up across something.
We don't have what a
rational number is.
So we said that the system gives
us individual numbers,
so we can have 5 and 3, but
somehow we don't have a way of
saying there's a thing that has
both a 3 and a 4 in it, or
both a 2 and a 3.
It's almost as if we'd like to
imagine that somehow there are
these clouds, and a cloud
somehow has both a numerator
and a denominator in it, and
that's what we'd like to work
in terms of.
Well, how are we going to
solve that problem?
We're going to solve that
problem by using this
incredibly powerful design
strategy that you've already
seen us use over and over.
And that's the strategy
of wishful thinking.
Just like before when we didn't
have a procedure, we
said, well, let's imagine that
that procedure already exists.
We'll say, well, let's imagine
that we have these clouds.
Now more precisely what I mean
is let's imagine that we have
three procedures, one
called make-RAT.
make-RAT is going to take as
arguments two numbers, so I'll
call them numerator and
denominator, and it'll return
for us a cloud--
one of these clouds.
I don't really know
what a cloud is.
It's whatever make-RAT returns,
that's its business.
And then we're going to say,
suppose we've got one of these
clouds, we have a procedure
called numer, which takes in a
cloud that has an n and a d in
it, whatever a cloud is, and I
don't know what it is,
and returns for us
the numerator part.
And then we'll assume we have a
procedure denom, which again
takes in a cloud, whatever a
cloud is, and returns for us
the denominator [? required. ?]
This is just like before, when
if we're building a square
root, we assume that we
have good enough.
Right?
And what we'll say is, we'll go
find George, and we'll say
to George, well, it's your
business to make us these
procedures.
And how you choose to implement
these clouds, that's
your problem.
We don't want to know.
Well, having pushed this task
off onto George, then it's
pretty easy to do
the other part.
Once we've got the clouds, it's
pretty easy to write the
thing that does say addition
of rational numbers.
You can just say define,
well, let's say +RAT.
Define +RAT, which will
take in two rational
numbers, x and y.
x and y are each these clouds.
And what does it do?
Well, it's going to return
for us a rational number.
What rational number is it?
Well, we've got the
formulas there.
The numerator of it is the
sum of the product of the
numerator of x and the
denominator of y.
It's one thing in the sum.
And the other thing in the
numerator is the product of
the numerator of y and
the denominator of x.
The star, close the plus.
Right, that's the first argument
to make-RAT, which is
the numerator of the thing
I'm constructing.
And then the rest of the thing
goes into make-RAT is the
denominator of the answer, which
is the product of the
denominator of x and the
denominator of y.
Like that.
OK?
So there is the analog of doing
rational number addition.
And it's no problem at
all, assuming that
we have these clouds.
And of course, we can do
multiplication in the same way.
Define how to get the product
of two rational
numbers, call it *RAT.
Takes in two of these clouds, x
and y, it returns a rational
number, make-RAT, whose
numerator is the product of
the numerators--
numerator of x times
the numerator of y.
And the denominator of the thing
it's going to return is
the product of the
denominators.
Well, except that I haven't
told you what these clouds
are, that's all there
is to it.
See, what did I do?
I assumed by wishful thinking
that I had a new
kind of data object.
And in particular, I assumed I
had ways of creating these
data objects.
Make-RAT creates one
of these things.
This is called a constructor.
All right, I have a thing that
constructs such data objects.
And then I assume I have things
that, having made these
things, I have ways of getting
the parts out.
Those are called selectors.
And so formally, what I said is
I assumed I had procedures
that are constructors and
selectors for these data
objects, and then I went
off and used them.
That's no different in kind from
saying I assume I have a
procedure good-enough,
and I go use it to
implement square root.
OK, well before we go on, let's
ask the question of why
do we want to do this
in the first place?
See, why do we want a procedure
like +RAT that takes
in two rational numbers and
returns a rational number?
See, another way to think about
this is, well, here's
this formula.
And I've also got to implement
something that
adds rational numbers.
One other way to think about is,
well, there's this thing,
and I type in four numbers,
an n1, and a d1, and
an n2, and a d2.
And it sets some registers in
the machine to this numerator
and this denominator.
So I might say, well, why don't
I just add rational
numbers by I type in four
numbers, numerators and
denominators, and get out two
numbers, which is a numerator
and a denominator.
Why are we worrying
about building
things like this anyway?
Well, the answer is, suppose
you want to think about
expressing something like this,
suppose I'd like to
express the idea of taking two
rational numbers, x plus y,
say, and multiplying that
by the sum of two
other rational numbers.
Well, the way I do it, having
things like +RAT and *RAT, is
I'd say, oh yeah, what that
is is just the product.
That's *RAT of the sum of x and
y and the sum of s and t.
So except for syntax, I get an
expression that looks like the
way I want to think about
it mathematically.
I want to say there
are two numbers.
There's a thing which is the
sum of them, and there's a
thing which is the
sum of these two.
That's this and this.
And then I multiply them.
So I get an expression that
matches this expression.
If I did the other thing, if I
said, well, the way I want to
think about this is I type into
my machine four numbers,
which are the numerators and the
denominators of x and y,
and then four more numbers,
which are the numerators and
denominators of s and t.
And then what I'd be sitting
with is, well,
what would I do?
I'd add these, and somehow I'd
have to have two temporary
variables, which are the
numerators and denominators of
this sum, and I'd go off and
store them someplace.
And then I'd go over here, I'd
type in four more numbers, I'd
get two more temporary
variables, which are the
numerators and denominators
of s and t.
And then finally, I put those
together by multiplying them.
You see, what's starting to
happen, there are all these
temporary variables, which are
sort of the guts of the
internals of these rational
numbers that start hanging out
all over the system.
And of course, if I had more
and more complicated
expressions, there'd be more and
more guts hanging out that
confuse my programming.
And those of you who sort of
programmed things like that,
where you're just adding numbers
in assembly language,
you sort of see you have to
suddenly be concerned with
these temporary variables.
But more importantly than
confusing my programming,
they're going to confuse
my mind.
Because the whole name of this
game is that we'd like the
programming language to express
the concepts that we
have in our heads, like rational
numbers are things
that you can add and then take
that result and multiply them.
Let's break for questions.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: I don't quite see the
need- when we had make-RAT
with the numerator and
denominator, we had to have
the numerator and denominator
to pass as parameters to
create the cloud, and then we
extracted to get back what we
had to have originally.
PROFESSOR: That's right.
So the question is, I sort of
have the numerator and the
denominator, why am I worrying
about having the cloud given
that I have to get
the pieces out?
That's sort of what I tried to
say at the end, but let me try
and say it again,
because that's
really the crucial question.
The point is, I want to carry
this numerator and denominator
around together all the time.
And it's almost as if I want
to know, yeah, there's a
numerator and denominator in
there, but also, I would like
to say, fine, but from another
point of view, that's x.
And I carry x around, and I name
it as x, and I hold it.
And I can say things like, the
sum of x and y, rather than
just have-- see, it's not so bad
when I only think about x,
but if I have a system with 10
rational numbers, suddenly I
have 20 numerators and
denominators, which are not
necessarily--
if I don't link them, then it's
just 20 arbitrary numbers
that are not linked in
any particular way.
It's a lot like saying, well, I
have these instructions that
are the body of the procedures,
why do I want to
package them and say
it's the procedure?
It's exactly the same idea.
No?
OK.
Let's break, let's just stretch
and get somebody--
[INAUDIBLE]
[MUSIC PLAYING]
OK, well, we've been working
on this rational number
arithmetic system, and then
what we did, the important
thing about what we did, is we
thought about the problem by
breaking it into two pieces.
We said, assume there is this
contract with George, and
George has figured out the way
to how to construct these
clouds, provided us procedures
make-RAT, which was a
constructor, and selectors,
which are numerator and
denominator.
And then in terms of that, we
went off and implemented
addition and multiplication
of rational numbers.
Well, now let's go look
at George's problem.
How can we go and package
together a numerator and a
denominator and actually make
one of these clouds?
See, what we need is a kind of
glue, a glue for data objects
that allows us to put
things together.
And Lisp provides such
a glue, and that glue
is called list structure.
List structure is a way of
gluing things together, and
more precisely, Lisp provides
a way of constructing things
called pairs.
There's a primitive operator
in Lisp called cons.
We can take a look at it.
There's a thing called cons.
Cons is an operator which takes
in two arguments called
x and y, and it returns for
us a thing called a pair.
All right, so a thing called a
pair that has a first part a
second part.
So cons takes two objects.
There's a thing called a pair.
The first part of the cons
is x, and the second part
of the cons is y.
And that's what it builds.
And then we also assume
we have ways of
getting things out.
If you're given a pair, there's
a thing called car,
and car of a pair, p, gives
you out the first part
of the pair, p.
And there's a thing called cdr,
and cdr of the pair, p,
gives you the second part
of the pair, p.
OK, so that's how we
construct things.
There's also a conventional
way of drawing pictures of
these things.
Just like we write down that
as the conventional way of
writing Plato's idea of two,
the way we could draw a
diagram to represent cons of
two and three is like this.
We draw a little box.
And so here's the box we're
talking about, and this box
has two arrows coming
out of it.
And say the first part of this
pair is 2, and the second part
of this pair is 3.
And this notation has
a name, it's called
box and pointer notation.
By the way, let me say right now
that a lot of people get
confused that there's some
significance to the geometric
way I drew these pointers,
the directions.
Like some people think it'd be
different if I took this
pointer and turned it up here,
and put the 3 out here.
That has no significance.
All right?
It's merely you have a bunch
of arrows, these
pointers, and the boxes.
The only issue is how they're
connected, not the geometric
arrangement of whether
I write the pointer
across, or up, or down.
Now it's completely un-obvious,
probably, why
that's called list structure.
We're not actually going to
talk about that today.
We'll see that next time.
So those are pairs, there's
cons that constructs them.
And what I'm going to know about
cons, and car, and cdr,
is precisely that if I have any
x and y, all right, if I
have any things x and y, and I
use cons to construct a pair,
then the car of that pair is
going to be x, the thing I put
in, and the cdr of that
pair is going to be y.
That's the behavior of these
operators, cons, car, and cdr.
Given them, it's pretty clear
how George can go off and
construct his rational
numbers.
After all, all he has to do--
remember George's problem was
to implement make-RAT,
numerator, and denom.
So all George has to do is
say define make-RAT of
some n and a d--
so all I have to do
is cons them.
That's cons of n and d.
And then if I want to get the
numerator out, I would say
define the numerator, numer,
of some rational number, x.
If the rational number's
implemented as a pair, then
all I have to do is get
out the car of x.
And then similarly, define the
denom is going to be the cdr,
the other thing I put
into the pair.
Well, now we're in business.
That's a complete
implementation of rational numbers.
Let's use it.
Suppose I want to say, so I want
to think about how to add
1/2 plus 1/4 and watch
the system work.
Well, the way I'd use that is
I'd say, well, maybe define a.
I have to make a 1/2.
Well, that's a rational number
with numerator 1 and
denominator 2, so a will
be make-RAT of 1 and 2.
And then I'll construct
the 1/4.
I'll say define d to be
make-RAT of 1 and 4.
And if I'd like to look
at the answer--
well, assuming I don't have a
special thing that prints
rational numbers, or
I could make one--
I could say, for instance,
define the answer to be +RAT
of a and b, and now I can
say, what's the answer?
What are the numerators and
denominators of the answer?
So if I'm adding 1/2 and 1/4,
I'll say, what is the
numerator of the answer?
And the system is going
to type out, well, 6.
Bad news.
And if I say what's the
denominator of the answer, the
system's going to type out 8.
So instead of what I would
really like, which is for it
to say that 1/2 and 1/4 is 3/4,
this foolish machine is
going to say, no, it's 6/8.
Well, that's sort of bad news.
Where's the bug?
Why does it do that,
after all?
Well, it's the way that
we just had +RAT.
+RAT just took the--
it said you add the numerator
times the denominator, you add
that to the numerator times the
denominator, and put that
over the product of the two
denominators, and that's why
you get 6/8.
So what was wrong with our
implementation of +RAT?
What's wrong with that rational
number arithmetic
stuff that we did before
the break?
Well, the answer is one way to
look at it is absolutely
nothing's wrong.
That's perfectly good
implementation.
It follows the sixth grade,
fifth grade mathematic for
adding fractions.
One thing we can say is, well,
that's George's problem.
Like, boy, wasn't George dumb
to say that he can make a
rational number simply by
sticking together the
numerator and the denominator?
Wouldn't it be better for
George, when he made a
rational number, to reduce the
stuff to lowest terms?
And what I mean is, wouldn't
it be better for George,
instead of using this version
of make-RAT, to use this one
on the slide?
Or instead of just saying cons
together n and d, what you do
is compute the greatest common
divisor of n and d, and gcd is
the procedure which, well, for
all we care is a primitive,
which computes the greatest
common divisor of two numbers.
So the way I can construct a
rational number is get the
greatest common divisor of the
two numbers, and I'm going to
call that g, and then instead
of consing together n and d,
I'll divide them through.
I'll cons together the quotient
of n by the the gcd
and the quotient of
d by the gcd.
And that will reduce the
rational number to lowest
terms. So when I do
this addition,
when +RAT calls make-RAT--
and for the definition of +RAT
it had a make-RAT in there--
just by the fact that it's
constructing that, the thing
will get reduced to lowest
terms automatically.
OK, that is a complete system.
For rational number arithmetic,
let's look at what
we've done.
All right, we said we want
to build rational number
arithmetic, and we had
a thing called +RAT.
We implemented that.
And I showed you multiplying
rational numbers, and although
I didn't put them up there,
presumably we'd like to have
something that subtracts
rational numbers, and I don't
know, all sorts of things.
Things that test equality in
division, and maybe things
that print rational numbers
in some particular way.
And we implemented those
in terms of pairs.
These pairs, cons, car, and cdr
that are built into Lisp.
But the important thing is that
between these and these,
we set up an abstraction
barrier.
We set up a layer
of abstraction.
And what was that layer
of abstraction?
That layer of abstraction was
precisely the constructor and
the selectors.
This layer was make-RAT,
and numer, and denom.
This methodology, another way
to say what it's doing, is
that we are separating the way
something is used, separating
the use of data objects,
from the
representation of data objects.
So up here, we have the way
that rational numbers are
used, do arithmetic on them.
Down here, we have the way that
they're represented, and
they're separated by
this boundary.
The boundary is the constructors
and selectors.
And this methodology
has a name.
This is called data
abstraction.
Data abstraction is sort of the
programming methodology of
setting up data objects by
postulating constructors and
selectors to isolate use
from representation.
Well, so why?
I mean, after all, we didn't
have to do it this way.
It's perfectly possible to do
rational number addition
without having any compound data
objects, and here on the
slide is one example.
We certainly could have defined
+RAT, which takes in
things x and y, and we'll say,
well what are these rational
numbers really?
So really, they're just pairs,
and the numerator's the car
and the denominator's the cdr.
So what we'll do is we'll take
the car of x times the cdr
of y, multiply them.
Take the car of y times the
cdr of x, multiply them.
Add them.
Take the cdr of x and the cdr of
y, multiply them, and then
constitute together.
Well, that sort of does
the same thing.
But this ignores the problem of
reducing things to lowest
terms, but let's not worry
about that for a minute.
But so what?
Why don't we do it that way?
Right?
After all, there are sort of
fewer procedures to define,
and it's a lot more
straightforward.
It saves all this self-righteous
BS about
talking about data
abstraction.
We just sort of do it.
I mean, who knows, maybe it's
even marginally more efficient
depending on whatever compiler
were using for this.
What's the point of isolating
the use from the
representation?
Well, it goes back to this
notion of naming.
Remember, one of the most
important principles in
programming is the same as
one of the most important
principles in sorcery,
all right?
That's if you have the name
of the spirit, you get
control over it.
And if you go back and look at
the slide, you see what's in
there is we have this thing
+RAT, but nowhere in the
system, if I have a +RAT and a
-RAT and a *RAT, and things
that look like that, nowhere
in the system do I have a
thing that I can point at which
is a rational number.
I don't have, in a system like
that, the idea of rational
number as a conceptual entity.
Well, what's the advantage
of that?
What's the advantage of
isolating the idea of rational
numbers as a conceptual entity,
and really naming it
with make-RAT, numerator,
and denominator.
Well, one advantage is you might
want to have alternative
representations.
See, before I showed you that
one way George can solve this
things not reduced to lowest
terms problem, is when you
build a rational number, you
divide up by the greatest
common denominator.
Another way to do that
is shown over here.
I can have an alternative
representation for rational
numbers where when you make
a rational number,
you just cons them.
However, when you go to select
out the numerator, at that
point you compute the gcd of
the stuff that's sitting in
that pair, and divide
out by the gcd.
And similarly, when I get the
denominator, at that point
when I go to get the
denominator, I'll divide out
by the gcd.
So the difference would be in
the old representation, when
ans was constructed here, say
what's 6 and 8, in the first
way, the 6 and 8 would have
got reduced when they got
stuck into that pair, numerator
would select out 3.
And in the way I just showed
you, well, ans would get 6 and
8 put in, and then at the point
where I said numerator,
some computation would
get done to put out
3 instead of 6.
So those are two different
ways I might do it.
Which one's better?
Well, it depends, right?
If I'm making a system where
I am mostly constructing
rational numbers and hardly
ever looking at them, then
it's probably better not to do
that gcd computation when I
construct them.
If I'm doing a system where I
look at things a lot more than
I construct them, then it's
probably better to do the work
when I construct them.
So there's a choice there.
But the real issue is that you
might not be able to decide at
the moment you're worrying about
these rational numbers.
See, in general, as systems
designers, you're forced with
the necessity to make decisions
about how you're
going to do things, and in
general, the way you'd like to
retain flexibility is to never
make up your mind about
anything until you're
forced to do it.
The problem is, there's a very,
very narrow line between
deferring decisions and outright
procrastination.
So you'd like to make progress,
but also at the same
time, never be bound by the
consequences of your decisions.
Data abstraction's one
way of doing this.
What we did is we used
wishful thinking.
See, we gave a name
to the decision.
We said, make-RAT, numerator,
and denominator will stand for
however it's going to be done,
and however it's going to be
done is George's problem.
But really, what that was doing
is giving a name to the
decision of how we're going to
do it, and then continuing as
if we made the decision.
And then eventually, when we
really wanted it to work,
coming back and facing what
we really had to do.
And in fact, we'll see a couple
times from now that you
may never have to choose any
particular representation,
ever, ever.
Anyway, that's a very powerful
design technique.
It's the key to the reason
people use data abstraction.
And we're going to see that
idea again and again.
Let's stop for questions.
AUDIENCE: What does this
decision making through
abstraction layers do to the
axiom of do all your design
before any of your code?
PROFESSOR: Well, that's
someone's axiom, and I bet
that's the axiom of someone who
hasn't implemented very
large computer systems
very much.
I said that computer science is
a lot like magic, and it's
sort of good that
it's like magic.
There's a bad part of
computer science
that's a lot like religion.
And in general, I think people
who really believe that you
design everything before you
implement it basically are
people who haven't designed
very many things.
The real power is that you can
pretend that you've made the
decision and then later on
figure out which one is right,
which decision you ought
to have made.
And when you can do that, you
have the best of both worlds.
AUDIENCE: Can you explain
the difference
between let and define?
PROFESSOR: Oh, OK.
Let is a way to establish
local names.
Let me give you sort
of the half answer.
And I'll say, later on we can
talk about the whole very
complicated thing.
But the big difference for now
is that, see, when you're
typing at Lisp, you're typing
in this environment where
you're making definitions.
And when you say define a to be
5, if I say define a to be
5, then from then on the thing
will remember that a is 5.
Let is a way to set up a local
context where there's a
definition.
So if I type something like,
saying let a-- no, I
shouldn't say a--
if I said let z be 10, and
within that context, tell me
what the sum of z and z is.
So if I typed in this expression
to Lisp, and then
this would put out 20.
However, then if I said what's
z, the computer would say
that's an unbound variable.
So let is a way of setting up
a context where you can make
definitions.
But those definitions are
local to this context.
And of course, if I'd said a
in here, I'd still get 20.
But this a would not interfere
at all with this one.
So if I type this, and then type
this, and then say what's
a? a will still be 5.
So there's some other subtle
differences between let and
define, but that's the
most important one.
All right, well, we've looked
at implementing this little
system for doing arithmetic on
rational numbers as an example
of this methodology of
data abstraction.
And that's a way of controlling
complexity in
large systems. But, see, like
procedure definition, and like
all the ways we're going to
talk about for controlling
complexity, the real power of
these things show up not when
you sort of do these things in
themselves, like it's not such
a great thing that we've done
rational number arithmetic,
it's that you can use these as
building blocks for making
more complicated things.
So it's no wonderful idea that
you can just put two numbers
together to form a pair.
If that's all you ever wanted to
do, there are tons of ways
that you can do that.
The real issue is can you do
that in such a way so that the
things that you build become
building blocks for doing
something even more complex?
So whenever someone shows you
a method for controlling
complexity, you should say,
yeah, that's great, but what
can I build with it?
So for example, let me just
run through another thing
that's a lot like the
rational number one.
Suppose we would like to
represent points in the plane.
You sort of say, well, there's
a point, and we're going to
call that point p.
And that point might have
coordinates, like this might
be the point 1 comma 2.
The x-coordinate might
be 1, and it's
y-coordinate might be 2.
And we'll make a little system
for manipulating
points in the plane.
And again, we can do
that-- here's a
little example of that.
It can represent vectors, the
same as points in the plane,
and we'll say, yep, there's
a constructor called
make-vector, make-vector's going
to take two coordinates,
and here we can implement them
if we like as pairs, but the
important thing is that
there's a constructor.
And then given some vector, p,
we can find its x-coordinate,
or we can get its
y-coordinate.
So there's a constructor
and selectors for
points in the plane.
Well, given points in the plane,
we might want to use
them to build something.
So for instance, we might want
to talk about, we might have a
point, p, and a point, q, and p
might be the point 1, 2, and
q might be the point 2, 3.
And we might want to talk about
the line segment that
starts at p and ends at q.
And that might be
the segment s.
So we might want to build points
for vectors in terms of
numbers, and segments
in terms of vectors.
So we can represent
line segments in
exactly the same way.
All right, so the line segment
from p to q, we'll say there's
a constructor, make-segment.
And make up names for the
selectors, the starting point
of the segment and the ending
point of the segment.
And again, we can implement a
segment using cons as a pair
of points, and car and cdr get
out the two points that we put
together to get the segment.
Well, now having done that,
we can have some
operations on them.
Like we could say, what's the
midpoint of a line segment?
So here's the midpoint of a line
segment, that's going to
be the points whose coordinates
are the averages
of the coordinates
of the endpoints.
OK, there's the midpoint.
So to get the midpoint of a line
segment, s, we'll just
say grab the starting point to
the segment, grab the ending
point of the segment, and
now make a vector--
make a point whose coordinates
are the average of the
x-coordinate of the first point
and the x-coordinate of
the second point, and whose
y-coordinate is the average of
the y-coordinates.
So there's an implementation
of midpoint.
And then similarly, we can
build something like the
length of the segment.
The length of the segment
is a thing whose--
use Pythagoras's rule, the
length of the segment is the
square root of the d x squared
plus d y squared.
We'll say to get the length of
a line segment, we'll let dx
be the difference of the
x-coordinate of one endpoint
and the x-coordinate of the
other endpoint, and we'll let
dy be the difference of
the y-coordinates.
And then we'll take the square
root of the sum of the squares
of dx and dy, that's
what this says.
All right, so there's an
implementation of length.
And again, what we built
is a layered system.
We built a system which
has, well, say up
here there's segments.
And then there's an abstraction
barrier.
The abstraction barrier
separates the implementation
of segments from the
implementation of vectors and
points, and what that
abstraction barrier is are the
constructors and selectors.
It's make-segment, and
segment-start, and
segment-end.
And then there are vectors.
And vectors in turn are built
on top of pairs and numbers.
So I'll say pairs and numbers.
And that has its own abstraction
barrier, which is
make-vector, and x-coordinate,
and y-coordinate.
So we have, again,
a layered system.
You're starting to see that
there are layers here.
I ought to mention, there is a
very important thing that I
kind of took for granted.
And it's sort of so natural, but
on the other hand it's a
very important thing.
Notice that in order to
represent this segment s, I
said this segment is
a pair of points.
And a point is a pair
of numbers.
And if I were going to draw the
box and pointers structure
for that, I would say, oh, the
segment is, given those
particular representations that
I showed you, I'd say
this segment s is a pair, and
the first thing in the pair is
a vector, and the vector
is a pair of numbers.
And that's this, that's p.
And the other thing in the
segment is q, which is itself
a pair of numbers.
So I almost took it for granted
when I said that cons
allows you to put
things together.
But it's very easy to not
appreciate that, because
notice, some of the things
I can put together can
themselves be pairs.
And let me introduce a word that
I'll talk about more next
time, it's one of my favorite
words, called closure.
And by closure I mean that the
means of combination in your
system are such that when you
put things together using
them, like we make a pair, you
can then put those together
with the same means
of combination.
So I can have not only a pair
of numbers, but I can have a
pair of pairs.
So for instance, making arrays
in a language like Fortran is
not a closed means of
combination, because I can
make an array of numbers,
but I can't
make an array of arrays.
And one of the things that you
should ask, one of your tests
of quality for a means of
combination that someone shows
you, is gee, are the things
you make closed under that
means of combination?
So pairs would not be nearly so
interesting if all I could
do was make a pair of numbers.
I couldn't build very much
structure at all.
OK, well, we'll come
back to that.
I just wanted to
mention it now.
You'll hear a lot about
closure later on.
You can also see the potential
for losing control of
complexity as you have a layered
system if you don't
use data abstraction.
Let's go back and look at
this slide for length.
Length works and is a simple
thing because I can say, when
I want to get this value, I
can say, oh, that is the
x-coordinate of the first
endpoint of the segment.
And each of these things,
each of these selectors,
x-coordinate and endpoint, stand
for a decision choice
whose details I don't
have to look at.
So I could perfectly well,
again, just like rational
numbers I did before, I could
say, oh well, gee, a segment
really is a pair of pairs.
And the x-coordinate of the
first endpoint or the segment
really is the--
well, what is it?
It's the car of the car
of the segment.
So I could perfectly well
go and redefine length.
I could say, define the length
of some segment s.
And I could start off writing
something like, well, we'll
let dx be-- well, what's
it have to be?
It's got to be the difference
of the two coordinates, so
that's the difference of, the
first one is the car of the
car of s, subtracted from the
first one, the car of the
other half of it,
the cdr of s.
All right, and then
dy would be--
well, let's see, I'd get the
y-coordinate, so it'd be the
difference of the cdr of the car
of s, and the cdr of the
cdr of s, sort of go on.
You can see that's much harder
to read than the
program I had before.
But worse than that,
suppose you'd gone
and implemented length?
And then the next day, George
comes to you and says, I'm
sorry, I changed my mind.
I want to write points with the
x-coordinate first. So you
come back you stare at
this code and say, oh
gee, what was that?
That was the car, so I have to
change this to cdr, and this
is cdr, and this now
has to be car.
And this has to be car.
And you sort of do that, and
then the next day George comes
back and says, sorry, the guys
designing the display would
like lines to be painted in the
opposite direction, so I
have to write the endpoint
first in the order.
And then you come back and you
stare at this code, and say,
gee, what was it
talking about?
Oh yeah, well I've got to change
this one to cdr, and
this one becomes car, this one
comes car, and this becomes
cdr.
And you go up and do that, and
then the next day, George
comes back and says, I'm sorry,
what I really meant is
that the segments always have
to be painted from left to
right on the screen.
And then you sort of, it's
clear, you just go and punch
George in the mouth
at that point.
But you see, as soon as we have
a 10 layer system, you
see how that complexity
immediately builds up to the
point where even something like
this gets out of control.
So again, the way we've gotten
out of that is we've named
that spirit.
We built a system where there
is a thing, which is the
representation choice
for how you're going
to talk about vectors.
And choices about that
representation are localized
right there.
They don't have their guts
spilling over into things like
how you compute the length and
how you compute the midpoint.
And that's the real power
of this system.
OK, we're explicit about
them, so that we have
control over them.
All right, questions?
AUDIENCE: What happens in the
case where you don't want to
be treating objects
in terms of pairs?
For instance, in
three-dimensional space, you'd
have three coordinates.
Or even in the case
where you have
n-dimensional space, what happens?
PROFESSOR: Right, OK.
Well, this is a preview of
what I'll say tomorrow.
But the point is, once you have
two things, you have as
many things as you want.
All right?
Because if I want to make three
things, I could start
making things like a pair whose
first thing is 1, and
whose second thing is another
pair that, say,
has 2 and 3 in it.
And so on, a hundred things.
I can nest them out of pairs.
I made a pretty arbitrary
decision about how to do it,
and you can immediately
see there are lots
of ways to do that.
What we'll start talking about
next time are conventions for
how to do things like that.
But notice that what this really
depends on is I can
make pairs of pairs.
If all I could do was
make pairs of
numbers, I'd be stuck.
OK.
Let's break.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
All right, well, we've just gone
off and done a couple of
simple examples of
data abstraction.
Now I want to do something
more complicated.
We're going to talk about
what it means.
And this will be harder, because
it's always much
harder in computer programming
to talk about what something
means than to go
off and do it.
But let's go back to almost
the very beginning.
Let's go back to the point where
I said, we just assumed
that there were procedures,
make-RAT,
and numer, and denom.
Let's go back to where we had
this, at the very beginning,
constructors and selectors,
and when often defined the
rational number arithmetic.
And remember, I said at that
point we were sort of done,
except for George.
Well, what is it that we'd
actually done at that point?
What was it that was done?
Well, what I want to say is,
what was done after we'd
implemented the operations and
terms of these, was that we
had defined a rational number
representation in terms of
abstract data.
What do I mean by
abstract data?
Well, the idea is that at that
point, when we had our +RAT
and our *RAT, that any
implementation of make-RAT,
and numerator, and denominator
that George supplied us with,
could be the basis for
a rational number
representation.
Like, it wasn't our concern
where you divided through to
get the greatest common
denominator, or any of that.
So the idea is that what we
built is a rational arithmetic
system that would sit on top
of any representation.
What do I mean by any
representation?
I mean, certainly it can't be
the case that all I mean is
George can reach in a bag and
pull out three arbitrary
procedures and say, well,
fine, now that's the
implementation.
That can't be what I mean.
What I've got to mean is that
there's some way of saying
whether three procedures are
going to be suitable as a
basis for rational number
representation.
If we think about it, what
suitable might mean is if I
have to assume something like
this, I have to say that if x
is the result of say, doing
make-RAT of n and d, then the
numerator of x divided by
the denominator of x is
equal to n over d.
See, what that is is that's
George's contract.
What we mean by writing a
contract for rational numbers,
if you think about it, this
is the right thing.
And the two ones we showed
do the right thing.
See, if I'm taking out greatest
common divisors, it
doesn't matter whether I take
them out or not, or the place
where I take them, because
the idea is I'm
going to divide through.
But see, this is George's
contract.
So what we really say to George
is your business is to
go off and find us three
procedures, make-RAT, and
numerator, and denominator, that
fulfill this contract for
any choice of n and d.
And that's what we mean by we
can use that as the basis for
a rational number
representation.
And other than that, it fulfills
this contract.
We don't care how he does it.
It's not our business.
It's below the layer
of abstraction.
In fact, if we want
to say, what is a
rational number really?
See, what's it really, without
having to talk about going
below the layer of abstraction,
what we're forced
into saying is a rational number
really is sort of this
axiom, is three procedures,
make-RAT, numerator, and
denominator, that satisfy
this axiom.
In some sense, abstractly,
that's what a
rational number is really.
That's sort of easy words to
listen to, because what you
have in your head, of course,
is well, for all this thing
about saying that's what a
rational number is really, you
actually just saw that we
built rational numbers.
See, what we really did
is we built rational
numbers on top of pairs.
So for all I'm saying
abstractly, we can say a
rational number really
is just this axiom.
You can listen to that
comfortably, because you're
saying, well, yeah, but really
it's actually pairs, and I'm
just annoying you by trying
to be abstract.
Well, let me, as an antidote for
that, let me do something
that I think is really
going to terrify you.
I mean, it's really going to
bring you face to face with
the sort of existential reality
of this abstraction
that we're talking about.
And what I'm going
to talk about is,
what are pairs really?
See, what did I tell
you about pairs?
I tricked you, right?
I said that Lisp has this
primitive called cons that
builds pairs.
But what did I really
tell you about?
If you go back and said, let's
look on this slide, all I
really told you about pairs is
that there happens to be this
property, these properties of
cons, car, and cdr. And all I
really said about pairs is that
there's a thing called
cons, and a thing called car,
and a thing called cdr.
And it is the case that if I
build cons of x, y and take
car of it, I get x.
And if I build cons of x, y and
get cdr of it, I get y.
And even though I lulled you
into thinking that there's
something in Lisp that does
that, so you pretended you
knew what it was, in fact, I
didn't tell you any more about
pairs than this tells you
about rational numbers.
It's just some axiom
for pairs.
Well, to drive that home, let me
really scare you, and show
you what we might build
pairs in terms of.
And what you're going to see is
that we can build rational
numbers, and line segments, and
vectors, and all of this
stuff in terms of pairs, and
we're going to see below here
that pairs can be built
out of nothing at all.
Pure abstraction.
So let me show you on this slide
an implementation of
cons, car, and cdr. And we'll
look at it again in a second,
but notice that their procedure
definitions of cons,
car, and cdr, you don't see any
data in there, what you
see is a lambda.
So cons here is going to
return-- is a procedure that
returns a procedure, just like
average [UNINTELLIGIBLE].
Cons of a and b returns a
procedure of an argument
called pick, and it says, if
pick is equal to 1, I'm going
to return a, and if pick is
equal to 2, I'm going to
return b, and that's what
cons is going to be.
Car of a thing x, car of a
pair x, is going to be x
applied to 1.
And notice that makes sense.
You might not understand why or
how I'm doing such a thing,
but at least it makes sense,
because the thing constructed
by cons is a procedure, and
car applies that to 1.
And similarly, cdr applies
that thing to 2.
OK, now I claimed that this is a
representation of cons, car,
and cdr, and notice there's
no data in it.
All right, it's built
out of air.
It's just procedures.
There's no data objects at all
in that representation.
Well, what could that
possibly mean?
Well, if you really believe this
stuff, then you have to
believe that in order to show
that that's a representation
for cons, car, and cdr, all I
have to do is show that it
satisfies the axiom.
See, all I should have to
convince you of is, for
example, that gee, that car of
cons of 37 and 49 is 37 for
arbitrary values of 37 and 49.
And cdr the same way.
See, if I really can demonstrate
to you that that
weird procedure definition, in
terms of [? air ?], has the
property that it satisfies this,
then you just have to
grant me that that is a possible
implementation of
cons, car, and cdr, on which I
can build everything else.
Well, let's look at that.
And this will be practice in
the substitution model.
How could we check this?
We sort of know how
to do that.
It's just the same substitution
model.
Let's look.
We start out, and we
say, what's car of
cons of 37 and 49?
What do we do?
Cons is some procedure.
Its value is cons was a
procedure of a and b.
The thing returned by cons is
its procedure body with 37 and
49 substituted for
the parameters.
It'll be 37 substituted for a
and 49 substituted for b.
So this expression has the
same meaning as this
expression.
Its car of, and the body of
cons was this thing that
started with lambda.
And it says, so if pick is equal
to 1, where pick is this
other argument, if pick is equal
to 1, it's 37, that's
where a was, and if pick
is equal to 2, it's 49.
So that's the first step.
I'm just going through
mechanical substitution.
And remember, at this point in
the course, if you're confused
about what things mean, go
mechanically through the
substitution model.
Well, what is this reduced to?
Car said, take your argument,
which in this case is this,
and apply it to 1.
That was the definition
of car.
So if I look at car, if I do
that, the answer is, well,
it's that argument, this
was the argument to
car, applied to 1.
Well, what does that mean?
I take 1, and I substitute it
in the body here for this
value of pick, which
is the name of the
argument, what do I get?
Well, I get the thing that says
if 1 equals 1 it's 37,
and if 1 equals 2 it's 49,
so the answer's 37.
And similarly, if I'd taken cdr,
that would apply it to 2,
and I'd get 49.
So you see, what I've
demonstrated is that that
completely weird implementation
of cons, car,
and cdr, satisfies the axioms.
So it's a perfectly valid way
of building, in fact, all of the
data objects we're going
to see in Lisp.
So they all, if you like,
can be built on sort of
existential nothing.
And as far as you know,
that's how it works.
You couldn't tell.
If all you're ever going to do
with pairs is construct them
with cons and look at them with
car and cdr, you couldn't
possibly tell how this
thing works.
Now, it might give you a sort
of warm feeling inside if I
say, well, yeah, in fact, for
various reasons there happens
to be a primitive called cons,
car, and cdr, and if it's too
scary, if this kind of stuff is
too scary, you don't have
to look inside of it.
So that might make you feel
better, but the point is, it
really could work this way,
and it wouldn't make any
difference to the
system at all.
So in some sense, we don't
need data at all to build
these data abstractions.
We can do everything in
terms of procedures.
OK, well, why did I terrify
you in this way?
First, I really want to
reinforce this idea of
abstraction, that you really
can do these things
abstractly.
Secondly, I want to introduce
an idea we're going to see
more and more of in this course,
which is we're going
to blur the line between
what's data
and what's a procedure.
See, in this funny
implementation it turned out
that cons of something happened
to be represented in
terms of a procedure, even
though we think of it as data.
While here that's sort of a
mathematical trick, but one of
the things we'll see is that
a lot of the very important
programming techniques that
we're going to get to sort of
depend very crucially on
blurring this traditional line
between what you consider
a procedure and what you
consider data.
We're going to see more
and more of that,
especially next time.
OK, questions?
AUDIENCE: If you asked
the system to print
a, what would happen?
PROFESSOR: The question is, what
would happen if I asked
the system to print a.
Given this representation, you
already know the answer.
The answer is compound
procedure a,
just like last time.
It'd say compound procedure.
It might say a little
bit more.
It might say compound procedure
lambda or something
or other, depending on details
of how I named it.
But it's a procedure.
And the only reason for that is
I haven't told the system
anything special about how
to print such things.
Now, it's in fact true that with
the actual implementation
of cons that to be built in
the system, it would print
something else.
It would print, say,
this is a pair.
AUDIENCE: When you define cons,
and then you pass it
into values, how does it know
where to look for the cons,
because you can use cons
over and over again?
How does it know where to look
to know which a and b it's
supposed to pull back out?
I don't know if I'm expressing
that quite right.
Where is it stored?
PROFESSOR: OK, the question is,
I sort of have a cons with
a 37 and a 49, and I might make
another cons with a 1 and
a 2, and I might have one
called a, and I might
have one called b.
And the question is,
how does it know?
And why don't they
get confused?
And that's a very
good question.
See, you have to really believe
that the procedures
are objects.
It's sort of like saying--
let's try
another simpler example.
Suppose I ask for the
square root of 3.
So I asked for the square root
of 5, and then I ask for the
square of 20.
You're probably not the least
bit bothered that I can take
square root and apply it to 5,
and then I can take square
root and apply it to 20.
And there's sort of no issue,
gee, doesn't it get confused
about whether it's working
on 5 or 20?
There's no issue about that
because you're thinking of a
procedure which goes off
and does something.
Now, in some sense you're asking
me the same question.
But it's really bothering you,
and it's bothering you for a
really good reason.
Because when I write that,
you're saying gee, this is, I
know, sort of a procedure.
But it's not a procedure
that's just running.
It's just sort of a procedure
sitting there.
And how can it be that sometimes
this procedure has
37 and 49, and there might be
another one which has 5 and 6
in there, and why don't
they get confused?
So there's something very,
very important that's
bothering you.
And it's really crucial
to what's going on.
We're suddenly saying that
procedures are not just the
act of doing something.
Procedures are conceptual
entities, objects, and if I
built cons of 37 and 49, that's
a particular procedure
that sits there.
And it's different from
cons of 3 and 4.
That's another procedure
that sits there.
AUDIENCE: Both of them
exist independently.
PROFESSOR: And exists
independently.
AUDIENCE: And they both can be
referenced by car and cdr.
PROFESSOR: And they both would
be referenced by car and cdr.
Just like I could increment
this, and I
could increment that.
They're objects.
And that's sort of where
we're going.
See, the fact that you're asking
the question shows that
you're really starting to think
about the implications
of what's going on.
It's the difference between
saying a procedure is just the
act of doing something.
And a procedure is a real object
that has existence.
AUDIENCE: So when the procedure
gets built, the
actual values are now
substituted for a and b--
PROFESSOR: That's right.
AUDIENCE: And then that
procedure exists as lambda,
and pick is what's actually
passed in.
PROFESSOR: Yes, when cons gets
called, and the result of cons
is a new procedure that's
constructed, that new
procedure has an argument
that's called pick.
AUDIENCE: But it no longer
has an a and b.
The a and b are the
actual values
that are passed through.
PROFESSOR: And it has-- right,
according to the substitution
model, what it now has is not
those arbitrary names a and b,
it somehow has that 37
and 49 in there.
But you're right, that's a hard
thing to think about it,
and it's different from the way
you've been thinking about
procedures.
AUDIENCE: And if I have again
cons of 37 and 49, it's a
different [UNINTELLIGIBLE]?
PROFESSOR: And if you make
another cons of 37 and 49,
you're into a wonderful
philosophical problem, which
is going to be what the lecture
about halfway through
this course is about.
Which is, if I cons 37 and 49,
and I do it again, is that the
same thing, or is it
a different thing?
And how could you tell?
And when could it
possibly matter?
And that's sort of like
saying, is that the
same thing as this?
Or is this the same
thing as that?
It's the same kind
of question.
And that's a very, very
deep question.
And I can't answer in
less than an hour.
But we will.