[MUSIC PLAYING]
PROFESSOR: Well, last time we
talked about compound data,
and there were two main points
to that business.
First of all, there was
a methodology of data
abstraction, and the point of
that was that you could
isolate the way that data
objects are used from the way
that they're represented: this
idea that there's this guy,
George, and you go out make a
contract with him; and it's
his business to represent the
data objects; and at the
moment you are using them,
you don't think
about George's problem.
And then secondly, there was
this particular way that Lisp
has of gluing together things to
form objects called pairs,
and that's done with cons, car
and cdr. And the way that
cons, car and cdr are
implemented is basically
irrelevant.
That's sort of George's
problem of how
to build those things.
It could be done
as primitives.
It could be done using
procedures in some weird way,
but we're not going to
worry about that.
And as an example, we looked at
rational number arithmetic.
We looked at vectors,
and here's
just a review of vectors.
Here's an operation that takes
the sum of of two vectors, so
we want to add this vector, v1,
and this vector, v2, and
we get the sum.
And the sum is the vector whose
coordinates are the sum
of the coordinates of the
pieces you're adding.
So I can say, to define
make-vect, right, to add two
vectors I make a vector, whose x
coordinate is the sum of the
two x coordinates, and whose y
two y coordinates.
And then similarly, we could
have an operation that scales
vectors, so here's a procedure
scale that multiplies a
vector, v, by some number, s.
So here's v, v goes from there
to there and I scale v, and I
get a vector in the same
direction that's longer.
And again, to scale a vector,
I multiply the successive
coordinates.
So I make a vector, whose x
coordinate is the scale factor
times the x coordinate and
whose y coordinate is the
scale factor times
the y coordinate.
So those are two operations that
are implemented using the
representation of vectors.
And the representation of
vectors, for instance, is
something that we can build
in terms of pairs.
So George has gone out and
implemented for us make-vector
and x coordinate and y
coordinate, and this could be
done, for instance, using cons,
car and cdr; and notice
here, I wrote this in a slightly
different way.
The procedures we've seen
before, I've said something
like say, make-vector of x
and y: cons of x and y.
And here I just wrote
make-vector cons.
And that means something
slightly different.
Previously we'd say, define
make-vector to be a procedure
that takes two arguments,
x and y, and does
cons of x and y.
And here I am saying define
make-vector to be the thing
that cons is, and that's almost
the same as the other
way we've been writing things.
And I just want you to get
used to the idea that
procedures can be objects, and
that you can name them.
OK, well there's vector
representation, and again, if
that was all there was
to it, this would
all be pretty boring.
And the point is, remember, that
you can use cons to glue
together not just numbers to
form pairs, but to glue
together arbitrary things.
So for instance, if we'd like
to represent a line segment,
say the line segment that goes
from a certain vector: say,
the segment from the vector 2,3
to the point represented
by the vector 5,1.
If we want to represent that
line segment, then we can
build that as a pair of pairs.
So again, we can represent
line segments.
We can make a constructor that
makes a segment using cons,
selects out the start of a
segment, selects out the end
point of the segment; and then
if we actually look at that,
if we peel away the abstraction
layers, and say
what's that really is a pair
of pairs, we'd say
well that's a pair.
Here's the segment.
It's car, right, it's car
pointer is a pair, and it's
cdr is also a pair, and then
what the car is-- here's the
car, that itself is
a pair of 2 and 3.
And similarly the cdr is
And let me remind you again,
that a lot of people have some
idea that if I'd taken this
arrow and somehow written it
to point down, that would
mean something else.
That's irrelevant.
It's only how these are
connected and not whether this
arrow happens to go vertically
or horizontally.
And again just to remind
you, there was
this notion of closure.
See, closure was the thing
that allowed us to start
building up complexity, that
didn't trap us in pairs.
Particularly what I mean is
the things that we make,
having combined things using
cons to get a pair, those
things themselves can be
combined using cons to make
more complicated things.
Or as a mathematician might say,
the set of data objects
in List is closed under the
operation of forming pairs.
That's the thing that allows
us to build complexity.
And that seems obvious, but
remember, a lot of the things
in the computer languages that
people use are not closed.
So for example, forming arrays
in basic and Fortran is not a
closed operation, because you
can make an array of numbers
or character strings or
something, but you can't make
an array of arrays.
And when you look at means of
combination, you should be
should be asking yourself
whether things are closed
under that means
of combination.
Well in any case, because we
can form pairs of pairs, we
can start using pairs to glue
things together in all sorts
of different ways.
So for instance if I'd like to
glue together the four things,
1, 2, 3 and 4, there are a
lot of ways I can do it.
I could, for example, like we
did with that line segment, I
could make a pair that
had a 1 and a 2 and
a 3 and a 4, right?
Or if I liked, I could do
something like this.
I could make a pair, whose first
thing is a pair, whose
car is 1, and his cdr is itself
a pair that has the 2
and the 3, and then I could
put the 4 up here.
So you see, there are a lot of
different ways that I can
start using pairs to glue things
together, and so it'll
be a good idea to establish
some kind of conventions,
right, that allow us to deal
with this thing in some
conventional way, so we're
not constantly
making an ad hoc choice.
And List has a particular
convention for representing a
sequence of things as,
essentially, a chain of pairs,
and that's called a List.
And what a List is is
essentially just a convention
for representing a sequence.
I would represent the sequence
1, 2, 3 and 4 by
a sequence of pairs.
I'd put 1 here and then the
cdr of this would point to
another pair whose car was the
next thing in the sequence,
and the cdr would point to
another pair whose car was the
next thing in the sequence--
so there's 3--
and then another one.
So for each item in the
sequence, I'll get a pair.
And now there are no more, so
I put a special marker that
means there's nothing more in
the List. OK, so that's a
conventional way to glue things
together if you want to
represent a sequence, right.
And what it is is a bunch of
pairs, the successive cars of
each pair are the items that you
want to glue together, and
the cdr pointer points
to the next pair.
Now if I actually wanted to
construct that, what I would
type into List is this: I'd
actually construct that as
saying, well this thing is the
cons of 1 onto the cons of 2
onto the cons of 3 onto
the cons of 4 onto,
well, this thing nil.
And what nil is is a name for
the end of List marker.
It's a special name, which means
this is the end of the
List. OK, so that's how I would
actually construct that.
Of course, it's a terrible drag
to constantly have to
write something like the cons
of 1 onto the cons of 2 onto
the cons of 3, whenever you
want to make this thing.
So List has an operation that's
called List, and List
is just an abbreviation for
this nest of conses.
So I could say, I could
construct that by saying that
is the List of 1, 2, 3 and 4.
And all this is is another
way, a piece of syntactic
sugar, a more convenient
way for writing
that chain of conses--
cons of cons of cons of cons
of cons of cons onto nil.
So for example, I could build
this thing and say, I'll
define 1-TO-4 to be the
List of 1, 2, 3 and 4.
OK, well notice some of the
consequences of using this
convention.
First of all if I have this
List, this 1, 2, 3 and 4, the
car of the whole thing
is the first element
in the List, right.
How do I get 2?
Well, 2 would be the car of the
cdr of this thing 1-TO-4,
it would be 2, right.
I take this thing, I take the
cdr of it, which is this much,
and the car of that is 2, and
then similarly, the car of the
cdr of the cdr of 1-TO-4,
cdr, cdr, car--
would give me 3, and so on.
Let's take a look at that
on the computer
screen for a second.
I could come up to List, and I
could type define 1-TO-4 to be
the List of 1, 2,
3 and 4, right.
And I'll tell that to List, and
it says, fine, that's the
definition of 1-TO-4.
And I could say, for instance,
what's the car of the cdr of
the cdr of 1-TO-4, close
paren, close paren.
Right, so the car of the cdr
of the cdr would be 3.
Right, or I could say,
what's 1-TO-4 itself.
And you see what List typed out
is 1, 2, 3, 4, enclosed in
parentheses, and this notation,
typing the elements
of the List enclosed in
parentheses is List's
conventional way for printing
back this chain of pairs that
represents a sequence.
So for example, if I said,
what's the cdr of 1-TO-4,
that's going to be the rest of
the List. That's the thing
pointed to by the first pair,
which is, again, a sequence
that starts off with 2.
Or for example, I go off and
say, what's the cdr of the cdr
of 1-TO-4; then that's 3,4.
Or if I say, what's the cdr of
the cdr of the cdr of the cdr
of 1-TO-4, and I'm down there
looking at the end of List
pointer itself, and List prints
that as just open
paren, close paren.
You can think of that as a List
with nothing in there.
All right, see at the end what
I did there was I looked at
the cdr of the cdr of the cdr
of 1-TO-4, and I'm just left
with the end of List
pointer itself.
And that gets printed
as open close.
All right, well that's a
conventional way you can see
for working down a
List by taking
successive cdrs of things.
It's called cdring down a
List. And of course it's
pretty much of a drag to type
all those cdrs by hand.
You don't do that.
You write procedures
that do that.
And in fact one very, very
common thing to do in List is
to write procedures that, sort
of, take a List of things and
do something to every element in
List, and return you a List
of the results.
So what I mean for example, is
I might write a procedure
called Scale-List, and
Scale-List I might say I want
to scale by 10 the entire List
1-TO-4, and that would return
for me the List 10,
20, 30, 40.
[UNINTELLIGIBLE PHRASE]
Right, it returns List, and well
you can see that there's
going to be some kind
of recursive
strategy for doing it.
How would I actually write
that procedure?
The idea would be, well if you'd
like to build up a List
where you've multiplied every
element by 10, what you'd say
is well you imagine that you'd
taken the rest of the List--
right, the thing represented
by the cdr of the List, and
suppose I'd already built a List
where each of these was
multiplied by 10--
that would be Scale-List of the
cdr of the List. And then
all I have to do is multiply the
car of the List by 10, and
then cons that onto the rest,
and I'll get a List.
Right and then similarly, to
have scaled the cdr of the
List, I'll scale the cdr of
that and cons onto that 2
multiplied by 10.
And finally when I get all the
way down to the end, and I
only have this end
of List pointer.
All right, this thing whose
name is nil-- well I just
returned an end of
List pointer.
So there's a recursive strategy
for doing that.
Here's the actual procedure
that does that.
Right, this is an example of
the general strategy of
cdr-ing down a List and
so called cons-ing
up the result, right.
So to Scale a List l by some
scale factor s, what do I do?
Well there's a test, and List
has the predicate called null.
Null means is this thing the
end of List pointer, or
another way to think of that is
are there any elements in
this List, right.
But in any case if I'm looking
at the end of List pointer,
then I just return the
end of List pointer.
I just return nil, otherwise I
cons together the result of
doing what I'm going to do to
the first element in the List,
namely taking the car of l and
multiplying it by s, and I
cons that onto recursively
scaling the rest of the List.
OK, so again, the general idea
is that you recursively do
something to the rest of the
List, to the cdr of the List,
and then you cons that onto
actually doing something to
the first element of the List.
When you get down to the end
here, you return the end of
List pointer, and that's a
general pattern for doing
something to a List. Well of
course you should know by now
that the very fact that
there's a general pattern there
means I shouldn't be
writing this procedure at all.
What I should do is write a
procedure that's the general
pattern itself that says, do
something to everything in the
List and define this thing
in terms of that.
Right, make some higher order
procedure, and here's the
higher order procedure
that does that.
It's called MAP, and what MAP
does is it takes a List, takes
a List l, and it takes a
procedure p, and it returns
the List of the elements gotten
by applying p to each
successive element in the List.
All right, so p to v1, p
to v2, p of en.
Right, so I think of taking this
List and transforming it
by applying p to each element.
And you see all this procedure
is is exactly the general
strategy I said.
Instead of multiply by 10,
it's do the procedure.
If the List is empty,
return nil.
Otherwise, apply p to the first
element of the List.
Right, apply p to car of l, and
cons that onto the result
of applying p to everything in
the cdr of the List, so that's
a general procedure
called MAP.
And I could define Scale-List
in terms of MAP.
Let me show you that first.
But I could say Scale-List is
another way to define it is
just MAP along the List by the
procedure, which takes an item
and multiplies it by s.
Right, so this is really the
way I should think about
scaling the List, build that
actual recursion into the
general strategy, not to every
particular procedure I write.
And of course, one of the values
of doing this is that
you start to see commonality.
Right, again you're capturing
general patterns of usage.
For instance, if I said MAP,
the square procedure, down
this List 1-TO-4, then I'd end
up with 1, 4, 9 and 16.
Right, or if I said MAP down
this List, lambda of x plus
x10, if I MAP that down 1-TO-4,
then I'd get the List
where everything had 10 added
to it: right, so I'd get 11,
12, 13, 14.
And you can see that's going
to be a very, very common
idea: doing something to every
element in the List.
One thing you might think about
is writing MAP in an
iterative style.
The one I wrote happens to
evolve a recursive process,
but we could just as easily have
made one that evolves an
iterative process.
But see the interesting thing
about it is that once you
start thinking in
terms of MAP--
see, once you say scale is just
MAP, you stop thinking
about whether it's iterative
or recursive, and you just
say, well there's this
aggregate, there's this List,
and what I do is transform every
item in the List, and I
stop thinking about the
particular control
structure in order.
That's a very, very important
idea, and it, I guess it
really comes out of APL.
It's, sort of, the really
important idea in APL that you
stop thinking about control
structures, and you start
thinking about operations on
aggregates, and then about
halfway through this course,
we'll see when we talk about
something called stream
processing, how that view of
the world really comes
into its glory.
This is just us a, sort
of, cute idea.
But we'll see much more
applications of that later on.
Well let me mention that there's
something that's very
similar to MAP that's also a
useful idea, and that's--
see, MAP says I take a List, I
apply something to each item,
and I return a List of the
successive values.
There's another thing I might
do, which is very, very
similar, which is take a List
and some action you want to do
and then do it to each item
in the List in sequence.
Don't make a List of the
values, just do this
particular action, and that's
something that's
very much like MAP.
It's called for-each, and
for-each takes a procedure and
a List, and what it's going to
do is do something to every
item in the List. So basically
what it does: it says if the
List is not empty, right, if
the List is not null, then
what I do is, I apply my
procedure to the first item in
the List, and then I do this
thing to the rest of the List.
I apply for-each to the
cdr of the List.
All right, so I do it to the
first of the List, do it to
the rest of the List, and of
course, when I call it
recursively, that's going to do
it to the rest of the rest
of the List and so on.
And finally, when I get done, I
have to just do something to
say I'm done, so we'll return
the message "done." So that's
very, very similar to MAP.
It's mostly different
in what it returns.
And so for example, if I had
some procedure that printed
things on the screen, if I
wanted to print everything in
the List, I could say for-each,
print this List. Or
if I had a List of figures, and
I wanted to draw them on
the display, I could say
for-each, display on the
screen this figure.
Let's take questions.
AUDIENCE: Does it create a new
copy with something done to
it, unless you explicitly
tell it to do that?
Is that correct?
PROFESSOR: Right.
Yeah, that's right.
For-each does not create
a List. It just
sort of does something.
So if you have a bunch of things
you want to do and
you're not worried about
values like printing
something, or drawing something
on the screen, or
ringing the bell on the
terminal, or for something,
you can say for-each, you know,
do this for-each of
those things in the List,
whereas MAP actually builds
you this new collection
of values that you
might want to use.
It's just a subtle difference
between them.
AUDIENCE: Could you write MAP
using for-each, so that you
did some sort of cons or
something to build
the List back up?
PROFESSOR: Well, sort of.
I mean, I probably could.
I can't think of how to do it
right offhand, but yeah, I
could arrange something.
AUDIENCE: The vital difference
between MAP and for-each is
one is recursive and the other
is not in the sense you
defined early yesterday,
I believe.
PROFESSOR: Yeah, about MAP and
for-each and recursion.
Yeah, that's a good point.
For the MAP procedure I
wrote, that happens to
be a recursive process.
And the reason for that is that
when you've done this
thing to the rest of the List,
you're waiting for that value
so that you can stick it on to
the beginning of the List,
whereas for-each doesn't
really have any
values to wait for.
So that turns out to be
an iterative process.
That's not fundamental.
I could have defined MAP so
that it's evolved by an
iterative process.
I just didn't happen to.
AUDIENCE: If you were to cons
for each with a List that had
embedded Lists, I imagine
it would work, right?
It would give you the internal
elements of each of those
internal Lists?
PROFESSOR: OK, the question
is if I [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
for each or MAP, for that
matter, with a List that had
Lists in it--
although we haven't really
looked at that yet--
would that work.
The answer is yes in the sense
I mean work and no in the
sense that you mean work,
because all that--
see if I give you a List, where
hanging off here is, you
know, is something that's not
a number, maybe another List
or you know, another cons or
something, for-each just says
do something to each item in
this List. It goes down
successively looking
at the cdrs.
AUDIENCE: OK.
PROFESSOR: And as far as it's
concerned, the first item in
this List is whatever
is hanging off here.
AUDIENCE: Mhm.
PROFESSOR: That might or might
not be the right thing.
AUDIENCE: So it wouldn't
go down into the--
PROFESSOR: Absolutely not.
I could certainly write
something else.
There's another, what you're
looking for is a common
pattern of usage called tree
recursion, where you take a
List, and you actually go all
the way down to the what's
called the leaves of the tree.
And you could write such a
thing, but that's not for-each
and it's not MAP.
Remember, these things
are really
being very simple minded.
OK, no more questions?
All right, let's break.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
PROFESSOR: What I'd like to do
now is spend the rest of this
time talking about one example,
and this example, I
think, pretty much summarizes
everything that we've done up
until now: all right, and that's
List structure and
issues of abstraction, and
representation and capturing
commonality with higher order
procedures, and also is going
to introduce something we
haven't really talked about a
lot yet-- what I said is the
major third theme in this
course: meta-linguistic
abstraction, which is the idea
that one of the ways of
tackling complexity in
engineering design is to build
a suitable powerful language.
You might recall what I said was
pretty much the very most
important thing that we're
going to tell you in this
course is that when you think
about a language, you think
about it in terms of what are
the primitives; what are the
means of combination--
right, what are the things that
allow you to build bigger
things; and then what are the
means of abstraction.
How do you take those bigger
things that you've built and
put black boxes around them and
use them as elements in
making something even
more complicated?
Now the particular language I'm
going to talk about is an
example that was made up
by a friend of ours
called Peter Henderson.
Peter Henderson is
at the University
of Stirling in Scotland.
And what this language is about
is making figures that
sort of look like this.
This is this is a woodcut by
Escher called "Square Limit."
You, sort of, see it has this
complicated, kind of,
recursive, sort of, recursive
kind of figure, where there's
this fish pattern in the middle
and things sort of
bleed out smaller and smaller
in self similar ways.
Anyway, Peter Henderson's
language was for describing
figures that look like that and
designing new ones that
look like that and drawing
them on a display screen.
There's another theme that we'll
see illustrated by this
example, and that's the issue
of what Gerry and I have
already mentioned a lot: that
there's no real difference, in
some sense, between procedures
and data.
And anyway I hope by the end of
this morning, if you're not
already, you will be completely
confused about what
the difference between
procedures and data are, if
you're not confused about
that already.
Well in any case, let's start
describing Peter's language.
I should start by telling you
what the primitives are.
This language is very
simple because
there's only one primitive.
A primitive is not quite
what you think it is.
There's only one primitive
called a picture, and a
picture is not quite what
you think it is.
Here's an example.
This is a picture of George.
The idea is that a picture in
this language is going to be
something that draws a figure
scaled to fit a rectangle that
you specify.
So here you see in [? Saint ?]
[? Lawrence's ?]
outline of a rectangle, that's
not really part of the
picture, but the picture--
you'll give it a rectangle, and
it will draw this figure
scaled to fit the rectangle.
So for example, there's
George, and here,
this is also George.
It's the same picture,
right, just scaled to
fit a different rectangle.
Here's George as a fat kid.
That's the same George.
It's all the same figure.
All of these three things
are the same
picture in this language.
I'm just giving it different
rectangles to scale itself in.
OK, those are the primitives.
That is the primitive.
Now let's start talking about
the means of combination and
the operations.
There is, for example, an
operation called Rotate.
And what Rotate does is, if I
have a picture, say a picture
that draws an "A" in some
rectangle that I give it, the
Rotate of that--
say the Rotate by 90 degrees
would, if I give it a
rectangle, draw the same image,
but again, scaled to
fit that rectangle.
So that's Rotate
by 90 degrees.
There's another operation called
Flip that can flip
something, either horizontally
or vertically.
All right, so those are, sort
of, operations, or you can
think of those as means of
combination of one element.
I can put things together.
There's a means of combination
called Beside, and what Beside
does: it'll take two pictures,
let's say A and B--
and by picture I mean something
that's going to draw
an image in a specified
rectangle--
and what Beside will do--
I have to say, Beside of A and
B, the side of two pictures
and some number, s.
And s will be a number
between zero and one.
And Beside will draw a picture
that looks like this.
It will take the rectangle
you give it and
scale its base by s.
Say s is 0.5.
And then over here
it will draw--
it'll put the first picture,
and over here it'll put the
second picture.
Or for instance if I gave it a
different value of s, if I
said Beside with a 0.25, it
would do the same thing,
except the A would
be much skinnier.
So it would draw something
like that.
So there's a means of
combination Beside, and
similarly there's an Above,
which does the same thing
except it puts them vertically
instead of horizontally.
Well let's look at that.
All right, there's George and
his kid brother, which is,
right, constructed by taking
George and putting him Beside
the Above--
taking the empty picture, and
there's a thing called the
empty picture, which does
the obvious thing--
putting the empty picture above
a copy of George, and
then putting that whole
thing Beside George.
Here's something called P which
is, again, George Beside
Flipping George, I think,
horizontally in this case, and
then Rotating the whole result
180 degrees and putting them
Beside one another with the
basic rectangle divided at
0.5, right, and I can call that
P. And then I can take P,
and put it above the Flipped
copy of itself, and I can call
that Q.
Notice how rapidly that we've
built up complexity, just in,
you know, 15 seconds, you've
gotten from George to that
thing Q. Why is that?
How are how we able to
do that so fast?
The answer is the closure
property.
See, it's the fact that when
I take a picture and put it
Beside another picture, that's
then, again, a picture that I
can go and Rotate and Flip or
put Above something else.
Right, and when I take that
element P, which is the Beside
or the Flip or the Rotate
of something,
that's, again, a picture.
Right, the world of pictures is
closed under those means of
combination.
So whenever I have something,
I can turn right around and
use that as an element
in something else.
So maybe better than List and
segments, that just gives you
an image for how fast you can
build up complexity, because
operations are closed.
OK, well before we go on with
building more things, let's
talk about how this language
is actually implemented.
The basic element that sits
under the table here is a
thing called a rectangle, and
what a rectangle is going to
be, it's a thing that specified
by an origin that's
going to be some vector
that says where
the rectangle starts.
And then there's going to be
some other vector that I'm
going to call the horizontal
part of the rectangle, and
another picture called the
vertical part of the rectangle.
And those three pieces are the
elements: where the lower
vertex is, how you get to the
next vertex over here, and how
you get to the vertex
over there.
The three vectors specify
a rectangle.
Now to actually build
rectangles, what I'll assume
is that we have a constructor
called "make rectangle," or
"make-rect," and selectors for
horiz and vert and origin that
get out the pieces of
that rectangle.
And well, you know a lot of
ways you can do this now.
You can do it by using pairs in
some way or other standard
List or not.
But in any case, the
implementation of these
things, that's George's
problem.
It's just a data representation
So let's assume we have these
rectangles to work with.
OK.
Now the idea of this, remember
what's got to happen.
Somehow we have to worry about
taking the figure and scaling
it to fit some rectangle that
you give it, that's the basic
thing you have to arrange, that
these pictures can do.
How do we think about that?
Well, one way to think about
that is that any time I give
you a rectangle, that defines,
in some sense, a
transformation from
the standard
square into that rectangle.
Let me say what I mean.
By the standard square, I'll
mean something, which is a
square whose coordinates are
0,0, and 1,0, and 0,1 and 1,1.
And there's some sort of
the obvious scaling
transformation, which maps this
to that and this to that,
and sort of, stretches
everything uniformly.
So we take a line segment like
this and end up mapping it to
a line segment like that, so
some point xy goes to some
other point up there.
And although it's not important,
with a little
vector algebra, you could
write that formula.
The thing that xy goes to, the
point that xy goes to is
gotten by taking the origin of
the rectangle and then adding
that as a vector to--
well, take x, the x coordinate,
which is something
between zero and one, multiply
that by the horizontal vector
of the rectangle; and take the
y coordinate, which is also
something between zero and one
and multiply that by the
vertical vector of
the rectangle.
That's just a little
linear algebra.
Anyway, that's the formula,
which is the right obvious
transformation that takes things
into the unit square,
into the interior of
that rectangle.
OK well, let's actually look
at that as a procedure.
So what we want is the thing
which tells us that particular
transformation that a
rectangle defines.
So here's the procedure.
I'll call it coordinate-map.
Coordinate-map is the thing that
takes as its argument a
rectangle and returns for you
a procedure on points.
Right, so for each rectangle you
get a way of transforming
a point xy into that
rectangle.
And how do you get it?
Well I just--
writing in List what I wrote
there on the blackboard--
I add to the origin
of the rectangle
the result of adding--
I take the horizontal part of
the rectangle; I scale that by
the x coordinate of the point.
I take the vertical vector
of the rectangle.
I scale that by the y coordinate
of the point, and
then add all those
three things up.
That's the procedure.
That is the procedure that I'm
going to apply to a point.
And this whole thing is
generated for each rectangle.
So any rectangle defines a
coordinate MAP, which is a
procedure on points.
OK.
All right, so for example,
George here, my original
George, might have been
something that I specified by
segments in the unit square, and
then for each rectangle I
give this thing, I'm going to
draw those segments inside
that rectangle.
How actually do I do that?
Well I take each segment in my
original reference George that
was specified, and to each of
the end points of those
segments, I applied the
coordinate MAP of the
particular rectangle I
want to draw it in.
So for example, this lower
rectangle, this George as a
fat kid rectangle, has
its coordinate MAP.
And if I want to draw this
image, what I do is for each
segment here, say for this
segment, I transformed that
point by the coordinate MAP,
transform that point by the
coordinate MAP.
That will give me this point
and that point and draw the
segment between them.
Right, that's the idea.
Right, and if I give it a
different rectangle like this
one, that's a different
coordinate MAP, so I get a
different image of those
line segments.
Well how do we actually get
a picture to start with?
I can build a picture to start
with out of a List of line
segments initially.
Here's a procedure that builds
what I'll call a primitive
picture, meaning one I, sort of,
got that didn't come out
of Beside or Rotate
or something.
It starts with a List of
line segments, and now
it does what I said.
What's a picture have to be?
First of all it's a procedure
that's defined on rectangles.
What does it do?
It says for each--
this is going to be a List
of line segments--
for each segment, for each s,
which is a segment in this
List of segments, well
it draws a line.
What line does it draw?
It gets the start point of that
segment, transforms that
by the coordinate MAP
of the rectangle.
That's the first new point
it wants to do.
Then it takes the endpoint of
the segment, transforms that
by the coordinate MAP of the
rectangle, and then draws a
line between.
Let's assume drawline is some
primitive that's built into
the system that actually draws
a line on the display.
All right, so it transforms
the endpoints by the
coordinate MAP of the rectangle,
draws a line
between them, does that
for each s in
this List of segments.
And now remember again, a
picture is a procedure that
takes a rectangle as argument.
So when you hand it a rectangle,
this is what it
does: draws those lines.
All right, so there's--
how would I actually
use this thing?
Let's make it a little
bit more concrete.
Right, I would say for instance,
define R to be
make-rectangle of some stuff,
and I'd have to specify some
vectors here using
make-vector.
And then I could say, define
say, G to be make-picture, and
then some stuff.
And what I'd have to specify
here is a List of line
segments, right, using
make segment.
Make-segment might be made out
of vectors, and vectors might
be made out of points.
And then if I actually wanted to
see the image of G inside a
rectangle, well a picture is
a procedure that takes a
rectangle as argument.
So if I then called G with an
input of R, that would cause
whatever image G is worrying
about to be drawn inside the
rectangle R. Right, so that's
how you'd use that.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
PROFESSOR: Well why is it that
I say this example is nice?
You probably don't
think it's nice.
You probably think it's
more weird than nice.
Right, representing these
pictures as procedures, which
do complicated things
with rectangles.
So why is it nice?
The reason it's nice is that
once you've implemented the
primitives in this way, the
means of combination just fall
out by implementing
procedures.
Let me show you what I mean.
Suppose we want to
implement Beside.
So I'd like to--
suppose I've got a picture.
Let's call it P1.
P1 is going to be-- and
now remember what a
picture really is.
It's a thing that if you can
hand it some rectangle, it
will cause an image to be drawn
in whatever rectangle
you hand it.
And suppose P2 two is some other
picture, and you hand
that a rectangle.
And whatever rectangle
you hand it,
it draws some picture.
And now if I'd like to implement
Beside of P1 and P2
with a scale factor A, well
what does that have to be?
That's got to be picture.
It's got to be a thing that you
hand it a rectangle, and
it draws something in
that rectangle.
So if hand Beside
this rectangle--
let's hand it a rectangle.
Well what's it going to do?
it's going to take this
rectangle and split it into
two at a ratio of A and one
minus A. And it will say, oh
sure, now I've got
two rectangles.
And now it goes off to P1 and
says P1, well draw yourself in
this rectangle, and goes off
to P2, and says, P2, fine,
draw yourself in
this rectangle.
The only computation it has to
do is figure out what these
rectangles are.
Remember a rectangle is
specified by an origin and a
horizontal vector and a vertical
vector, so it's got
to figure out what
these things are.
So for this first rectangle, the
origin turns out to be the
origin of the original
rectangle, and the vertical
vector is the same as the
vertical vector of the
original rectangle.
The horizontal vector is the
horizontal vector of the
original rectangle
scaled by A. And
that's the first rectangle.
The second rectangle, the origin
is the original origin
plus that horizontal vector
scaled by A. The horizontal
vector of the second rectangle
is the rest of the horizontal
vector of the first one, which
is 1 minus A times the
original H, and the vertical
vector is still v. But
basically it goes and
constructs these two
rectangles, and the important
point is having constructed
the rectangles, it says OK,
p1, you draw yourself in
there, and p2, you draw yourself
in there, and that's
all Beside has to do.
All right, let's look at
that piece of code.
Beside of a picture and another
picture with some
scaling ratio is first of all,
since it's a picture, a
procedure that's going to take
a rectangle as argument.
What's it going to do?
It says, p1 draw yourself in
some rectangle and p2 draw
yourself in some other
rectangle.
And now what are those
rectangles?
Well here's the computation.
It makes a rectangle, and this
is the algebra I just did on
the board: the origin,
something; the horizontal
vector, something; and the
vertical vector, something.
And for p2, the rectangle it
wants has some other origin
and horizontal vector
and vertical vector.
But the important point is that
all it's saying is, p1,
go do your thing in one
rectangle, and p2, go do your
thing in another rectangle.
That's all the Beside
has to do.
OK, similarly Rotate--
see if I have this picture A,
and I want to look at say
rotating A by 90 degrees, what
that should mean is, well take
this rectangle, which is origin
and horizontal vector
and vertical vector, and now
pretend that it's really the
rectangle that looks like this,
which has an origin and
a horizontal vector up here, and
a vertical vector there,
and now draw yourself with
respect to that rectangle.
Let me show you that
as a procedure.
All right, so we'll Rotate 90 of
the picture, because again,
a procedure for rectangle, which
says, OK picture, draw
yourself in some rectangle; and
then this algebra is the
transformation on
the rectangle.
It's the one which makes it
look like the rectangle is
sideways, the origin is
someplace else and the
vertical vector is someplace
else, and the horizontal
vector is someplace else,
and vertical vector
is someplace else.
OK?
OK.
OK, again notice, the crucial
thing that's going on here is
you're using the representation
of pictures as
procedures to automatically
get the closure property,
because what happens is, Beside
just has this thing p1.
Beside doesn't care if that's
a primitive picture or it's
line segments or if p1 is,
itself, the result of doing
Aboves or Besides or Rotates.
All Beside has to know about,
say, p1 is that if you hand p1
a rectangle, it will cause
something to be drawn.
And above that level, Beside
just doesn't--
it's none of its business how p1
accomplishes that drawing.
All right, so you're using the
procedural representation to
ensure this closure.
OK.
So implementing pictures as
procedures makes these means
of combination, you know, both
pretty simple and also, I
think, elegant.
But that's not the
real punchline.
The real punchline comes when
you look at the means of
abstraction in this language.
Because what have we done?
We've implemented the means of
combination themselves as
procedures.
And what that means is that when
we go to abstract in this
language, everything that List
supplies us for manipulating
procedures is automatically
available to do things in this
picture language.
The technical term I want to
say is not only is this
language implemented in List,
obviously it is, but the
language is nicely embedded
in List. What I mean is by
embedding the language in this
way, all the power of List is
automatically available
as an extension to
whatever you want to do.
And what do I mean by that?
Example: say, suppose I want
to make a thing that takes
four pictures A, B, C and D, and
makes a configuration that
looks like this.
Well you might call that, you
know, four pictures or
something, four-pict
configuration.
How do I do that?
Well I can obviously do that.
I just write a procedure that
takes B above D and A above C
and puts those things
beside each other.
So I automatically have List's
ability to do procedure
composition.
And I didn't have to make
that specifically
in the picture language.
It's automatic from the fact
that the means of combination
are themselves procedures.
Or suppose I wanted to do
something a little bit more
complicated.
I wanted to put in a parameter
so that for each of these, I
could independently specify
a rotation by 90 degrees.
That's just putting a parameter
in the procedure.
It's automatically there.
Right, it automatically comes
from the embedding.
Or even more, suppose I wanted
to, you know, use recursion.
Let's look at a recursive
means of
combination on pictures.
I could say define--
let's see if you can figure out
what this one is-- suppose
I say define what it means
to right-push a picture,
right-push a picture and some
integer N and some scale
factor A. I'll define this to
say if N equals 0, then the
answer is the picture.
Otherwise I'm going to put--
oops, name change: P. Otherwise,
I'm going to take P
and put it beside the results of
recursively right-pushing P
with N minus 1 and A and use a
scale factor of A. OK, so if
N0 , it's P. Otherwise I put P
with a scale factor of A--
I'm sorry I didn't align
this right--
recursively beside the result of
right-pushing P, N minus 1
times with a scale
factor of A.
There's a recursive means
of combination.
What's that look like?
Well, here's what
it looks like.
There's George right-pushed
against himself twice with a
scale factor of 0.75.
OK.
Where'd that come from?
How did I get all this
fancy recursion?
And the answer is just
automatic, absolutely automatic.
Since these are procedures, the
embedding says, well sure,
I can define recursive
procedures.
I didn't have to arrange that.
And of course, we can
do more complicated
things of the same sort.
I could make something
that does an up-push.
Right, that sort of goes like
this, by recursively putting
something above.
Or I could make something
that, sort
of, was this scheme.
I might start out with a picture
and then, sort of,
recursively both push it aside
and above, and that might put
something there.
And then up here I put the same
recursive thing, and I
might end up with something
like this.
Right, so there's a procedure
that's a little bit more
complicated than right-push
but not much.
I just do an Above
and a Beside,
rather than just a Beside.
Now if I take that and apply
that with the idea of putting
four pictures together, which I
can surely do; and I go and
I apply that to Q, which we
defined before, right, what I
end up with this is this thing,
which is, sort of, the
square limit of Q, done twice.
Right, and then we can compare
that with Escher's "Square
Limit." And you see, it's
sort of the same idea.
Escher's is, of course,
much, much prettier.
If we go back and look at
George, right, if we go look
at George here--
see, I started with a fairly
arbitrary design, this picture
of George and did
things with it.
Right, whereas if we go look at
the Escher picture, right,
the Escher picture is not
an arbitrary design.
It's this very, very clever
thing, so that when you take
this fish body and Rotate it and
shrink it down, it bleeds
into the next one
really nicely.
And of course with George,
I didn't really do
anything like that.
So if we look at George, right,
there's a little bit of
match up, but not very nice,
and it's pretty arbitrary.
One very nice project, by the
way, would be to write a
procedure that could take some
basic figure like this George
thing and start moving the ends
of the lines around, so
you got a really nice one when
you went and did that "Square
Limit" process.
That'd be a really nice
thing to think about.
Well so, we can combine
things.
We can recursive procedures.
We can do all kinds of things,
and that's all automatic.
Right, the important point, the
difference between merely
implementing something in
a language and embedding
something in the language, so
that you don't lose the
original power of the language,
and what List is
great at, see List is a lousy
language for doing any
particular problem.
What it's good for is figuring
out the right language that
you want and embedding that in
List. That's the real power of
this approach to design.
Of course, we can go further.
See, you saw the other thing
that we can do in List is
capture general methods of doing
things as higher order
procedures.
And you probably just from me
drawing it got the idea that
right-push and the analogous
thing where you push something
up and up and up and up and this
corner push thing are all
generalizations of a common
kind of idea.
So just to illustrate and give
you practice in looking at a
fairly convoluted use of higher
order procedures, let
me show you the general idea
of pushing some means of
combination to recursively
repeat it.
So here's a good one
to puzzle out.
We'll define it what it means
to push using a means of
combination.
Comb is going to be something
like the Beside or Above.
Well what's that going to be.
That's going to be a procedure,
remember what
Beside actually was, right.
It took a picture, took two
pictures and a scale factor.
Using that I produced something
that took a level
number and a picture and a scale
factor, that I called
right-push.
So this is going to be something
that takes a
picture, a level number and
a scale factor, and
it's going to say--
I'm going to do some
repeated operation.
I'm going to repeatedly apply
the procedure which takes a
picture and applies the means of
combination to the picture
and the original picture and the
one I took in here and the
scale factor, and I do the
thing which repeats this
procedure N times, and I apply
that whole thing to my
original picture.
Repeated here, in case you
haven't seen it, is another
higher order procedure that
takes a procedure and a number
and returns for you another
procedure that applies this
procedure N times.
And I think some of you have
already written repeated as an
exercise, but if you haven't,
it's a very good exercise in
thinking about higher
order procedures.
But in any case, the result of
this repeated is what I apply
to picture.
And having done that, that's
going to capture--
that is the thing, the way I got
from the idea of Beside to
the idea of right-push So having
done that, I could say
define right-push to
be push of Beside.
Or if I say, define up-push to
be push of Beside, I'd get the
analogous thing or define
corner-push to be push of some
appropriate thing that did both
the Beside and Above, or
I could push anything.
Anyway this is, if you're having
trouble with lambdas,
this is an excellent exercise
in figuring
out what this means.
OK, well there's a lot to
learn from this example.
The main point I've been
dwelling on is the notion of
nicely embedding a language
inside another language.
Right, so that all the power of
this language like List of
the surrounding language is
still accessible to you and
appears as a natural
extension of the
language that you built.
That's one thing that this
example shows very well.
OK.
Another thing is, if you go
back and think about that,
what's procedures
and what's data.
You know, by the time we
get up to here, my God,
what's going on.
I mean, this is some procedure,
and it takes a
picture and an argument,
and what's a picture.
Well, a picture itself, as you
remember, was a procedure, and
that took a rectangle.
And a rectangle is
some abstraction.
And I hope now that by now
you're completely lost as to
the question of what
in the system is
procedure and what's data.
You see, there isn't
any difference.
There really isn't.
And you might think of a
picture sometimes as a
procedure and sometimes as data,
but that's just, sort
of, you know, making you
feel comfortable.
It's really both in some sense
or neither in some sense.
OK, there's a more general point
about the structure of
the system as creating a
language, viewing the
engineering design process as
one of creating language or
rather one of creating
a sort of sequence
of layers of language.
You see, there's this
methodology, or maybe I should
say mythology, that's, sort
of, charitably called
software, quote, engineering.
All right, and what does it say,
it's says well, you go
and you figure out your task,
and you figure out exactly
what you want to do.
And once you figure out exactly
what you want to do,
you find out that it breaks out
into three sub-tasks, and
you go and you start working
on-- and you work on this
sub-task, and you figure out
exactly what that is.
And you find out that that
breaks down into three
sub-tasks, and you specify them
completely, and you go
and you work on those two, and
you work on this sub-one, and
you specify that exactly.
And then finally when you're
done, you come back way up
here, and you work on your
second sub-task, and specify
that out and work it out.
And then you end up with--
you end up at the end with
this beautiful edifice.
Right, you end up with a
marvelous tree, where you've
broken your task into sub-tasks
and broken each of
these into sub-tasks
and broken those
into sub-tasks, right.
And each of these nodes is
exactly and precisely defined
to do the wonderful, beautiful
task to make it fit into the
whole edifice, right.
That's this mythology.
See only a computer scientist
could possibly believe that
you build a complex system
like that, right.
Contrast that with this
Henderson example.
It didn't work like that.
What happened was that
there was a sequence
of layers of language.
What happened?
There was a layer of a thing
that allowed us to build
primitive pictures.
There's primitive pictures
and that was a language.
I didn't say much about it.
We talked about how to construct
George, but that was
a language where you talked
about vectors and line
segments and points and where
they sat in the unit square.
And then on top of that,
right, on top of that--
so this is the language
of primitive pictures.
Right, talking about line
segments in particular
pictures in the unit square.
On top of that was
a whole language.
There was a language of
geometric combinators, a
language of geometric positions,
which talks about
things like Above and Beside
and right-push and Rotate.
And those things, sort of,
happened with reference to the
things that are talked about
in this language.
And then if we like, we saw that
above that there was sort
of a language of schemes
of combination.
For example, push, which talked
about repeatedly doing
something over with
a scale factor.
And the things that were being
discussed in that language
were, sort of, the things
that happened down here.
So what you have is, at each
level, the objects that are
being talked about are the
things that were erected at
the previous level.
What's the difference between
this thing and this thing?
The answer is that over here in
the tree, each node, and in
fact, each decomposition down
here, is being designed to do
a specific task, whereas in
the other scheme, what you
have is a full range
of linguistic
power at each level.
See what's happening there, at
any level, it's not being set
up to do a particular task.
It's being set up to talk about
a whole range of things.
The consequence of that for
design is that something
that's designed in that method
is likely to be more robust,
where by robust, I mean that if
you go and make some change
in your description, it's more
likely to be captured by a
corresponding change, in the
way that the language is
implemented at the next level
up, right, because you've made
these levels full.
So you're not talking about a
particular thing like Beside.
You've given yourself a whole
vocabulary to express things
of that sort, so if you go and
change your specifications a
little bit, it's more likely
that your methodology will
able to adapt to capture that
change, whereas a design like
this is not going to be robust,
because if I go and
change something that's in here,
that might affect the
entire way that I decomposed
everything down,
further down the tree.
Right, so very big difference
in outlook in decomposition,
levels of language
rather than, sort
of, a strict hierarchy.
Not only that, but when you have
levels of language you've
given yourself a different
vocabularies for talking about
the design at different
levels.
So if we go back and look at
George one last time, if I
wanted to change this picture
George, see suddenly I have a
whole different ways of
describing the change.
Like for example, I may want to
go to the basic primitive
design and move the endpoint
of some vector.
That's a change that I would
discuss at the lowest level.
I would say the endpoint
is somewhere else.
Or I might come up and say, well
the next thing I wanted
to do, this little replicated
element, I might want to do by
something else.
I might want to put a scale
factor in that Beside.
That's a change that I would
discuss at the next level of
design, the level
of combinators.
Or I might want to say, I might
want to change the basic
way that I took this pattern
and made some recursive
decomposition, maybe not
bleeding out toward the
corners or something else.
That would be a change
that I would discuss
at the highest level.
And because I've structured the
system to be this way, I
have all these vocabularies for
talking about change in
different ways and a lot of
flexibility to decide which
one's appropriate.
OK, well that's sort of a big
point about the difference in
software methodology that comes
out from List, and it
all comes, again, out of the
notion that really, the design
process is not so much
implementing programs as
implementing languages.
And that's really the powerful
of List. OK, thank you.
Let's take a break.